<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="147">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01892397</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-067</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01892397</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of NovoTTF-100A for Recurrent Atypical and Anaplastic Meningioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of NovoTTF-100A for Recurrent Atypical and Anaplastic Meningioma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NovoCure Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out what effects, good or bad, the NovoTTF-100A device
      has on the patient and meningioma. This study is being done because currently there are no
      proven effective medical treatments for a progressive meningioma that has failed surgery
      and/or radiation. The study uses an experimental device called NovoTTF-100A. NovoTTF-100A is
      &quot;experimental&quot; because it has not been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration
      (FDA) for this type of tumor, although it has been approved for a different type of tumor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>progression-free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>From the treatment start date to the date of the first observation of progressive disease (including clinical progression) or death due to any cause. Patients not known to be progression-free at 6 months will be considered treatment failures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>From the treatment start date to date of death of any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>graded according to most up-to-date CTCAE version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NovoTTF-100A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment plan is to have patients use the NovoTTF-100A device in monotherapy for &gt; 18 hours per day as per the treatment standard established from prior studies. A medical professional will see each patient at least once per month while on the device for toxicity assessment, compliance evaluation via downloading of the log-file on the device by the Novocure technician (which involves the technician simply attaching the device to a computer via USB where software reads how many hours per day on each day the device was used), and physical examination. Extent of disease evaluations will occur at baseline, 8 weeks, and then every 8 weeks thereafter. These evaluations will include MRI of the brain (or CT head if a patient cannot undergo MRI).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NovoTTF-100A</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>NovoTTF-100A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically proven recurrent WHO grade II (atypical) or grade III (anaplastic)
             intracranial supratentorial meningioma.

          -  Unequivocal evidence for tumor progression by MRI (or CT scan is MRI is
             contraindicated). The scan must be performed within 14 days of registration.

          -  Patients must be on a stable or decreased dose of steroids for at least 5 days prior
             to baseline imaging

          -  Patients with recent resection for recurrent disease must have recovered from the
             effects of surgery and should not start treatment for at least 28 days after surgery.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least 1cm x 1 cm of contrast
             enhancing disease.

          -  Patients must have received prior radiotherapy for meningioma. Patients may have
             received standard external beam radiation, interstitial brachytherapy, or
             radiosurgery in any combination. An interval of &gt; 4 weeks (28 days) must have elapsed
             from the completion of radiotherapy to study entry and there must be subsequent
             evidence of tumor progression. Patients with prior interstitial brachytherapy or
             stereotactic radiosurgery must have confirmation of true progressive disease rather
             than radiation necrosis based on PET, MR-perfusion, MR-spectroscopy, or surgical
             documentation of disease. If there is any question, investigators should discuss with
             the study PI.

          -  Prior therapy: there is no limit on the number of prior surgeries, radiation therapy
             treatments, radiosurgery treatments, or chemotherapy.

          -  All patients must sign an informed consent indicating that they are aware of the
             investigational nature of the study. Patients must sign an authorization for the
             release of their protected health information.

          -  Age &gt; or = to 18 years old

          -  Karnofsky performance status &gt; or = to 60%

          -  4 weeks (28 days) from any radiation treatment, stereotactic radiosurgery,
             conventional surgery, or chemotherapy.

          -  Life expectancy at least 3 months

          -  Patients with NF (Neurofibromatosis) are eligible, and may have other stable CNS
             tumors, such as schwannoma, acoustic neuroma, or ependymoma, but ONLY if these
             lesions have been stable in size for the preceding 6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of any other cancer (except non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma in-situ of the cervix, unless in complete remission and off all therapy for
             the disease for a minimum of 3 years).

          -  Concomitant use of any other investigational drugs.

          -  Concurrent treatment on another clinical trial. Supportive care trials or
             non-treatment trials (i.e. Quality of life) are allowed.

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding. Patients must be surgically sterile, postmenopausal, or
             agree to use effective contraception during the period of therapy. The definition of
             effective contraception will be based on the judgment of the principal investigator
             or a designated associate. Male patients must be surgically sterile or agree to
             effective contraception. Woman of childbearing potential must have a negative B-HCG
             pregnancy test documented within 14 days prior to registration.

          -  Implanted pacemaker, defibrillator, deep brain stimulator, or vagus nerve stimulator,
             or documented significant arrhythmia at the discretion of the investigator.

          -  Evidence of increased intracranial pressure (midline shift &gt;5mm, clinically
             significant papilledema, vomiting and nausea, or reduced level of consciousness).

          -  Infratentorial meningioma (patients may have infratentorial meningioma if there is
             concurrent growing supratentorial meningioma that serves as the target lesion)

          -  Coagulopathy (as evidenced by PT or APTT &gt;1.5 times upper limit of normal in patients
             not undergoing anticoagulation)

          -  Thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt;100x10^3/uL) Neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count
             &lt;1x10^3/uL)

          -  Severe acute infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Kaley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Thomas Kaley, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-5122</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lisa DeAngelis, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-7123</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memoral Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basking Ridge</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Kaley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-5122</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center at Commack</name>
      <address>
        <city>Commack</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11725</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Kaley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-5122</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Kaley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-5122</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lisa DeAngelis, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-7123</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Kaley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 1, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intracranial supratentorial meningioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Atypical and Anaplastic Meningioma</keyword>
  <keyword>NovoTTF-100A</keyword>
  <keyword>13-067</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Meningioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
