<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="397">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01949376</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01NR014182-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01NR014182-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01949376</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mild Cognitive Impairment in Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>HippoPCI</acronym>
  <official_title>Hippocampal Predictors of Cognitive Impairment (HippoPCI) in Breast Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to improve our understanding of differences in size, shape and
      activity of a variety of brain areas that can occur in women with breast cancer undergoing
      adjuvant chemotherapy or hormonal therapy, and how these brain areas are related to the
      development of mild cognitive impairment as the result of these treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to identify neuroimaging biomarkers for predicting mild cognitive impairment
      (MCI) in breast cancer patients receiving adjuvant chemo and/or hormonal therapy by
      examining hippocampal-cortical neurocircuitry. Adjuvant therapies increase long-term
      survival, but produce changes in cognitive function in 30% (up to 70%) of women on average
      with breast cancer. Cognitive decline negatively impacts quality of life in patients and
      their supporters. Therefore, early identification of patients at risk for developing
      treatment-related cognitive impairment is needed to develop potential prevention or
      treatment options and prevent further decline. Our recent work demonstrates that patients
      receiving adjuvant hormonal treatment exhibit decline in cognition as soon as three months
      post treatment. Although neuroimaging studies have identified brain changes associated with
      chemotherapy (&quot;chemo brain&quot;, no investigation has assessed the type and severity of such
      changes following hormonal therapy, nor has any study determined which individuals are at
      greatest risk for cognitive impairment.

      Our central hypothesis is that measures of the hippocampal-cortical integrity can be used to
      predict cognitive decline, and changes of specific domains of cognitive performance in
      patients receiving adjuvant therapy over time will be related to changes in specific
      components of this circuitry over time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of change in cognitive function from baseline to one year</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured using a neuropsychological test battery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of change of brain structure from baseline to one year</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured using structural MRI scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of change of brain function from baseline to one year</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to one year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured using a functional MRI scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CH+ Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>any stage of breast cancer without brain metastasis, has undergone surgery prior to screening, will undergo hormonal therapy with or without chemotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CH- Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>any stage of breast cancer without brain metastasis, has undergone surgery prior to screening, will undergo no therapy or radiation therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CON (Controls)</arm_group_label>
    <description>healthy, cognitively normal subjects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        CON subjects will be recruited from advertisement and through the Northwestern University
        (NU) Cognitive Neurology and Alzheimer's Disease Center (CNADC).

        The CH+ and CH- patients will be recruited from the 3 following sites, through physician
        referral: a) outpatient facility at Galter Pavilion of Northwestern Memorial Hospital; b)
        to Maggie Daley Center for Women's Cancer Care at Prentice Women's Hospital; and c) Lynn
        Sage Comprehensive Breast Cancer Center at Prentice Women's Hospital.

        Additional participants will be recruited (a) through advertisement in local newspapers,
        craigslist, and at community programs that serve cancer patients, including hospitals and
        support groups, and (b) from community educational events sponsored by the Robert H. Lurie
        Comprehensive Cancer Center and the Women's Health Research Institute.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female, within the age range of 40-70

          -  Post-menopausal, or will undergo hormonal therapy.

          -  CH+ patients - any stage of breast cancer without brain metastasis, has undergone
             surgery prior to screening, will undergo hormonal therapy with or without
             chemotherapy.

          -  CH- patients - any stage of breast cancer without brain metastasis, has undergone
             surgery prior to screening, will undergo no therapy or radiation therapy.

          -  CON - cognitively normal on the basis of annual neuropsychological and research
             neurological examinations done as part of the Uniform Data Set (UDS), of the NIA
             Alzheimer's Disease Centers (ADC) program, recruited from the NU CNADC Clinical Core.

          -  All subjects must have given signed, informed consent prior to registration on study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who report significant medical, neurologic, or psychiatric illness,
             including but not limited to:

          -  Major depression

          -  Schizophrenia

          -  ADHD

          -  Autism

          -  Alzheimer's disease

          -  Dementia

          -  Obsessive-compulsive disorder

          -  Post-traumatic stress disorder

          -  Individuals with an Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - Self Report (IDS-SR)
             score of 30 or higher, since this level of depression could affect cognitive test
             performance.

          -  Left-handed individuals, as including this population would muddy MRI brain analysis
             due to differing lateralization of function between right- and left-handed
             individuals

          -  Brain surgery or head injury

               -  Individuals reporting previous head injury

               -  Individuals requiring neurosurgical procedures

          -  Ineligibility for MRI scanning, including but not limited to:

               -  Individuals who have non-MRI compatible medical implants or devices

               -  Individuals who have any potential metal in their bodies

               -  Individuals who have claustrophobia

               -  Individuals with permanent makeup

          -  Individuals reporting consumption of drugs that would affect cognition
             (neuropsychiatric or illicit)

          -  Individuals indicating a history of breast cancer will be excluded from the healthy
             control group

          -  Women entering this study should be post-menopausal.  If, however, a woman becomes
             pregnant after enrolling in the study, she will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lei Wang, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica Berger, LCSW</last_name>
    <phone>312-503-4995</phone>
    <email>jessica.berger1@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Melody Fairchild, M.A.T.</last_name>
    <phone>312-503-7071</phone>
    <email>m-fairchild@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Berger, LCSW</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-4995</phone>
      <email>jessica.berger1@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Melody Fairchild, M.A.T.</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-7071</phone>
      <email>m-fairchild@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lei Wang, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://niacal.northwestern.edu/projects/16</url>
    <description>Hippocampal Predictors of Cognitive Impairment (HippoPCI) in Breast Cancer Patients</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 19, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 19, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lei Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>adjuvant therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>hormone therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>chemo brain</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
