<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="281">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01817751</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-14816</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HM14816</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01817751</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sorafenib Tosylate, Valproic Acid, and Sildenafil Citrate in Treating Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Sorafenib, Valproic Acid, and Sildenafil in the Treatment of Recurrent Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well sorafenib tosylate, valproic acid, and sildenafil
      citrate works in treating patients with recurrent glioblastoma. Sorafenib tosylate, valproic
      acid, and sildenafil citrate may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the
      enzymes needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The combination of sorafenib, valproic acid, and sildenafil may have therapeutic potential
      for the treatment of GBM in the clinic. The combination of sorafenib and valproic acid is
      predicated on the basis that sorafenib activity is enhanced by HDAC inhibition. The addition
      of sildenafil is based on its ability to block ABCB1 and ABCG2 drug efflux pumps. As the
      ABCG2 transporter is the primary transporter involved in the efflux of sorafenib at the BBB,
      blocking its action is predicted to increase the concentration of sorafenib in the brain.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the efficacy of the combination of sorafenib (sorafenib tosylate), valproic acid, and sildenafil (sildenafil citrate), in terms of 6-month progression-free survival (PFS) in glioblastoma (GBM).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier method will be used to describe the time to progression and the median time to progression will be estimated, along with its 95% confidence intervals, for the entire population and for PDGFRa expression, respectively. Cox regression analysis will be used to evaluate baseline characteristics and any potential covariates.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>I. Evaluate the overall response rate, based on Response Assessment in Neuro-Oncology (RANO) criteria, to the drug combination in the entire study population and to the drug combination in PDGFRa expressing tumors.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Will be estimated for the entire study population and for the PDGFRa expressing GBM cohort, along with the 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the efficacy of the drug combination, in terms of 12-month survival and median overall survival in the entire GBM cohort and in the PDGFRa expressing GBM cohort.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier method will be used to describe the time to overall survival and the median time to overall survival will be estimated, and along with its 95% confidence intervals, for the entire population and for PDGFRa expression, respectively. Cox regression analysis will be used to evaluate baseline characteristics and any potential covariates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Nervous System</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate, valproic acid, sildenafil)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive sorafenib tosylate PO, valproic acid* PO, and sildenafil citrate PO BID for 4 weeks. Courses repeat every 4 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
* NOTE: Patients not receiving antiepileptic therapy begin valproic acid 1 week prior to the first day of sorafenib tosylate and sildenafil citrate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sorafenib tosylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate, valproic acid, sildenafil)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pyridinecarboxamide, chloro-trifluoromethylphenyl pyridine-carboxyllic acid methyamide-methylbenzenesulfonate tosylate, Nexavar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>valproic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate, valproic acid, sildenafil)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-Propylpentanoic or Propylvaleric Acid, Alti-Valproic, Depakene, Di-n-propylacetic Acid, Ergenyl, Novo-Valproic, VA, Valproate, Valproate Sodium</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sildenafil citrate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate, valproic acid, sildenafil)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Viagra</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pathologically confirmed GBM, with documented computed tomography (CT) or magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI) progression after first line therapy; biopsy is also an
             acceptable method of confirming progression

          -  Measurable or evaluable disease by RANO criteria

          -  Fixed or decreasing dose of corticosteroids (or no corticosteroids) for at least
             1week prior to registration

          -  At least 12 weeks since the completion of radiation therapy

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1, or 2

          -  White blood cell (WBC) &gt;= 3.0

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5

          -  Platelets &gt;= 80,000

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &gt;= 8.5

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 5 x upper
             institutional limit

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2.5 mg/dl

          -  Creatinine clearance (CrCL) &gt;= 30 as measured by the standard Cockroft-Gault equation

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 3 months

          -  Willingness to use contraception as required

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Investigational agent within 4 weeks or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer, of first
             dose of study treatment

          -  Prior systemic therapy for relapsed GBM

          -  History of coagulopathy

          -  History of allergic reactions or intolerance to any of the required agents on the
             study

          -  Seizure disorder necessitating the use of enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs
             (EIAEDs); efforts may be made by the treating physician to change the antiepileptic
             drug from another agent to valproic acid or non-EIAED prior to excluding the patient
             from study

          -  Contraindication to antiangiogenic agents, including:

               -  Pulmonary hemorrhage/bleeding event &gt;= grade 2 (Common Terminology Criteria for
                  Adverse Events [CTCAE] version 4) within 4 weeks of first dose of study drug

               -  Any other hemorrhage/bleeding event &gt;= grade 3 within 4 weeks of first dose of
                  study treatment

               -  MRI evidence of any intracranial hemorrhage within the past 4 weeks, or prior
                  history of significant intratumoral, intracerebral, or subarachnoid hemorrhage

               -  Serious non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture

          -  Major surgery within 2 weeks of the start of study treatment, or ongoing
             complications from surgeries performed previously

          -  Clinically significant cardiac disease, including major cardiac dysfunction, such as
             uncontrolled angina, clinical congestive heart failure with New York Heart
             Association (NYHA) class III or higher, ventricular arrhythmias requiring
             antiarrhythmic therapy

          -  Systolic blood pressure &gt; 160 mm Hg or diastolic pressure &gt; 100 mm Hg despite optimal
             medical management

          -  History of priapism

          -  Known history of retinitis pigmentosa

          -  Arterial thromboembolic events less than 6 months prior to first study treatment

          -  Serious uncontrolled infection &gt; grade 2

          -  Patient with known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positivity

          -  Unable to swallow medication or suspected malabsorption

          -  Patients on chronic nitrate therapy or alpha-blockers

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing

          -  Baseline corrected QT (QTc) &gt; 500 msec, on screening electrocardiogram (EKG)

          -  Other condition(s) that in the opinion of the investigator might compromise the
             objectives of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Asadullah Khan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virginia Commonwealth University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Diane Holdford, RN</last_name>
    <phone>804-828-0296</phone>
    <email>djholdfo@vcu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diane Holdford, RN</last_name>
      <phone>804-828-0296</phone>
      <email>djholdfo@vcu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Asadullah Khan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 20, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adult giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult brain tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Valproic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sildenafil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Citric Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
