<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="41">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01651078</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LAASR01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01651078</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laser Ablation After Stereotactic Radiosurgery for Patients With Metastatic Brain Tumors.</brief_title>
  <acronym>LAASR</acronym>
  <official_title>Laser Ablation After Stereotactic Radiosurgery. A Post-Marketing Surveillance (Phase IV) Multicenter Observational Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Monteris Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Monteris Medical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The need for new technologies and devices in the field of neurosurgery is well-established.
      In addition to the advanced engineering and medical aspects of a newly available medical
      device, the adoption and incorporation of such a device into healthcare organizations
      greatly influences it's impact on patients.  As the FDA cleared NeuroBlate™ System (formerly
      called AutoLITT®; a minimally invasive neurosurgical device) is a new to the marketplace,
      there is limited experience as to how such a system is best used by healthcare
      organizations.  This (a) post-marketing, multi-site, (b) open-label study involving (c) a
      single cohort of brain tumor patients that undergo routine NeuroBlate procedures is aimed at
      collecting, in a reasonably controlled fashion, such descriptive information, and comparing
      the collected information on patient Quality of Life (QoL) and healthcare utilization to
      published and historical information.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-surgery, and up to 4 points along 6 mo follow-up</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>FACT-Br Standardized Patient Reporting Instrument will be used to assess changes (relative to baseline) in Quality of Life during 6 month follow-up (post surgery)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2, 4, 12, 26 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Standard clinical MRI scans will be assessed during the follow-up period. Assessment will be for evidence of disease progression and other indicators of treatment effect.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout study (pre-op through 6 mo follow-up)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>CTAE 4 Adverse events will be recorded and analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Utilization of Healthcare Resources</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout study, collected at end of patient involvement.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Various aspects of the clinical and non-clinical services required/utilized by the patient cohort will be collected and analyzed.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Brain Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Progression</condition>
  <condition>Radiation Necrosis</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Main cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients (from normal clinical population) whom are scheduled for NeuroBlate/AutoLITT surgery to treat metastatic brain tumors previously treated with Stereotactic Radiosurgery (SRS), but have developed progression or radiation necrosis of SRS treated tumors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients will have been already, as part of normal clinical practice, schedulled for
        NeuroBlate/AutoLITT based neurosurgery to treat metastatic brain tumors that have
        previously been treated with Stereotactic Radiosurgery (SRS), but have developed either
        progression or radiation necrosis (as assesed by MRI) of the SRS treated tumors.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Up to 3 target supratentorial metastatic lesions (up to 5 cm in maximum dimension
             perpendicular to planned primary trajectory axis) previously treated with SRS, with
             radiological evidence of progression, pseudoprogression or radionecrosis. Subject may
             have up to 5 non target lesions present. Non target lesions must be small (less than
             3 mm) or not expected (in Investigator's judgment) to contribute to symptomology
             during the course of the study or confound interpretation of radiological and
             clinical measures.

          2. Target tissue/tumors treatable with one or two NeuroBlate trajectories per tumor.

          3. Patient and condition amenable to NeuroBlate, but surgery is not preferred (due to
             lack of mass-effect, tumor located in an eloquent region, or circumstances where, in
             the PI-neurosurgeon's judgment, resection could result in long-lasting neurological
             deficits).

          4. Patients with stable systemic primary malignancy.

          5. KPS ≥ 70.

          6. Age &gt;18 years.

          7. Tumor clearly defined on gadolinium enhanced T1 or MP-RAGE, or comparable MRI
             sequence with midline shift &lt; 1 cm.

          8. Minimum interval since last drug therapy:

               1. 2 weeks since last non-cytotoxic therapy,

               2. 3 weeks since last Avastin treatment,

               3. 3 weeks must have elapsed since the completion of a non-nitrosourea containing
                  chemotherapy, and

               4. 6 weeks since the completion of a nitrosourea containing chemotherapy regimen.

          9. Patients must be able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Females who are pregnant or breast feeding.

          2. Leptomeningeal metastases.

          3. Uncontrolled infectious process.

          4. Symptoms due to mass effect of the tumor (with steroid treatment), including marked
             edema, significant midline shift (e.g., &gt; 5 mm) or high intracranial pressure, where
             surgical debulking in the first 30 days post NeuroBlate treatment would be required
             for therapy.

          5. Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic &gt;180 mm Hg), angina pectoris, or cardiac
             dysrhythmia, or recent (within 6 weeks) history of intracranial hemorrhage.

          6. Serious infection, immunosuppression or concurrent medical condition (chronic or
             acute in nature) that may prevent safe participation or ability to meet follow-up
             requirements.

          7. Abnormal absolute neutrophil count (ANC&lt;1500/mm3), or PT and aPTT (&gt;1.5x
             institutional upper limit), platelets (&lt;100,000/mm3) or hemoglobin (&lt;10 gm/dL), or
             the administration of antiplatelet agents within 7 days prior to treatment.

          8. Inadequate bone marrow, liver and renal function (e.g., total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN;
             AST, ALT &gt; 2.5 x ULN; alkaline phosphatase &gt; 2.5 x ULN; serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 x
             ULN).

          9. Patients whose physical dimensions cannot be accommodated in the MRI scanner or
             patients with contraindications to MRI imaging such as pacemakers, non-compatible
             aneurysm clips, shrapnel and other internal ferromagnetic objects.

         10. Other concurrent medical or other condition (chronic or acute in nature) that in the
             opinion of the investigator may prevent safe participation or otherwise render this
             patient ineligible for the study.

         11. Patients with treatable tumors (those of the size described in the first Inclusion
             Criterion) involving the posterior fossa (brainstem and cerebellum) will be excluded
             as will patients where the anticipated treatment margin will be within 5 mm of
             critical intracranial structures (e.g., primary branches of cerebral vessels, dural
             sinuses, hypophysis or cranial nerves).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gene H. Barnett, MD, MBA, FACS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gene H. Barnett, MD</last_name>
      <phone>216.445.1379</phone>
      <email>barnetg@ccf.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gene H. Barnett, MD, MBA, FACS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 26, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 24, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Brain Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Progression</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation Necrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Necrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
