<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="117">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01454596</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110266</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-C-0266</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01454596</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>White Blood Cells With Anti-EGFR-III for Malignant Gliomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of the Safety and Feasibility of Administering T Cells Expressing Anti-EGFRvIII Chimeric Antigen Receptor to Patients With Malignant Gliomas Expressing EGFRvIII</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - A new cancer treatment involves collecting white blood cells from a patient, modifying
      them to act against the cancer, and returning them to the body. The white blood cells may
      then be able to identify and destroy the cancer cells. Some kinds of advanced gliomas
      contain a protein called EGFR, which is not present in normal tissues. Doctors want to
      modify white blood cells to have an anti-EGFR effect, and use them to treat the glioma.

      Objectives:

      - To see if anti-EGFR white blood cells are a safe and effective treatment for advanced
      gliomas.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals greater than or equal to 18 years of age and less than or equal to 66 years of
      age who have a malignant glioma that has not responded to standard treatments.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a medical history and physical exam. They will also
           have blood tests and imaging studies.

        -  Participants will have leukapheresis about a month before the treatment to collect
           white blood cells.

        -  They will have chemotherapy 1 week before the treatment to prepare the body for the
           anti-EGFR cells.

        -  The anti-EGFR cells will be given as an infusion. Interleukin-2 will be given along
           with the cells to help boost the immune system's response. It will be given every 8
           hours for up to 15 doses.

        -  Participants will be monitored in the hospital with blood tests and other studies
           during their recovery from treatment.

        -  Participants will have regular followup exams with blood tests, imaging studies, and
           other exams every 1 to 6 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      - Patients with recurrent gliomas have very limited treatment options. EGFR variant III

      (EGFRvIII) is the most common mutant variant of EGFR and is present in 24-67% of patients
      with glioblastoma.

        -  EGFRvIII expression promotes oncogenesis and is associated with poor prognosis.

        -  EGFRvIII is not expressed in normal tissue and is an attractive target for
           immunotherapy.

        -  We have constructed a retroviral vector that contains a chimeric antigen receptor (CAR)
           that recognizes the EGFRvIII tumor antigen, which can be used to mediate genetic
           transfer of this CAR with high efficiency without the need to perform any selection.

      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary Objectives

        -  To evaluate the safety of the administration of anti-EGFRvIII CAR engineered peripheral
           blood lymphocytes in patients receiving the non-myeloablative conditioning regimen, and
           aldesleukin

        -  Determine the six month progression free survival of patients receiving anti-EGFRvIII
           CAR-engineered peripheral blood lymphocytes and aldesleukin following a
           nonmyeloablative but lymphoid depleting preparative regimen.

      Secondary objectives

        -  Determine the in vivo survival of CAR gene-engineered cells.

        -  Evaluate radiographic changes after treatment

      ELIGIBILITY:

        -  Histologically proven glioblastoma or glisarcoma expressing EGFRvIII as determined by
           IHC or RT-PCR

        -  Failed prior standard treatment with radiotherapy with or without chemotherapy

        -  Karnofsky score greater than or equal to 60%

        -  Cardiac, pulmonary and laboratory parameters within acceptable limits

      DESIGN:

        -  The study will be conducted using a Phase I/II design.

        -  Patients will be accrued to both the phase I and phase II portion of the trial in two
           groups:

        -  patients with recurrent malignant glioma requiring steroid use at the start of
           treatment

        -  patients with recurrent malignant glioma not requiring steroids at the start of
           treatment.

        -  Patients will receive a non-myeloablative but lymphocyte depleting preparative regimen
           consisting of cyclophosphamide and fludarabine followed by intravenous infusion of ex
           vivo tumor reactive, CAR gene-transduced PBMC, plus IV aldesleukin.

        -  Once the MTD has been determined for each individual group in the phase I portion of
           the trial, the study will proceed to the phase II portion.

        -  Patients will again be accrued to the same two groups. For each of the 2 groups
           evaluated, the study will be conducted using a single stage phase II design.

        -  A total of 160 patients may be enrolled over a period of 7 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and the six month progression free survival in patients administered anti-EGFRlll CAR engineered peripheral blood lymphocytes, the non-myeloablative conditioning regimen, and aldesleukin.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the in vivo survival of CAR gene-engineered cells.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate radiographic changes after treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Brain Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-EGFRvIII CAR (PG13-139-CD8-CD28BBZ (F10) transduced PBL</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aldesleukin</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Patients with histologically proven glioblastomas or gliosarcomas that express
             EGFRvIII as assessed by IHC or PCR.

          2. Patients must have progression of disease after radiotherapy (including patients that
             undergo surgery for recurrent disease and are rendered NED). This includes recurrent
             GBM after receiving all standard first-line treatment, including surgery (if feasible
             due to neurosurgical and neuro-anatomical considerations) and adjuvant radiotherapy
             +/- chemotherapy.

          3. Patients must either not be receiving steroids, or be on a stable dose of steroids
             for at least five days prior to registration.

          4. Patients must be greater than or equal to 18 years of age and less than or equal to
             age 66, and must have a life expectancy &gt;  8 weeks

          5. Patients must be able to understand and sign the Informed Consent Document

          6. Must be willing to sign a durable power of attorney.

          7. Patients must have a Karnofsky performance status of greater than or equal to 60

          8. Patients of both genders must be willing to practice birth control for four months
             following the preparative regimen.

          9. Women of child bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the preparative chemotherapy on the fetus.

         10. Serology:

               -  Seronegative for HIV antibody. (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
                  this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who are HIV
                  seropositive can have decreased immune-competence and thus be less responsive to
                  the experimental treatment and more susceptible to its toxicities.)

               -  Seronegative for hepatitis B antigen, and seronegative for hepatitis C antibody
                  unless antigen negative.  If hepatitis C antibody test is positive, then
                  patients must be tested for the presence of antigen by RT-PCR and be HCV RNA
                  negative.

         11. Hematology

               -  WBC greater than or equal to 3000/mm(3)

               -  ANC greater than or equal to 1000/mm(3) without the support of filgrastim

               -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm(3)

               -  Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 8.0 g/dl (eligibility level for hemoglobin
                  may be reached by transfusion)

         12. Chemistry:

               -  ALT/AST less than or equal to to 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Creatinine less than or equal to to 1.6 mg/dl

               -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to to 1.5 mg/dl, except in patients with
                  Gilbert's Syndrome who must have a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dl.

         13. Patients must be at least 4 weeks from radiation therapy. Additionally, patients must
             be at least 6 weeks from nitrosoureas, 4 weeks from temozolomide, 3 weeks from
             procarbazine, 2 weeks from vincristine and 4 weeks from last bevacizumab
             administration. Patients must be at least 4 weeks from other cytotoxic therapies not
             listed above and 2 weeks for non-cytotoxic agents (e.g., interferon, tamoxifen)
             including investigative agents. All toxicities from prior therapies should be
             resolved to CTCAE less than or equal to grade 1 (except for toxicities such as
             alopecia, or vitiligo).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. A prior history of gliadel implantation in the past six months..

          2. Women who are currently pregnant or breast feeding because of the potentially
             dangerous effects of the preparative regimen on the fetus or infant.

          3. Active systemic infections, coagulation disorders or other major medical illnesses
             including those of the cardiovascular, respiratory or immune system, myocardial
             infarction, cardiac arrhythmias, obstructive/restrictive pulmonary disease.

          4. Any form of primary immunodeficiency (such as Severe Combined Immunodeficiency
             Disease).

          5. Concurrent opportunistic infections (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
             this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who have decreased immune
             competence may be less responsive to the experimental treatment and more susceptible
             to its toxicities).

          6. History of severe immediate hypersensitivity to any of the agents including

             cyclophosphamide, fludarabine, or aldesleukin.

          7. History of coronary revascularization or ischemic symptoms.

          8. Clinically significant hemorrhagic or ischemic stroke, including transient ischemic
             attacks and other central nervous system bleeding in the preceding 6 months that were
             not related to glioma surgery. History of prior intratumoral bleeding is not an
             exclusion criteria; patients who with history of prior intratumoral bleeding,
             however, need to undergo a non-contrast head CT to exclude acute bleeding.

          9. Other concomitant anti-cancer therapy except corticosteroids.

         10. Any patient known to have an LVEF less than or equal to 45%.

         11. Documented FEV1 less than or equal to 60% predicted tested in patients with:

               -  A prolonged history of cigarette smoking (20 pk/year of smoking within thepast 2
                  years).

               -  Symptoms of respiratory dysfunction
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>66 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven A Rosenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>June Kryk, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-1929</phone>
    <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact NCI/Surgery Branch Recruitment Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-820-4505</phone>
      <email>ncisbirc@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2011-C-0266.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>FRANKEL SA, GERMAN WJ. Glioblastoma multiforme; review of 219 cases with regard to natural history, pathology, diagnostic methods, and treatment. J Neurosurg. 1958 Sep;15(5):489-503. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>13576192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stupp R, Mason WP, van den Bent MJ, Weller M, Fisher B, Taphoorn MJ, Belanger K, Brandes AA, Marosi C, Bogdahn U, Curschmann J, Janzer RC, Ludwin SK, Gorlia T, Allgeier A, Lacombe D, Cairncross JG, Eisenhauer E, Mirimanoff RO; European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Brain Tumor and Radiotherapy Groups; National Cancer Institute of Canada Clinical Trials Group. Radiotherapy plus concomitant and adjuvant temozolomide for glioblastoma. N Engl J Med. 2005 Mar 10;352(10):987-96.</citation>
    <PMID>15758009</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Murray T, Xu J, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2007. CA Cancer J Clin. 2007 Jan-Feb;57(1):43-66.</citation>
    <PMID>17237035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 6, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine monophosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
