<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="431">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01540799</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pathway M-1 (CIP-003)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01540799</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pathway M-1: Sphenopalatine Ganglion Stimulation for the Treatment of Chronic or High Frequency, High Disability Migraine Headache</brief_title>
  <acronym>Pathway M-1</acronym>
  <official_title>Pathway M-1: Sphenopalatine Ganglion Stimulation for the Treatment of Chronic or High Frequency, High Disability Migraine Headache</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Autonomic Technologies, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Autonomic Technologies, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Denmark: Danish Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the clinical study is to evaluate the use of an implanted sphenopalatine
      ganglion (SPG) neurostimulator for the treatment of migraine headache pain, migraine
      headache symptoms and migraine frequency in high disability migraineurs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Single Blind (Subject), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Device- and Surgical-Related Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Implantation through completion of Experimental Period (between 14 and 22 weeks following the implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Occurrence rate of death, any surgery or hospitalization due to deterioration in subject health, or other Major Device-related Adverse Events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effective Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Through completion of Experimental Period (between 14 and 22 weeks following the implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference between the number of Migraine Pain Days during the last 4 weeks of the Baseline Period and the number of Migraine Pain Days during the last 4 weeks of the Experimental Period.
Migraine Pain Day: Any day with
moderate or severe headache with a duration of at least 1 hour AND meeting criteria C and D for migraine ICHD-II 1.1 OR
Acute Medication (pharmacologic medications, not including SPG stimulation, used to treat migraine pain) use for a migraine attack (of any severity or duration).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache Frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Through completion of Experimental Period (between 14 and 22 weeks following the implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Difference between the total number of Migraine Pain Days during the last 4 weeks of the Baseline Period and the total number of Migraine Pain Days including days where SPG stimulation was used for a migraine attack (of any severity or duration) during the last 4 weeks of the Experimental Period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Relief at 1 Hour</measure>
    <time_frame>Experimental Period (begins between 8 and 16 weeks following implantation procedure; ends between 14 and 22 weeks following implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of migraine pain treatments using SPG stimulation during the Experimental Period with Pain Relief at 1 hour following the start of SPG stimulation with no Acute Medication use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Freedom at 1 Hour</measure>
    <time_frame>Experimental Period (begins between 8 and 16 weeks following implantation procedure; ends between 14 and 22 weeks following implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of migraine pain treatments using SPG stimulation during the Experimental Period with Pain Freedom at 1 hour following the start of SPG stimulation with no Acute Medication use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Migraine Associated Symptom Relief at 1 Hour</measure>
    <time_frame>Experimental Period (begins between 8 and 16 weeks following implantation procedure; ends between 14 and 22 weeks following implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of migraine pain treatments using SPG stimulation during the Experimental Period with relief of migraine associated symptoms [i.e., photophobia, phonophobia, nausea/vomiting] at 1 hour following the start of SPG stimulation with no Acute Medication use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disability and Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Experimental Period (assessment occurs between 14 and 22 weeks following the implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disability and Quality of Life as categorized by the HIT-6, MIDAS and SF-36v2 surveys administered at the end of the Experimental Period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Evaluation of SPG Stimulation Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Experimental Period (assessment occurs between 14 and 22 weeks following the implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Global patient evaluation of SPG stimulation therapy (very poor, poor, no opinion, good, very good) administered at the end of the Experimental Period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prophylactic Medication Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Open Label Period (one year following the implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Use of prophylactic medications during the Open Label Period as compared to Baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute Medication Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Open Label Period (one year following the implantation procedure)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Use of acute medication during the Experimental and/or Open Label Periods as compared to Baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Migraine</condition>
  <condition>High Frequency, High Disability Migraine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Other</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stimulation not able to be felt</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ATI Neurostimulation System</intervention_name>
    <description>ATI Neurostimulator (NS-100) and Remote Controller (RC-200)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Other</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age from &gt;= 18 years old.

          -  Subject has been diagnosed with migraine headache with or without aura according to
             the 2004 ICHD-II criteria 1.1 or 1.2.1 or chronic migraine according to 2006 ICHD-IIR
             Appendix 1.5.1 .

          -  Subject reports at least 75% of migraine attacks having predominantly fixed (non
             side-shifting) unilateral temporal or ocular pain, with a preference that the subject
             reports associated cranial autonomic symptoms.

          -  Subject reports a minimum of 8 days per month with migraine attacks of at least
             moderate severity based on the subject/Investigator's knowledge for at least 3 months
             prior to inclusion and confirmed in a diary for at least 1 month (4 weeks) prior to
             inclusion.

          -  Subject reports a minimum of 4 migraine attacks per month.

          -  Subject reports at least 24 hours of pain free periods between typical migraine
             attacks, and at least 4 migraine-free days per month.

          -  Subject has a MIDAS score of III or IV, or has a HIT-6 score &gt; 56.

          -  Subject is medically intractable in the opinion of the Investigator.

          -  Subject has had stable type and dosage of prophylactic headache medications for at
             least 1 month prior to study enrollment and agrees to maintain stable type and dosage
             of prophylactic headache medications through the completion of the Experimental
             Period.

          -  Subject is able to distinguish migraine attacks from other headaches (i.e., TTH).

          -  Subject agrees to not participate in supplemental or alternative therapy during the
             study.  This includes: acupuncture, spinal manipulation, TENS, and magnetic fields
             treatments.

          -  Subject has the ability to read, comprehend, and to reliably record information as
             required by the Protocol.

          -  Subject is able to provide written informed consent prior to participation in the
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject's overall health, age and/or comorbidities place subject at high risk for
             complications from surgery and/or general anesthesia.

          -  Subject currently has Medication Overuse Headache (MOH) according to the ICHD-IIR
             2006 criteria.

          -  Subject reports continuous daily headaches for one month or longer at time of
             consent.

          -  Subject reports initial onset of migraines within the last year.

          -  Subject has undergone facial surgery in the area of the pterygopalatine fossa or
             zygomaticomaxillary buttress ipsilateral to the planned implant site that, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, may lead to the inability to properly implant the
             Neurostimulator.

          -  Subject has active oral or dental abscess.

          -  Subject has been treated with radiation to the facial region.

          -  Subject has been diagnosed with any major infectious processes such as osteomyelitis,
             or primary or secondary malignancies involving the face that have been active or
             required treatment in the past 6 months or requires periodic MRI follow-up.

          -  Subject's pterygomaxillary fissure is less than 1.2 mm in width at the level of the
             vidian canal, as determined by CT scan.

          -  Subject has clinically significant drug (including opioid) or alcohol abuse as
             defined by DSM-IV-TR, will likely be unable to refrain from substance abuse
             throughout the study, has other significant pain problem, substance abuse or active
             depressive episode that might confound the study assessments in the opinion of the
             Investigator.

          -  Subject is currently participating or has participated in the last month in another
             clinical study in which the subject has, is, or will be exposed to an investigational
             drug or device.

          -  Subject is felt to be at risk of non-compliance (e.g., for completing the diary or
             maintaining a stable headache medicine regimen or returning for required follow-up
             visits) in the Investigator's opinion.

          -  Subject is a woman of childbearing age who is pregnant, nursing, or not using
             contraception.

          -  Subject has had previous lesional radiofrequency ablation of the ipsilateral
             sphenopalatine ganglion (SPG).

          -  Subject has had blocks or nonlesional pulsed RF of the ipsilateral SPG in the last 3
             months.

          -  Subject has undergone botulinium toxin injections of the head and/or neck in the last
             3 months.

          -  Subject has or requires a pacemaker/defibrillator or other implantable device having
             a sense amplifier that is programmed 'On.'

          -  Subject has a history of bleeding disorders or coagulopathy or is unable to
             discontinue anticoagulation, antiplatelet, or GP IIb IIIa inhibitor medication in
             preparation for the implantation procedure.

          -  Subject is not suitable for the study for any reason in the judgment of the
             Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rigmor Jensen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Danish Headache Center, Glostrup Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Headache Research Unit. University Department of Neurology, Citadelle Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liege</city>
        <zip>B-4000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pascale Gerard</last_name>
      <phone>+32 4 225 6391</phone>
      <email>pascale.gerard@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean Schoenen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Delphine Magis, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Danish Headache Center &amp; Department of Neurology, Glostrup Hospital, University of Copenhagen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glostrup</city>
        <state>Copenhagen</state>
        <zip>DK-2600</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Messoud Ashina, MD, PhD, Dr.Med.Sci.</last_name>
      <phone>Tel: +45 4338632062</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Messoud Ashina, MD, PhD, Dr.Med.Sci.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servicio de Neurologia, Hospital Clinico Universitario</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Miguel JA Lainez, MD, PhD, FAAN, CMANA</last_name>
      <phone>+34 963868863</phone>
      <email>neurologia_hcv@gva.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose Miguel Lainez, MD, PhD, FAAN, CMANA</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Garcia, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 3, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 20, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Migraine</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic migraine</keyword>
  <keyword>High frequency migraine</keyword>
  <keyword>High disability migraine</keyword>
  <keyword>Sphenopalatine ganglion</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuromodulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurostimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Autonomic nervous system</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Synovial Cyst</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ganglion Cysts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
