<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="271">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00995007</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>090222</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>09-C-0222</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00995007</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Phase II Trial of Vandetanib (ZD6474) in Combination With Carboplatin Versus Carboplatin Alone Followed by Vandetanib Alone in Adults With Recurrent High-Grade Gliomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II Trial of Vandetanib (ZD6474) in Combination With Carboplatin Versus Carboplatin Alone Followed by Vandetanib Alone in Adults With Recurrent High-Grade Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Growth of new blood vessels (angiogenesis) provides many tumors, including brain
           tumors, with needed nutrients and oxygen for cancer cells to survive. One possible
           treatment for different kinds of cancer involves treatment with drugs that slow or stop
           angiogenesis and prevent further tumor growth.

        -  Vandetanib is an oral medication known to block angiogenesis and has shown significant
           antitumor activity in laboratory and animal studies. Vandetanib appears to be well
           tolerated by patients at specific daily doses.

        -  Carboplatin is a drug that interrupts division of cancer cells and has been shown to be
           a useful drug in treatment of tumors known as gliomas. It is a useful drug for treating
           brain tumors, but researchers are interested in gathering more information about how it
           works as a treatment for patients who have not responded to initial surgery, radiation,
           or chemotherapy.

      Objective:

      - To determine the safety and effectiveness of vandetanib and carboplatin, given together or
      sequentially, against recurrent high-grade gliomas.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults diagnosed with a malignant glioma who have received standard treatments that no
      longer appear to be effective.

      Design:

        -  Patients will be assigned to one of two groups. Group 1 patients (combination group)
           will receive oral vandetanib for 28 days and intravenous (IV) carboplatin (once at the
           beginning of the 28-day cycle). Group 2 patients (sequential group) will receive IV
           carboplatin alone (once at the beginning of the 28-day cycle) and then oral vandetanib
           (300 mg daily) for 28 days if the tumor grows or the patient develops unacceptable
           carboplatin toxicity.

        -  Treatment will continue in 28-day cycles for 1 year for both groups.

        -  Patients will undergo a number of tests and procedures during the treatment cycle,
           including physical examinations, routine laboratory tests, electrocardiograms, and
           magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans

        -  At the end of 1 year of treatment, patients will be reevaluated for possible
           continuation of drug therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      In vivo experiments have documented the ability of vandetanib (ZD6474) to inhibit tumor
      growth in various preclinical tumor models. Given the pronounced neovasculature associated
      with malignant gliomas, and abundant published data demonstrating the dependence of glioma
      growth on the maintenance and proliferation of this neovasculature, vandetanib represents a
      potentially promising new therapeutic approach to these otherwise refractory tumors. Phase
      II data of vandetanib for recurrent glioblastomas conducted at the National Institutes of
      Health showed promising activity but responses were usually short-lasting.

      Carboplatin has shown activity as monotherapy in the treatment of recurrent malignant
      gliomas in adults and preclinical data generated at Dr. Fine's laboratory demonstrate
      additive anti-glioma activity with vandetanib. The safety profile of carboplatin and the
      preclinical and clinical data supports its use in combination with vandetanib in patients
      with malignant gliomas.

      Vandetanib is also an EGFR inhibitor and it has been demonstrated that the presence of the
      EGFRvIII mutant and/or the presence of an intact PTEN and non-phosphorylated AKT predict for
      a higher likelihood of response to the EGFR inhibitors Tarceva and Iressa.

      Objectives:

      To establish data regarding the anti-tumor activity of vandetanib in combination with
      carboplatin and single agent carboplatin and to collect information regarding the spectrum
      of toxicities.

      To determine if the presence of the EGFRvIII mutant and/or the presence of an intact PTEN
      and non-phosphorylated AKT predict for a higher likelihood of response to vandetanib.

      Eligibility:

      Patients with histologically proven malignant glioma are eligible for this study.

      Design:

      Patients will be randomized (1:1) to one of two groups. Patients in group one will be
      treated with vandetanib (300 mg daily for patients not on enzyme inducing anti-epileptic
      drugs (EIAEDs) and 400 mg daily for patients on EIAEDs) and with carboplatin (area under the
      concentration-time curve at steady-state [AUC], 6mg/mL x min) once every 4-week cycle (
      combination group ). Patients in group two will receive carboplatin alone (AUC 6mg/mL x min)
      once every 4-week cycle. Patients who develop tumor progression or unacceptable toxicity on
      carboplatin alone (group 2) can then receive single agent vandetanib (300 mg daily for
      patients not on enzyme inducing anti-epileptic drugs (EIAEDs) and 400 mg daily for patients
      on EIAEDs) in 4-week cycles ( sequential group ). A total of 128 evaluable patients will be
      analyzed. The total accrual ceiling will allow for 74 patients to be enrolled in the GBM
      stratum and 74 patients in the AG stratum (total 148) to factor in replacing those patients
      who come off treatment prior to cycle 1.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To establish data regarding the anti-tumor activity of the combination of vandetanib with carboplatin or carboplatin alone in patients with recurrent high-grade gliomas not taking enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drugs (EIAEDs).</measure>
    <time_frame>+/- 1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To obtain information regarding the spectrum of toxicities of vandetanib with carboplatin or carboplatin alone administered to patients with recurrent high-grade gliomas not taking EIAEDs.</measure>
    <time_frame>+/- 1.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">148</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <condition>Gliosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Oligodendroglioma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Mixed Oligoastrocytoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combo Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sequential Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ZD6474</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients with histologically proven malignant primary gliomas who have progressive disease
        after radiotherapy will be eligible for this protocol.  These include glioblastoma
        multiforme (GBM), gliosarcoma, anaplastic astrocytoma (AA), anaplastic oligodendroglioma
        (AO), anaplastic mixed oligoastrocytoma (AMO), and malignant glioma/astrocytoma NOS.

        Patients must have an MRI/CT scan performed within 14 days prior to registration and on a
        fixed dose of steroids for at least 5 days. If the steroid dose is increased between the
        date of imaging and registration a new baseline MR/CT is required.  The same type of scan,
        that is, MRI or CT must be used throughout the period of protocol treatment for tumor
        measurement.

        Patients having undergone recent resection of recurrent or progressive tumor will be
        eligible as long as all of the following conditions apply:

        Patients will be eligible four weeks after surgery if they have recovered from the effects
        of surgery.

        Residual disease following resection of recurrent tumor is not mandated for eligibility
        into the study.  To best assess the extent of residual disease post-operatively, a CT/MRI
        should be done:

          -  no later than 96 hours in the immediate post-operative period or

          -  at least 4 weeks post-operatively, and

          -  within 14 days of registration, and

          -  on a steroid dosage that has been stable for at least 5 days.

        If the 96 hour scan is more than 14 days before registration, the scan needs to be
        repeated.  If the steroid dose is increased between the date of imaging and registration,
        a new baseline MRI/CT is required on a stable steroid dosage for at least 5 days.

        Patients must have failed prior radiation therapy.

        All patients or their previously designated DPA (if the patient is deemed by the treating
        physician to be cognitively impaired or questionably impaired in such a way that the
        ability of the patient to give informed consent is questionable) must sign an informed
        consent indicating that they are aware of the investigational nature of this study.

        Patients must be greater than or equal to 18 years old, and must have a life expectancy
        greater than 8 weeks.

        Patients must have a Karnofsky performance status of greater than or equal to 60.

        Patients must be at least six weeks from radiation therapy. Additionally, patients must be
        at least 6 weeks from nitrosoureas, 4 weeks from temozolomide, 3 weeks from procarbazine,
        and 2 weeks from last vincristine administration.  Patients must be at least 4 weeks from
        other cytotoxic therapies not listed above and 2 weeks for non-cytotoxic agents (e.g.,
        interferon, tamoxifen) including investigative agents.

        Patients must have adequate bone marrow function (WBC greater than or equal to
        3,000/microL, ANC greater than or equal to 1,500/mm(3), platelet count of greater than or
        equal to 100,000/mm(3), and hemoglobin greater than or equal to 10 gm/dl), adequate liver
        function (AST, ALT and alkaline phosphatase 2.5 less than or equal to ULN and bilirubin
        less than or equal to 1.5 times ULN), and adequate renal function (creatinine less than or
        equal to 1.5 mg/dL and/or creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 60 cc/min) before
        starting therapy. Patients must also have serum potassium greater than or equal to 3.5
        mg/dL, magnesium greater than or equal to 0.75 mmol/L and calcium levels within normal
        levels; supplementation is allowed. In cases where the serum calcium is below the normal
        range, 2 options would be available:  1) the calcium adjusted for albumin is to be
        obtained and substituted for the measured serum value.  Exclusion is to then be based on
        the adjusted for albumin values falling below the normal limit.  2) Determine the ionized
        calcium levels.  Exclusion is then to be based if these ionized calcium levels are out of
        normal range despite supplementation. These tests must be performed within 14 days prior
        to registration.  Eligibility level for hemoglobin may be reached by transfusion.

        Patients must either not be receiving steroids, or be on a stable dose of steroids for at
        least five days prior to registration.

        This study was designed to include women and minorities, but was not designed to measure
        differences of intervention effects.  Males and females will be recruited with no
        preference to gender.  No exclusion to this study will be based on race.  Minorities will
        actively be recruited to participate.

        Patients must not be pregnant or nursing, and all patients (both men and women) must be
        willing to practice birth control during and for 2 months after treatment with vandetanib
        and/or carboplatin. Women of childbearing potential (WCBP) must have a negative serum or
        urine pregnancy test.  In addition, WCBP patients must agree to use adequate contraceptive
        methods (oral, injectable, or implantable hormonal contraceptive; tubal ligation;
        intra-uterine device; barrier contraceptive with spermicide; or vasectomized partner).

        A 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG) to be performed within 2 weeks of trial entry with QTc
        less than 480 msec.  If a patient has a QTcB interval &gt; 480 ms on screening ECG, the
        screening ECG may be repeated twice [at least 24 hours apart] for a total of 3 ECGs. The
        average QTcB from the 3 screening ECGs must be less than or equal to 480 ms in order for
        the patient to be eligible for the study).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients who, in the view of the treating physician, have significant active hepatic,
        renal, or psychiatric diseases are ineligible.

        Prior treatment with vandetanib.

        Prior treatment with platinum-based therapy.

        Patients known to have an allergic response to mannitol.

        Clinically significant cardiovascular event (e.g. myocardial infarction, superior vena
        cava syndrome (SVC), New York Heart Association (NYHA) classification of heart disease
        greater than or equal to 2 within 3 months before entry; or presence of cardiac disease
        that, in the opinion of the investigator, increases the risk of ventricular arrhythmia.

        History of arrhythmia (multifocal premature ventricular contractions PVCs), bigeminy,
        trigeminy, ventricular tachycardia, or uncontrolled atrial fibrillation) which is
        symptomatic or requires treatment (CTCAE grade 3) or asymptomatic sustained ventricular
        tachycardia.  Atrial fibrillation, controlled on medication is not excluded.

        QTc prolongation with other medications that required discontinuation of that medication.

        Congenital long QT syndrome, or 1st degree relative with unexplained sudden death under 40
        years of age.

        Presence of left bundle branch block (LBBB.)

        QTc with Bazett's correction that is unmeasurable, or greater than or equal to 480 msec on
        screening ECG. (Note: If a subject has a QTc interval greater than or equal to 480 msec on
        screening ECG, the screen ECG may be repeated twice (at least 24 hours apart).  The
        average QTc from the three screening ECGs must be less than 480 msec in order for the
        subject to be eligible for the study. Patients who are receiving a drug that has a risk of
        QTc prolongation excluded if QTc is greater than or equal to 460 msec.

        Any concurrent medication that may cause QTc prolongation or induce Torsades de Pointes.
        Drugs listed in Appendix E, Table 2, that in the investigator's opinion cannot be
        discontinued are allowed; however, must be monitored closely.

        Concomitant medications that are potent inducers (rifampicin, rifabutin, St. John's Wort
        and EIAEDs of CYP3A4 function. EIAEDs are allowed.

        Hypertension not controlled by medical therapy (systolic blood pressure greater than 160
        mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 100 mm Hg)

        Currently active diarrhea that may affect the ability of the patient to absorb the
        vandetanib or tolerate diarrhea.

        Women who are currently pregnant or breast feeding.

        Patients known to have a malignancy (other than their malignant glioma) that has required
        treatment in the last 12 months and/or is expected to require treatment in the next 12
        months (except for non-melanoma skin cancer, carcinoma in situ in the cervix or ductal
        carcinoma in situ).

        Invasive procedures defined as follows:

          -  Major surgical procedure, open biopsy or significant traumatic injury within 28 days
             prior to Day 1 therapy

          -  Anticipation of need for major surgical procedures during the course of the study

          -  Core biopsy within 7 days prior to D1 therapy

        Patients should not be on anti-platelet medications (aspirin, clopidogrel, ticlopidine,
        prasugel). Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs should be used with caution if medically
        necessary.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Teri N Kreisl, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tracy Cropper, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-6298</phone>
    <email>tcropper@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Teri N Kreisl, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-3423</phone>
    <email>kreislt@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tracy Cropper, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>301-402-6298</phone>
      <email>tcropper@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2009-C-0222.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prados MD, Schold SC JR SC, Fine HA, Jaeckle K, Hochberg F, Mechtler L, Fetell MR, Phuphanich S, Feun L, Janus TJ, Ford K, Graney W. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 2 study of RMP-7 in combination with carboplatin administered intravenously for the treatment of recurrent malignant glioma. Neuro-oncol. 2003 Apr;5(2):96-103.</citation>
    <PMID>12672281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prados MD, Warnick RE, Mack EE, Chandler KL, Rabbitt J, Page M, Malec M. Intravenous carboplatin for recurrent gliomas. A dose-escalating phase II trial. Am J Clin Oncol. 1996 Dec;19(6):609-12.</citation>
    <PMID>8931682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 7, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 10, 2009</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiangiogenesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation</keyword>
  <keyword>Progression</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma Multiforme</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oligodendroglioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gliosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
