<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="150">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00147056</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BT002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00147056</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MRI-Guided Focused Ultrasound Feasibility Study for Brain Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Feasibility Study to Evaluate the Safety and Feasibility of Transcranial MRI-Guided Focused Ultrasound Surgery in the Treatment of Brain Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>InSightec</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>InSightec</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety of MRI-guided focused ultrasound thermal
      ablation of brain lesions performed through intact human skull using the ExAblate 3000
      system. We will collect data to establish the basic safety of this type of treatment as the
      basis for later studies that will evaluate its clinical efficacy. The hypothesis of the
      study is to determine if FUS under MRI-guidance and MRI-based thermometry can be safely
      delivered through an intact human skull with a low risk of transient short-term adverse
      effects as evaluated during follow-up of up to 3 months and a pre-defined target volume
      inside the brain lesion can be accurately ablated, as shown on post-treatment MRI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Non-invasive focused ultrasound surgery has special appeal for use inside the skull, where
      it is desirable to destroy lesions deep in the brain without damage to the surrounding brain
      tissue or other structures.

      The ExAblate systems are the result of an 8-year development by InSightec and GE Medical
      Systems. These systems combine a focused ultrasound surgery (FUS) delivery system and a
      conventional diagnostic 1.5 T MRI scanner.

      The ExAblate 2000 system is being used at Brigham and Women's (BWH) and in about a dozen
      other hospitals around the world for clinical trials in for the treatment of uterine
      fibroids, breast fibroadenoma, and breast carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI Guilded Focused ultrasound feasibility study for brain tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Metastatic Cancer to the Brain</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ExAblate 3000</intervention_name>
    <description>MRI-Guided Focused Ultrasound Feasibility Study for Brain</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with only recurrent glioblastoma (grade IV astro) and recurrent metastatic
             cancer to the brain for whom surgery has not been advised by a physician that is not
             associated with this study.

          2. Lesion(s) to be treated are located in the cerebral hemispheres, &gt; 1.5 cm from the
             cortex and the dura.

          3. Lesion(s) are clearly defined on pre-therapy contrast enhanced MRI scans.

          4. Three or less lesion(s) in the brain

          5. Size of solid mass of lesions is less than 2.5 cm in diameter (8 cm3  in volume).

          6. Men or women.

          7. Age between 18 and 70 years, inclusive.

          8. Karnofsky rating 70-100 (See Appendix A).

          9. ASA score 1-2.

         10. Able and willing to give informed consent.

         11. Able to communicate sensations during the MRGFUS procedure.

         12. Apparently able to attend all study visits (i.e., life expectancy of at least 3
             months).

         13. At least 14 days passed since last tumor therapy (i.e. surgery, chemotherapy,
             radiation therapy).  .

         14. No additional tumor therapies anticipated for at least 30 days (i.e. surgery,
             chemotherapy, radiation therapy).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        a) The lesion's appearance on the pre-therapy MR and CT scans:

          1. Brain edema and/or mass effect that causes midline shift or shift in wall of
             ventricle of more than 5 mm.

          2. Localized in the brain stem or the posterior fossa.

          3. Less than 5mm from primary branches of cerebral vessels, venous  sinus, hypophysis or
             cranial nerves.

          4. Evidence of recent (less than 2 weeks) hemorrhage.

          5. Containing calcifications. b) The sonication pathway to the lesion involves:

        a. More than 30% of the skull area traversed by the sonication pathway is covered by
        scars, scalp disorders (e.g., eczema), or atrophy of the scalp.

        b. Clips or other implanted objects in the skull or the brain. c) The subject presents
        with:

          1. Symptoms and signs of increased intracranial pressure (e.g., headache, nausea,
             vomiting, lethargy, and papaedama).

          2. Unstable hemodynamic status including:

        i. Documented myocardial infarction within six months of enrollment. ii. Symptomatic
        coronary artery stenosis. iii. Congestive heart disease requiring medication. iv.
        Anti-arrhythmic drug medication. v. Cardiac pacemaker. vi. Severe hypertension (diastolic
        BP &gt; 100 on medication). c. Anti-coagulation therapy or known bleeding disorder. d.
        Abnormal level of platelets (&lt; 100), PT (&gt;14) or PTT (&gt;36). e. Documented cerebral
        infarction within past 12 months. f. TIA due to arteriosclerosis in the last 1 month. g.
        Other known cerebral or general vasculopathy. h. Insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. i.
        Immunosuppression (corticosteroids to prevent brain edema are permitted). j. Known
        sensitivity to gadolinium-DTPA. k. Contraindications to MRI such as non-MRI-compatible
        implanted devices. l. Large subjects not fitting comfortably into the MRI scanner
        (generally &gt;250 lbs.) m. Difficulty to lay supine and still for up to 4 hours in the MRI
        unit or claustrophobia.

        n. Sleep apnea. o. Positive pregnancy test (for pre-menopausal women). p. Known
        life-threatening systemic disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.insightec.com</url>
    <description>Sponsor web page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 27, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 2, 2005</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Lesions</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>ExAblate</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
