<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="160">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01400672</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009LS136</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1004M81213</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01400672</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imiquimod/Brain Tumor Initiating Cell (BTIC) Vaccine in Brain Stem Glioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Imiquimod/BTIC Lysate-Based Vaccine Immunotherapy for Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma in Children and Young Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot/feasibility study. The study design represents a modification of current
      standard of care for Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma (DIPG) (5580 cGY involved field
      radiation), with the final two doses of radiation given at intervals during the vaccination
      phase of treatment.

      Patients between the ages of 3 years and 25 years diagnosed with Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine
      Glioma (DIPG) will be allowed to participate in the trial. Study enrollment will occur after
      the completion of conformal radiation therapy to a dose of 5580 cGy and the post radiation
      therapy (RT) magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) shows no disease progression.

      Three patients with glioblastoma multiforme, aged 16 years and older, will be entered first
      to confirm vaccine safety before enrolling DIPG patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vaccine will be produced by the University Of Minnesota Molecular and Cellular Therapeutics
      Facility using the established brain tumor initiating cell (BTIC) cell line GBM-6 as the
      antigen source. Vaccine administration will begin at four weeks (week 10) following
      completion of radiation therapy and will be given every two weeks for four doses. At the
      time of the 1st and 3rd vaccinations, additional 180 cGy fractions will be delivered in
      single doses in a novel effort to induce NKG2D ligand upregulation (thereby &quot;sensitizing&quot;
      residual tumor to lymphocyte attack). The total radiation dose for each patient will be 5940
      cGy. Subsequent vaccinations will be given every four weeks and will continue to a maximum
      of one year from study enrollment, by which time median survival will have passed based on
      historical data. Imaging will be obtained at study entry (post radiation therapy) and every
      eight weeks thereafter to eighteen months, after which time the interval between imaging
      follow-up episodes will be determined by the patient's clinical status. Imaging will include
      MRI of the brain using our current institutional brain tumor imaging protocol. Imaging will
      also include SPECT/MRI and perfusion MRI. FDG-PET imaging may be used in certain cases to
      differentiate tumor necrosis from progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Determined as Grade 3 or 4 toxicity observation after dosing with BTIC vaccination. Toxicity will be graded using the NCI's Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE 4.0) in terms of local, regional and systemic events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Drop-out rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours, 48 hours and 1 week after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Treatment feasibility will be based on the drop-out rate in absence of disease progression. Information will be presented in a tabular and descriptive manner</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Tumor Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Study entry through 24 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Imaging will include MRI, SPECT/MRI and perfusion MRI. FDG-PET imaging may be also be used Response criteria: Complete responses (CR) are those in which there is a disappearance of all enhancing tumor or tumor mass on consecutive MRI scans. Patients must be off steroids, and neurologically stable or improved.
Partial responses (PR) are those in which there is a ≥ 50% reduction in the size of the enhancing tumor or tumor mass on consecutive MRI scans. In addition, the patient must be neurologically stable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <condition>Adult Glioblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DIPG Patients Receiving Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma (DIPG) receiving radiation therapy, Tumor Lysate Vaccine (dose of 4 x 10^6 cells divided into 2 doses then every 4 weeks for up to 1 year) and Imiquimod (5% Aldara cream at a total dose of 12.5 mg) topically at each site prior to and 24 hours after vaccination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumor Lysate Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Vaccination is injected intradermally every 2 weeks for 4 doses, then every 4 weeks for up to 1 year.  Patients will receive 1 mg protein divided into 2 doses at two separate subinguinal sites.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DIPG Patients Receiving Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imiquimod</intervention_name>
    <description>Marketed as 5% Aldara cream topically applied; total of 12.5 mg divided between the two vaccination sites and reapplied at the vaccination sites 24 hours later.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DIPG Patients Receiving Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aldara cream</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Initial course of radiation therapy is given over 6-7 weeks, 5580 cGy. Additional 180 cGy fractions will be delivered as a single dose on days of 1st and 3rd vaccinations and given according to standard of care at University of Minnesota Medical Center. Total radiation dose will be 5940 cGy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DIPG Patients Receiving Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria - GBM patients only (enrollment plan 1):

          -  Histologically confirmed glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) World Health Organization
             (WHO) grade III-IV with recurrent or progressive disease after standard therapy

          -  Age 16 years or older

        Inclusion Criteria - DIPG patients only (enrollment plan 2 and 3):

          -  Diagnosis of diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma (DIPG) by magnetic resonance imaging
             (MRI). Because the safety of biopsy of DIPG has not been firmly established, biopsy
             will not be required for study enrollment.

          -  Completion of standard radiation therapy (not to exceed 5580 cGy) with a post
             radiation therapy (RT) MRI that shows no disease progression when compared with
             pre-RT MRI. All patients must be treated with Intensity Modulated Radiation Therapy
             (IMRT) or an equivalent conformal technique. The clinical target volume will be
             defined as the gross tumor volume (full extent of tumor visible on MRI) plus 1 cm
             margin. Patients from an outside institution who are referred after the start of
             radiation therapy may complete initial radiation therapy at their home institution as
             long as dosage guidelines are met and the total dose does not exceed 5580 cGy at the
             time of study registration.

          -  Able to begin vaccination 4 weeks (+ or - 1 week) of completion of standard radiation
             therapy

          -  Age 3 years and older Inclusion Criteria - all patients regardless of diagnosis

          -  Clinically stable and off or on low dose (no more than 0.1 mg/kg/day, maximum of 4
             mg/day dexamethasone) corticosteroid for at least 1 week prior to study enrollment

          -  Lansky (0-15 years) or Karnofsky (16 years or older) performance score of ≥ 60

          -  Adequate organ function within 14 days of study registration including the following:

               -  Adequate bone marrow reserve: absolute neutrophil (segmented and bands) count
                  (ANC) ≥ 1.0 x 10^9/L, platelets ≥ 100 x 10^9/L; Hemoglobin ≥ 8 g/dL

               -  Hepatic: - Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age and SGPT
                  (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age

               -  Renal: Normal serum creatinine for age or creatinine clearance &gt;60 ml/min/1.73
                  m^2.

          -  Sexually active females of child bearing potential must agree to use adequate
             contraception (diaphragm, birth control pills, injections, intrauterine device [IUD],
             surgical sterilization, subcutaneous implants, or abstinence, etc.) for the duration
             of the vaccination period. Sexually active males must agree to use barrier
             contraceptive for the duration of the vaccination period.

          -  Voluntary written informed consent must be obtained from all patients (if of assent
             age) and their parents or legal guardians before performance of any study-related
             procedure not part of normal medical care, with the understanding that consent may be
             withdrawn by the subject at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

        Exclusion Criteria - all patients:

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding. Pregnancy testing will be performed on all menstruating
             females within 14 days prior to study enrollment.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements

          -  Currently receiving any chemotherapy, investigational agents or registration on
             another therapy based trial or received chemotherapy with radiation therapy

          -  History of immune system abnormalities such as hyperimmunity (e.g., autoimmune
             diseases) and hypoimmunity (e.g., myelodysplastic disorders, marrow failures, AIDS,
             ongoing pregnancy, transplant immunosuppression)

          -  Any isolated laboratory abnormality suggestive of a serious autoimmune disease

          -  Any conditions that could potentially alter immune function (AIDS, multiple
             sclerosis, diabetes, renal failure)

          -  Receiving ongoing treatment with immunosuppressive drugs, excluding those patients
             requiring dexamethasone for treatment of tumor-related edema
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Moertel, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christopher Moertel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>612-626-2778</phone>
    <email>moert001@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tambra Dahlheimer, RN</last_name>
    <phone>612 626 2629</phone>
    <email>tdahlheimer@umphysicians.umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher Moertel, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-2778</phone>
      <email>moert001@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Moertel, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 19, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>glioblastoma multiforme</keyword>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pontine Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Imiquimod</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
