<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="42">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01779219</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STAT2009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01779219</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>iMRI-guided Brain Biopsies</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Safety and Effectiveness of Low Field Intraoperative MRI-guidance in Frameless Stereotactic Biopsies of Brain Tumours - a Prospective Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wroclaw Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wroclaw Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Poland: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: The aim of the study was to assess the safety and effectiveness of stereotactic
      brain tumour biopsy (STx biopsy) guided by low-field intraoperative MRI (iMRI) in comparison
      with its frameless classic analogue based on a prospective randomized trial.

      Patients are prospectively randomized into a low-field iMRI group and a control group that
      undergo a frameless STx biopsy. The primary endpoints of the analysis are:  postoperative
      complication rate and diagnostic yield, and the secondary endpoints: length of hospital stay
      and duration of operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION Stereotactic brain biopsy (STx biopsy) offers a relatively straightforward,
      accurate and safe method of obtaining diagnostic tissue. Frameless computer-based
      neuronavigation is now widely used in brain tumor surgery. It has many advantages over
      frame-based techniques and provides similar accuracy to the rigid frame. One of the methods
      applied to improve diagnostic yield and safety is the usage of intraoperative magnetic
      resonance imaging (iMRI), proposed by Bernays et al. in 2002.

      Besides the obvious indications given in previous papers, including STx biopsy of very
      small, deeply localized or cystic lesions, iMRI guidance is particularly useful in two
      cases.  The first one is when a satisfactory 3D volume modality cannot be obtained during
      preoperative high-field diagnostic MR imaging. When using iMRI there is no need to perform
      preoperative 3D imaging of any kind and manually register the patient's head in a
      neuronavigation system before the operation, which helps to significantly improve the
      workflow. In our study the total amount of patients with insufficient neuroimaging -
      admitted from outside medical centers - is over 30%. The second case is for teaching
      purposes - frameless iMRI guided STx biopsy, is relatively uncomplicated and technically
      straightforward and can be introduced as the first procedure during training in
      neurosurgical intraoperative imaging.

      Although the usefulness of ultra-low-field iMRI in STx biopsy was subsequently confirmed by
      other authors, according to our knowledge no previous published studies have compared iMRI
      to preoperative MRI for brain tumor biopsy according to evidence-based medicine guidelines
      (EBM). Though this method has been subject to slight criticism, it has been consequently
      applied in neurosurgical daily practice in recent years.

      The aim of our study was to verify the safety and effectiveness of the STx biopsy guided by
      low-field iMRI in comparison with its frameless classic analogue basing on a prospective
      randomized parallel-group, controlled trial. In the current paper we present the study
      design and results of the interim analysis.

      MATERIAL AND METHODS

      Patients Patients who are - following contemporary recommendations - scheduled to undergo
      STx biopsy, are prospectively recruited for the study. Each patient sign a written consent
      to participate in the study.

      Inclusion criteria The inclusion criteria were as follows: male and female patients ≥ 18
      years with supratentorial brain tumor scheduled to undergo STx biopsy. The estimated number
      of patients needed to reveal the difference of over 5% between primary endpoints' -
      diagnostic yield and complications ratio - at the level of significance 0.05 and power 80%
      was 465 per each arm.

      Exclusion criteria Patients unable to provide informed consent and those with metal implants
      which could prevent or influence the head MR study were excluded from the study.

      Allocation Patients were prospectively allocated by minimization according to demographic
      (gender, age) and epidemiologic data (preoperative Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group
      Performance Status-ECOG- a scale providing information about neurological and social status
      of a patient with oncological disease, maximum tumor diameter, presence of contrast
      enhancement, independent risk factors of hemorrhage - basal and thalamic localization and
      preoperative diabetes) into the iMRI and the control group.

      Intervention After being transferred to the operating room each patient was sedated with an
      intravenous infusion of Remifentanil with passive oxygen therapy and monitoring of vital
      functions. Additionally, the sites of head holder pins and skin incision were anaesthetized
      with 1% Lignocaine. All biopsies in both groups were performed via a 6 mm burr-hole with the
      use of the Vertec system (Medtronic Navigation, Louisville, CO, USA). A passively navigated
      side cut 2.2 mm biopsy needle was used. All operations were performed by one of the three
      first authors.

      In the iMRI-guided group the head of each patient was immobilized with a 3-pin
      iMRI-compatible head holder. The PoleStar N20 iMRI system (Medtronic Navigation, Louisville,
      CO, USA) with a 0.15-T constant magnet was used in all procedures. Subsequently, after the
      patient's positioning, the preoperative reference examination was routinely carried out
      (T1+gadolinum, T2 or FLAIR weighted - depending on the pathology, axial 4 mm scans). Images
      were automatically transferred into the neuronavigation system (StealthStation, Medtronic
      Navigation, Louisville, CO, USA). The entry point, target and optimal biopsy trajectory were
      then defined by the operator on the basis of the obtained iMRI images. Serial tissue samples
      (4 from the central and another 4 from the marginal part of the tumor) were collected
      according to the modified protocol described by Shooman et al., which made use of
      intraoperative histopathological examination obsolete. Following each operation, a control
      iMRI (T1-weighted, axial, 4 mm scan examination) was routinely performed to confirm and
      document the proper targeting and - as proposed by Bernays et al. - to exclude postoperative
      hyperacute intraparenchymal bleeding.

      A frameless STx biopsy was performed for each patient from the control group with the use of
      a neuronavigation system. The entry point, target and optimal biopsy trajectory were defined
      by the operator before the operation on the basis of the preoperatively obtained high-field
      MR images with the use of a neuronavigation workstation (Cranial 5, StealthStation
      Application Software, Medtronic Navigation, Louisville, CO, USA). Following surgery the
      specimens were sent for independent histopathological analysis.

      Postoperative care Postoperative care was conducted according to standard protocols and
      clinical guidelines. A postoperative follow-up head CT was subsequently performed 4 to 6
      hours after each procedure. All patients were followed up with a clinical examination 2
      weeks postoperatively performed by an independent and blinded for the allocation
      investigator.

      Data collection Demographic and epidemiological data were collected prospectively. The
      primary endpoints were: the ratio of acute postoperative complications and the diagnostic
      yield. The presence of acute postoperative complication was noted if any of following
      findings was noted: (wound site infection up to two weeks after the operation, a new
      neurological deficit developed up to 24 hours following the operation and present in a
      follow up clinical examination 2 weeks postoperatively), intraparenchymal hematoma with
      radiological or clinical signs of the intracranial expansion.) and the diagnostic yield. The
      diagnostic yield was expressed according to the literature as a percentage of patients in
      whom the histopathological diagnosis was possible on the basis of the biological material
      obtained during the operation. Secondary endpoints included: the preoperative (LOSpre),
      postoperative (LOSpost) and total length of hospital stay (LOS) as well as the preparation
      (Tprep), operation (Top) and total operating room (TOR) time. The LOS and T were routinely
      measured and recorded in the central hospital files by the independent staff.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for the duration of hospital stay and again 2 weeks after the operation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The presence of acute postoperative complication is noted if any of following findings is present: wound site infection up to two weeks after the operation, a new neurological deficit developed up to 24 hours following the operation and present in a follow up clinical examination 2 weeks postoperatively, intraparenchymal hematoma with radiological or clinical signs of the intracranial expansion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic yield</measure>
    <time_frame>For each patient 2 weeks after the operation</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The diagnostic yield is expressed according to the literature as a percentage of patients in whom the histopathological diagnosis was possible on the basis of the biological material obtained during the operation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>LOSpre will be assessed on the day of the operation; LOSpost and LOS will be calculated at discharge from the hospital - in average 1 day after the surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The preoperative (LOSpre), postoperative (LOSpost) and total length of hospital stay (LOS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time</measure>
    <time_frame>For each patient on the day of the operation (day 1)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The preparation (Tprep), operation (Top) and total operating room (TOR) time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Supratentorial Brain Tumour</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iMRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The PoleStar N20 iMRI system (Medtronic Navigation, Louisville, CO, USA) with a 0.15-T constant magnet is used in all procedures. Subsequently, after the patient's positioning, the preoperative reference examination is routinely carried out (T1+gadolinum, T2 or FLAIR weighted - depending on the pathology, axial 4 mm scans). The entry point, target and optimal biopsy trajectory are then defined by the operator on the basis of the obtained iMRI images. Serial tissue samples (4 from the central and another 4 from the marginal part of the tumour) are collected. Following each operation, a control iMRI (T1-weighted, axial, 4 mm scan examination) is routinely performed to confirm and document the proper targeting and to exclude postoperative hyperacute intraparenchymal bleeding.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>non-iMRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A frameless STx biopsy is performed for each patient from the control group with the use of a neuronavigation system. The entry point, target and optimal biopsy trajectory are defined by the operator before the operation on the basis of the preoperatively obtained high-field MR images with the use of a neuronavigation workstation (Cranial 5, StealthStation Application Software, Medtronic Navigation, Louisville, CO, USA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stereotactic intraoperative magnetic resonance (iMRI)-guided frameless brain tumour biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>The PoleStar N20 iMRI system (Medtronic Navigation, Louisville, CO, USA) with a 0.15-T constant magnet was used in all procedures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>iMRI</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>iMRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stereotactic frameless brain tumour biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>The entry point, target and optimal biopsy trajectory were defined by the operator before the operation on the basis of the preoperatively obtained high-field MR images with the use of a neuronavigation workstation (Cranial 5, StealthStation Application Software, Medtronic Navigation, Louisville, CO, USA).</description>
    <arm_group_label>non-iMRI</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neuronavigation</other_name>
    <other_name>Non-iMRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  male and female patients ≥ 18 years

          -  supratentorial brain tumour

          -  scheduled to undergo STx biopsy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients unable to provide informed consent

          -  metal implants which could prevent or influence the head MR study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marcin Czyż, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>504150014</phone>
    <email>mt.czyz@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neurosurgery, Wroclaw Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wroclaw</city>
        <zip>50-556</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcin Czyż, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+48504150014</phone>
      <email>mt.czyz@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcin Czyż, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paweł Tabakow, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Artur Weiser, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wojciech L Zub, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Włodzimierz Jarmundowicz, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Poland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shooman D, Belli A, Grundy PL. Image-guided frameless stereotactic biopsy without intraoperative neuropathological examination. J Neurosurg. 2010 Aug;113(2):170-8. doi: 10.3171/2009.12.JNS09573.</citation>
    <PMID>20136389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Czyż M, Tabakow P, Jarmundowicz W, Lechowicz-Głogowska B. Intraoperative magnetic resonance-guided frameless stereotactic biopsies - initial clinical experience. Neurol Neurochir Pol. 2012 Mar-Apr;46(2):157-60.</citation>
    <PMID>22581597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernays RL, Kollias SS, Khan N, Brandner S, Meier S, Yonekawa Y. Histological yield, complications, and technological considerations in 114 consecutive frameless stereotactic biopsy procedures aided by open intraoperative magnetic resonance imaging. J Neurosurg. 2002 Aug;97(2):354-62.</citation>
    <PMID>12186464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weaver CS, Leonardi-Bee J, Bath-Hextall FJ, Bath PM. Sample size calculations in acute stroke trials: a systematic review of their reporting, characteristics, and relationship with outcome. Stroke. 2004 May;35(5):1216-24. Epub 2004 Mar 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15031455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frati A, Pichierri A, Bastianello S, Raco A, Santoro A, Esposito V, Giangaspero F, Salvati M. Frameless stereotactic cerebral biopsy: our experience in 296 cases. Stereotact Funct Neurosurg. 2011;89(4):234-45. doi: 10.1159/000325704. Epub 2011 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21778794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Han B, Enas NH, McEntegart D. Randomization by minimization for unbalanced treatment allocation. Stat Med. 2009 Nov 30;28(27):3329-46. doi: 10.1002/sim.3710.</citation>
    <PMID>19739238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Isaacs D, Fitzgerald D. Seven alternatives to evidence based medicine. BMJ. 1999 Dec 18-25;319(7225):1618.</citation>
    <PMID>10600968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kundt G. Comparative evaluation of balancing properties of stratified randomization procedures. Methods Inf Med. 2009;48(2):129-34. doi: 10.3414/ME0538. Epub 2009 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>19283309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langen HJ, Kugel H, Ortmann M, Noack M, de Rochemont RM, Landwehr P. [Functional capacity of MRI-compatible biopsy needles in comparison with ferromagnetic biopsy needles. In vitro studies]. Rofo. 2001 Jul;173(7):658-62. German.</citation>
    <PMID>11512240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGirt MJ, Woodworth GF, Coon AL, Frazier JM, Amundson E, Garonzik I, Olivi A, Weingart JD. Independent predictors of morbidity after image-guided stereotactic brain biopsy: a risk assessment of 270 cases. J Neurosurg. 2005 May;102(5):897-901.</citation>
    <PMID>15926716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oken MM, Creech RH, Tormey DC, Horton J, Davis TE, McFadden ET, Carbone PP. Toxicity and response criteria of the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group. Am J Clin Oncol. 1982 Dec;5(6):649-55. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>7165009</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulder M, Spiro D. Intraoperative MRI for stereotactic biopsy. Acta Neurochir Suppl. 2011;109:81-7. doi: 10.1007/978-3-211-99651-5_13.</citation>
    <PMID>20960325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Senft C, Bink A, Franz K, Vatter H, Gasser T, Seifert V. Intraoperative MRI guidance and extent of resection in glioma surgery: a randomised, controlled trial. Lancet Oncol. 2011 Oct;12(11):997-1003. Epub 2011 Aug 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21868284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 15, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wroclaw Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marcin Czyz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.D., Ph.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intraoperative magnetic resonance</keyword>
  <keyword>stereotactic biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>frameless stereotaxy</keyword>
  <keyword>image-guided neurosurgery</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
