<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="232">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01556230</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAE1260</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01NS070600</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01556230</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Study of Clinically Nonfunctioning Pituitary Adenomas</brief_title>
  <acronym>PAPS</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Study of Clinically Nonfunctioning Pituitary Adenomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to carefully characterize the outcome of treatment for
      nonfunctioning pituitary adenomas. Pituitary adenomas are benign tumors of the pituitary
      gland. The study will follow 3 groups of patients with apparent pituitary adenomas (based on
      the MRI appearance and clinical presentation). One group of patients who will have surgery,
      a second who will not have surgery, and a third who have radiotherapy after surgery.  The
      study will determine predictors of tumor growth and regrowth after surgery and if certain
      tumor markers can predict if the tumor will continue to grow.  The study will determine
      whether the development of pituitary dysfunction, vision abnormalities or significant tumor
      growth differ between the no surgery, surgery, or radiation therapy groups.  Patients in the
      study will also complete questionnaires on quality of life and memory function testing
      before and after the follow up or surgery or radiation treatment in order to determine if
      quality of life or memory are affected by these treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research question(s):

      This study conducts a comprehensive prospective study of clinically nonfunctioning pituitary
      adenomas. The study aims to test the hypothesis that conservative, nonsurgical management of
      clinically nonfunctioning pituitary lesions that do not meet criteria for surgery as initial
      therapy is safe with respect to changes in pituitary function, tumor size and visual and
      neurological function. The study also aims to determine the outcome of transsphenoidal
      surgery and also in some cases the addition of pituitary radiotherapy for symptomatic,
      clinically nonfunctioning pituitary tumors and test the hypothesis that radiotherapy will
      reduce the recurrence rate of pituitary tumors. In addition, the study will consider whether
      clinical features or immunohistochemical markers of tumor proliferation predict tumor
      regrowth. In particular the study will test the hypothesis that the silent corticotroph
      tumor subtype, characterized by elevated plasma levels of ACTH or its precursor, POMC, is
      associated with an increased tumor recurrence rate. The study also aims to determine for the
      first time, prospectively, the impact of conservative follow up, surgery and RT on quality
      of life and neurocognitive function in patients with clinically nonfunctioning pituitary
      lesions.

      Study Purpose:

      This project is the first comprehensive prospective study of clinically nonfunctioning
      pituitary adenomas (CNFAs). The purpose of the project is to answer a number of important
      questions about the evaluation and management of these lesions. No rigorously developed
      guidelines exist for the evaluation, therapy or longterm monitoring of CNFAs. Rather,
      current management strategies are loosely defined and based almost exclusively on data from
      retrospectively reported series. As a result, a number of significant gaps exist in our
      current knowledge about CNFA management. With regard to asymptomatic pituitary lesions, the
      appropriate initial evaluation and followup strategies, as well as the safety of
      conservative, nonsurgical management are unknown. For symptomatic tumors, surgery is the
      initial treatment of choice, but many tumors recur and there exists no means of reliably
      predicting those at risk for recurrence. Further study of predictors of aggressive,
      recurrent tumors is needed. One possible predictor requiring study is the &quot;silent&quot;
      corticotroph tumor type. The safety of conservative followup for patients with small tumor
      remnants after surgery is not known. The need for radiation for all such patients remains
      unclear since the risks vs. benefits of postoperative RT for residual/recurrent tumors have
      not been prospectively studied. The longterm management of CNFA should also consider the
      impact of therapy on quality of life and neurocognitive function, but these have never been
      evaluated longitudinally. Our large prospective study is needed to answer these important
      questions about CNFA management.

      Study Design PROTOCOL I: Prospective Study of the outcome of conservative nonsurgical
      management of patients with asymptomatic, clinically nonfunctioning pituitary lesions. This
      protocol will evaluate prospectively the outcome of nonsurgical management of clinically
      nonfunctioning pituitary lesions that do not appear to need surgery as their initial
      therapy. The overall design consists of an initial baseline evaluation and then serial
      prospective follow up studies over time for up to 5 years of follow up. The study will
      evaluate laboratory testing, clinical examinations, quality of life and neurocognitive
      function in these patients. We will also collect data on visual fields and MRI studies of
      the pituitary tumor that are done prospectively as part of clinical care to evaluate these
      patients. Data to be collected will include the prevalence of pituitary dysfunction at
      presentation, the safety of conservative nonsurgical management of patients with
      asymptomatic, clinically nonfunctioning pituitary lesions with respect to the development of
      symptomatic tumor enlargement and pituitary dysfunction, the prevalence of the silent
      corticotroph tumor type that is characterized by elevated plasma levels of ACTH or its
      precursor, POMC, and if it is associated with an increased tumor recurrence rate and
      prospectively assess quality of life and neurocognitive function in patients with clinically
      nonfunctioning pituitary lesions treated without surgery.

      PROTOCOL II : Prospective study of the outcome of patients with symptomatic, clinically
      nonfunctioning pituitary tumors who are treated with transsphenoidal surgery and in some
      cases also radiotherapy. This protocol will evaluate prospectively the outcome of surgical
      management of asymptomatic clinically nonfunctioning pituitary lesions. The overall design
      consists of an initial baseline evaluation and then serial prospective follow up studies
      over time with up to 5 years of follow up. The study will evaluate laboratory testing,
      clinical examinations, quality of life and neurocognitive function in these patients. We
      will also collect data on visual fields and MRI studies of the pituitary tumor that are done
      prospectively as part of clinical care to evaluate these patients. Data to be collected will
      be analyzed to determine the safety of observation alone following surgery for patients who
      do not have a clinically significant tumor remnant, if the silent corticotroph tumor type is
      characterized by elevated plasma levels of ACTH or its precursor, POMC, and if it is
      associated with an increased tumor recurrence rate. A group of patients who are planning RT
      will also be studied by these same procedures before and after RT in order to determine if
      the outcomes of patients who receive RT for treatment of tumor regrowth to that of those who
      do not receive RT with respect to further tumor growth, endocrine or neurological
      dysfunction. We will also prospectively assess quality of life and neurocognitive function
      in patients with clinically nonfunctioning pituitary lesions treated with surgery alone or
      those who also receive radiotherapy.

      Study Subjects:

      Group I: A group of 100 adult patients with pituitary lesions that do not require surgical
      intervention will be studied as part of Protocol I. Eligible patients will have a pituitary
      lesion demonstrated on MRI to be consistent with an adenoma (not a cystic lesion such as a
      Rathke's cleft cyst). Patients meeting any of the following indications for surgery will be
      excluded: presence of visual or neurological deficits due to the tumor, tumor impingement on
      the optic chiasm and physical or laboratory abnormalities consistent with a biologically
      active hormone secreting tumor. Some patients may have elevations of pituitary hormones such
      as ACTH, but no elevation of end organ hormone such as cortisol. Patients with a pituitary
      tumor that makes a functioning hormone and has a resultant biochemical and/or clinical
      syndrome associated with it would be treated as appropriate with surgery or medication and
      would not be followed conservatively without surgery.

      Group II: A second group of 250 adult patients with pituitary lesions that require surgical
      intervention and who are planning on surgery will be studied as part of Protocol II.
      Although we have established general guidelines for who should be recommended for surgery,
      the formal decision whether or not to undergo surgery is a medical one made by the patient
      and the Neurosurgeon.

      Group III: Patients who are undergoing Radiotherapy and previously underwent surgery for
      their pituitary tumor are also eligible to participate.

      Subject Recruitment:

      Patients in both study groups will be recruited directly from the office of the
      participating Neurosurgeon, Dr. Jeffrey Bruce and by referral to our Neuroendocrine Unit
      from the other participating Neurosurgeon, Dr. Kalmon Post.

      Patients may also be recruited from out Neuroendocrine clinical practice or referred by
      outside physicians for participation in the study. Each patient will first be approached
      about participation in the study by their physician. It they are interested then the study
      team will discuss the study further with them.

      Study Procedures:

      Protocol I:

      Baseline Visit: History and physical examination, laboratory testing: prolactin, ACTH,
      cortisol, free thyroxine, TSH, LH, FSH, testosterone (men), GH, IGFI, POMC, asubunit, 24hour
      for urine free cortisol.

      Follow up visits: 6 and 12 months and yearly after the baseline visit. Testing at each visit
      includes an update of the history, laboratory testing as done at the baseline visit,
      physical examinations and completion of quality of life and neurocognitive testing, visual
      field testing and pituitary MRI scans. Those patients who develop a clinically significant
      enlargement of the tumor that meets a surgical indication will be given the option of
      entering Protocol II. Tumor enlargement will be considered clinically significant if the
      tumor grows to impinge on the optic chiasm or causes any visual disturbance or other
      neurological abnormality.

      Quality of life testing: Patients will be administered general health questionnaires SF36,
      NHP (Nottingham health profile) and disease specific questionnaires QLSH (quality of life
      satisfaction hypopituitarism) and QoL AGHD (Quality of life assessment of GH deficiency in
      adults). Neurocognitive testing: Patients will be administered a series of standard and
      widely used tests of neurocognitive function, primarily measures of memory and
      neurocognitive function, by trained personnel.

      Protocol II Baseline Visit: History and physical examination, laboratory testing (as in
      Protocol I), visual fields, quality of life, neurocognitive testing (as in Protocol I) and
      MRI scan. Follow up visits after surgery: 6 and 12 months and yearly after the baseline
      visit include the testing as done at the baseline visit. Surgical procedures will take place
      as per routine clinical practice of the surgeon. Records from the surgical procedure
      including extent and invasion of the tumor and occurrence of endocrine abnormalities
      postoperatively such as diabetes insipidus or new hypopituitarism will be recorded. If
      patients are referred for radiotherapy if they have residual tumor or regrowth of their
      tumor then they will be followed also prospectively with a baseline visit and follow up
      visits after radiotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2009</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pituitary tumor enlargement</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of patients with tumor enlargement over the study period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of hypopituitarism</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Number of patients with the development of hypopituitarism over the time frame.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurocognitive function change</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change in neurcognitive function test score over the time frame of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Pituitary Adenoma</condition>
  <condition>Pituitary Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with clinically nonfunctioning pituitary adenomas may be treated with surgery or by observation alone depending on the tumor size and other factors. The decision whether or not to treat the  tumor with surgery was made by the patient and their physicians. The purpose of this study is to carefully characterize the outcome of this conservative nonsurgical treatment including whether or not the tumor grows, if there is any change in hormone levels and whether surgery becomes necessary in the future.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with clinically nonfunctioning pituitary adenomas may be treated with surgery or by observation alone depending on the tumor size and other factors. The decision whether or not to treat the tumor with surgery is made by the patient and their physician. Patient who have decided to have surgery are invited to participate in this study that will evaluate the outcome of prospective follow up for you before and after surgery. The purpose of this study is to carefully characterize the outcome of surgical treatment including whether or not the tumor regrows, if the patient any change in hormone levels, and whether radiotherapy is needed in the future.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radiotherapy (Radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with clinically nonfunctioning pituitary adenomas may be treated initially with surgery or by observation alone depending on the tumor size and other factors. Some patients receive radiotherapy at some time after the surgery was done, typically because the tumor could not be fully removed and/or has regrown. The decision whether or not to treat the tumor with radiotherapy was made by the patient and their physicians. As the patient has decided to have radiotherapy for their pituitary tumor they are being invited to participate in this study that will evaluate the outcome of prospective follow up for you before and after radiotherapy. The purpose of this study is to carefully characterize the outcome of radiotherapy treatment including whether or not the tumor regrows or if there is a change in hormone levels.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Any persons diagnosed with a non-functioning pituitary adenoma that is willing to travel
        to our study center at Columbia University in New York, NY for all study visits.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with a pituitary tumor that does not secrete hormones AND

          -  Men and women 18 years of age or older AND

          -  Patient and their doctor have decided that the patient will have radiotherapy OR

          -  Patient and their doctor have decided that the patient will have surgery OR

          -  Patient and their doctor have decided that that the patient will have surgery

          -  Pituitary lesion is greater than or equal to 7.0 mm in maximal diameter

          -  Prolactin level is less than 100 ng/ml
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pamela U. Freda, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University College of Physicians&amp;Surgeons</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amanda N Wade, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-7243</phone>
    <email>anw2124@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jean Carlos Fernandez, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-4921</phone>
    <email>sjf2132@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University College of Physicians &amp; Surgeons</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amanda N. Wade, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-7243</phone>
      <email>anw2124@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jean Carlos Fernandez, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-4921</phone>
      <email>sjf2132@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pamela U. Freda, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sharon L Wardlaw, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey N Bruce, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven R Isaacson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 4, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 9, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pamela U. Freda</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pituitary gland</keyword>
  <keyword>pituitary adenoma</keyword>
  <keyword>pituitary tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>hypophysis</keyword>
  <keyword>endocrine</keyword>
  <keyword>neuroendocrine</keyword>
  <keyword>hormone</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
