<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="274">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01339052</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-033</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CBKM120XUS07T</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01339052</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Study of BKM120 for Subjects With Recurrent Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of BKM 120 for Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma and Activated PI3K Pathway</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Patrick Y. Wen, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BKM120 is a newly discovered drug that has been used in other research studies. Information
      from those other research studies suggests that BKM120 may help to slow or stop the growth
      of malignant gliomas. The purpose of this study is to see how well BKM120 works in patients
      with malignant gliomas.  Patients on this study will be treated in two groups: patients who
      are going to receive surgery and those who will not receive surgery. This study is trying to
      determine how effective BKM120 is in stopping cancer cells from growing.  For patients
      receiving surgery the research will also try to determine if an effective level of BKM120
      can penetrate the brain before surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For patients who will be having surgery, BKM will be taken orally for 8-12 days prior to
      surgery.  Prior to surgery they will have a FDG-PET scan and during surgery a sample of
      tumor will be taken for research.  Patients will resume oral BKM120 between 14 and 35 days
      after surgery.

      For patients who are not having surgery and post-surgery patients, BKM120 will be taken
      orally for 28 days (1 cycle).  Patients will continue on BKM120 as long as their brain tumor
      does not get worse and they do not have severe or intolerable side effects.

      During each cycle patients will have a physical examination, an assessment of tumor by MRI
      or CT, routine blood tests, questionnaires to assess mood, and research blood samples for
      genetic studies and other tests that will measure any additional effect of the study drug
      and disease status. Participants may also be required to undergo a electrocardiogram and/or
      MUGA scan to monitor heart function during the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort I: To evaluate PI3K pathway modulation of BKM120 in tumor tissue.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>PI3-Kinase pathway modulation will be measured using immunohistochemistry analyses of unstained tumor tissue to identify PI3-Kinase mutations including PIK3CA mutations, PTEN mutations, and PTEN deletion by immunohistochemistry. Expression of pAKT will also be analyzed using immunohistochemistry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort II: To investigate the treatment efficacy of BKM120 in participants with recurrent GBM as measured by 6-month progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Treatment efficacy will be based upon 6-month progression-free survival status. Progressive disease is defined using RANO (Response Assessment in Neuro-Oncology criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort I: To evaluate BKM120 concentration in tumor tissue, plasma, and cerebrospinal fluid.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood will be collected over various time points prior to surgery to determine individual pharmacokinetics.  During surgery, tumor tissue, plasma, and cerebrospinal fluid will be collected simultaneously. Tumor and plasma concentrations of the drug will be measured by liquid chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry to derive a tumor/plasma ratio.  Descriptive statistics (mean, SD, CV% or median (range)) will be performed on all plasma concentration-time data and derived PK parameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort I: To evaluate effects of BKM120 on tumor cell proliferation and tumor cell death</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Modulation in pAKT scoring as measured by reduction of staining intensity of one degree or more will be reported as consistent with a positive response to drug. In addition, participants will be independently scored as a positive response if a reduction in the percentage of pAKT positive cells within a tumor is greater than 50%, and therefore less likely due to normal geographic variation in positivity patterns. All pathway modulation scores will be correlated with effects on tumor growth by measuring Ki-67 (proliferation) and cleaved caspase 3 (CC3) (apoptosis/cell death).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort I: To investigate the safety profile of BKM120 in participants with recurrent GBM</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To assess the probability of toxicity associated with the treatment, the proportion of subjects with different grades of toxicities will be analyzed in order to further expand the safety profile for BKM120.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort I: To investigate pharmacokinetics of BKM120 in this population</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Pharmacokinetic parameters of BKM120 will be determined, either using a two-stage compartmental analysis or using a non-linear mixed-effect approach.  Pharmacokinetic parameters that will be derived include, but are not limited to oral drug clearance (CL/F), central and peripheral volume of distribution (V1 and V2) and absorption rate constant (Ka). Descriptive statistics (mean, SD, CV% or median (range)) will be performed on all plasma concentration-time data and derived PK parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort II: To investigate the radiographic response to BKM120</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Participants will be evaluated for radiographic response.  Response rate will be the proportion of participants with measurable disease who experience complete or partial radiographic response determined by the RANO Criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort II: To investigate median progression free survival and overall survival of participants with recurrent GBM receiving treatment with BKM120</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Median time to progression (defined using RANO criteria) and duration of survival will be measured in months for all enrolled cohort II participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I: Surgical subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects scheduled for surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II: Non-surgical subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects not candidates for surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BKM120</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg once daily, orally, for 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I: Surgical subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II: Non-surgical subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I: Surgical subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be able to understand and be willing to sign a written informed
             consent document.

          -  Subjects must be able to adhere to the dosing and visit schedules, and agree to
             record medication times accurately and consistently in a daily diary.

          -  Participants must be at least 18 years old.

          -  Participants must have a estimated life expectancy &gt; 8 weeks in the opinion of the
             clinician.

          -  Participants must have a Karnofsky performance status (KPS) ≥ 60. Nature of illness
             and treatment history

          -  Participants must have histologically confirmed glioblastoma or variants.
             Participants will be eligible if the original histology was low-grade glioma and a
             subsequent histological diagnosis of glioblastoma or variants is made.

          -  Participants may have had treatment for no more than 1 prior relapse(NOTE: Relapse is
             defined as progression following initial therapy (i.e., radiation ± chemotherapy)).
             The intent therefore is that patients  If the participant had a surgical resection
             for relapsed disease and no antitumor therapy was instituted for up to 12 weeks, and
             the participant undergoes another surgical resection, this is considered as a second
             relapse. For participants who had prior therapy for a low-grade glioma, the surgical
             diagnosis of a high-grade glioma will be considered the first relapse).

          -  Participants must have shown unequivocal evidence for tumor progression by MRI or CT
             scan.

          -  For Cohort 2, CT or MRI within 14 days prior to start of study drug. MRIs should
             include vascular imaging when possible.  For Cohort 2, corticosteroid dose must be
             stable or decreasing for at least 5 days prior to the scan. If steroids are added or
             the steroid dose is increased between the date of the screening MRI or CT scan and
             the start of treatment, a new baseline MRI or CT is required.  For Cohort 1 subjects,
             CT or MRI should be performed ideally within 14 days prior to study registration, but
             because the screening MRI for this subset of subjects will not be used for evaluation
             of response, it is acceptable for this MRI/CT to have been performed greater than 14
             days prior to registration if unavoidable. Furthermore, for this same reason,
             fluctuation in corticosteroid dose around this MRI does not warrant repeat scan so
             long as there is documented unequivocal evidence of tumor progression available.

          -  Immunohistochemical or genetic analysis on tumor tissue from a prior surgery must
             demonstrate activation of the PI3K pathway through one of the following: PIK3CA
             mutation of PIK3R1 mutation, PTEN negativity (&lt;10% of tumor cells staining) oh
             immunohistochemistry, PTEN mutation (any), homozygous deletion of PTEN

          -  Participants must have failed prior radiation therapy and must have an interval of at
             least 12 weeks from the completion of radiation therapy to study entry.

          -  Participants must have recovered to a grade 0 or 1 from the toxic effects of prior
             therapy (with the exception of lymphopenia which is common after therapy with
             temozolomide).

          -  From the projected start of scheduled study treatment, the following time periods
             must have elapsed: 4 weeks  or 5 half-lives (whichever is shorter)from any
             investigational agent, 4 weeks from cytotoxic therapy (except 23 days for
             temozolomide and 6 weeks from nitrosoureas), 6 weeks from antibodies, or 4  or 5
             half-lives (whichever is shorter) weeks from other anti-tumor therapies.

          -  Participants with prior therapy that included interstitial brachytherapy or
             stereotactic radiosurgery must have confirmation of progressive disease based upon
             nuclear imaging, MR spectroscopy, perfusion imaging or histopathology.

          -  Participants having undergone recent resection of recurrent or progressive tumor will
             be eligible for Cohort 2 as long as the following conditions apply: a) They have
             recovered from the effects of surgery; b)Residual disease following resection of
             recurrent tumor is not mandated for eligibility. To best assess the extent of
             residual disease postoperatively, an MRI or CT scan should ideally been performed  no
             later than 96 hours following surgery or at least 28-days postoperatively, but scans
             performed outside of this window are considered acceptable if no alternative is
             available. In either case, the baseline/screening MRI must be performed within 14
             days prior to registration. If the participant is taking corticosteroids, the dose
             must be stable or decreasing for at least 5 days prior to the scan. If steroids are
             added or the steroid dose is increased between the date of the screening MRI or CT
             scan and the start of treatment, a new baseline MRI or CT is required.

          -  Participants must have sufficient tissue from prior surgery for confirmation of
             diagnosis and correlative studies.  Submission of tissue is to occur within 30 days
             after registration.  The following amount of tissue is required: a) 25 unstained
             formalin fixed paraffin embedded (FFPE) sections (standard 4-5 micrometer thickness
             AND b)one of the following: i) At least 200 micrograms of frozen tissue OR ii)At
             least 10 (preferably 20) unstained FFPE sections of 10 micrometer thickness OR iii)
             At least 8 tissue cores from an FFPE block (200 micrometer total thickness of tissue
             from a block with a total surface area of 0.5 cm2)

          -  Clinical laboratory tests within 14 days prior to enrollment meeting the criteria
             listed in the protocol

          -  Cardiovascular assessment: baseline MUGA or Echocardiogram must demonstrate LVEF ≥ 50
             %

          -  Electrocardiogram must demonstrate QTc interval of less than 480 msec

          -  Women are considered post-menopausal and not of child bearing potential if they have
             had 12 months of natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea with appropriate clinical profile
             (e.g., age appropriate, history of vasomotor symptoms) or six months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea with serum FSH levels &gt; 40 mIU/mL and estradiol &lt; 20 pg/mL or have had
             surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without hysterectomy) at least six weeks
             ago. In the case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of the
             woman has been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment is she considered not
             of child bearing potential.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP), defined as all women physiologically
             capable of becoming pregnant, must use highly effective contraception (defined in
             protocol) during study treatment and for 16 weeks after study discontinuation.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             screening and within 48 hours prior to dosing with the study drug.

          -  Fertile males, defined as all males physiologically capable of conceiving offspring,
             must use condom during study treatment and for 16 weeks after study discontinuation
             and should not father a child in this period.

          -  Female partner of male study subject should use highly effective contraception while
             receiving study agent and for 16 weeks after final dose of study therapy.

        Cohort 1 Inclusion Criteria (In addition to the general eligibility criteria, participants
        in the Cohort 1 preoperative portion of the study must meet the following criteria on
        screening examination to be eligible):

          -  A participant who is deemed by the site Investigator to be an appropriate candidate
             for surgical resection may be enrolled in the Cohort 1 preoperative study.

          -  There must be sufficient recurrent tumor to allow at least 400mg of tissue to be
             collected ( 2 X 0.5 cm3) for pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic analysis.

          -  Immunohistochemical analysis on tumor tissue from an earlier surgery indicating pAKT
             positive (1-2+ on a 0-2+ scale). Patients may also have one of the other criteria
             listed for Cohort 2 but they are not mandatory.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who have received prior treatment with a P13K inhibitor, AKT inhibitor,
             mTOR inhibitor (e.g. rapamycin, MK2206, perifosine etc.).

          -  Participants who have received anti-angiogenic or anti-VEGF targeted agents (e.g.
             bevacizumab, cediranib, aflibercept, vandetanib, XL184, sunitinib etc).

          -  Participants taking an enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drug (EIAED): phenobarbital,
             phenytoin, fosphenytoin, primidone, carbamazepine, oxcarbazepine, eslicarbazepine,
             rufinamide, felbamate, and topiramate (only when daily dose exceeds 200 mg).
             Participant must be off any EIAEDs for at least two weeks prior to starting study
             drug.  A list of EIAED and other inducers of CYP3A4 is provided in Table C-3 of
             Appendix C of the protocol.

          -  Participants taking a drug known to be moderate and strong inhibitors or inducers of
             isoenzyme CYP3A (Appendix C). Participant must be off CYP3A inhibitors and inducers
             for at least two weeks prior to starting study drug. NOTE: participants must avoid
             consumption of Seville orange (and juice), grapefruit or grapefruit juice, grapefruit
             hybrids, pummelos and exotic citrus fruits from 7 days prior to the first dose of
             study drug and during the entire study treatment period due to potential CYP3A4
             interaction.

          -  Requirement of more than 8mg of dexamethasone daily.

          -  Participants taking drugs with known risk to promote QT prolongation and Torsades de
             Pointes (refer to protocol).

          -  Participants receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Current use of herbal preparations/medications, including but not limited to: St.
             John's wort, Kava, ephedra (ma huang), gingko biloba, dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA),
             yohimbe, saw palmetto, ginseng. Participants should stop using these herbal
             medications 7 days prior to first dose of study drug.

          -  Current use of warfarin sodium or any other coumadin-derivative anticoagulant.
             Participant must be off Coumadin-derivative anticoagulants for at least seven days
             prior to starting study drug. Low molecular weight heparin is allowed.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to BKM120.

          -  History of intratumoral or peritumoral hemorrhage if deemed significant by the
             treating physician.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, chronic liver disease (e.g., cirrhosis, hepatitis), chronic renal disease,
             pancreatitis, chronic pulmonary disease, or psychiatric illness/social situations
             that would limit compliance with study requirements. Subjects must be free of any
             clinically relevant disease (other than glioma) that would, in the Investigator's
             opinion, interfere with the conduct of the study or study evaluations.

          -  Individuals with a history of a different malignancy except for the following
             circumstances: if they have been disease-free for at least 3 years and are deemed by
             the investigator to be at low risk for recurrence of that malignancy, individuals
             with the following cancers are eligible if diagnosed and treated within the past 3
             years: cervical cancer in situ, and basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the
             skin.

          -  Known diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection

          -  Participants with history of protocol specified mood disorders as judged by the
             Investigator or a psychiatrist, or as result of participant's screening mood
             assessment questionnaire

          -  Participants with diarrhea ≥ CTCAE grade 2

          -  Participant has active cardiac disease including any of the following: Angina
             pectoris that requires the use of anti-anginal medications; Ventricular arrhythmias
             except for benign premature ventricular contractions; Supraventricular and nodal
             arrythmias requiring a pacemaker or not controlled with medication; Conduction
             abnormality requiring a pacemaker; Valvular disease with document compromise in
             cardiac function; Symptomatic pericarditis

          -  Participant has a history of cardiac dysfunction including any of the following:
             Myocardial infraction within the last 6 months, documented by persistent elevated
             cardiac enzymes or persistent regional wall abnormalities on assessment of LVEF
             function; History of documented congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association
             functional classification III-IV; c)Documented cardiomyopathy; d) Congenital long QT
             syndrome

          -  Participants with poorly controlled diabetes mellitus (glycosylated hemoglobin &gt; 8%)
             or poorly controlled steroid-induced diabetes mellitus (glycosylated hemoglobin &gt; 8%)

          -  Impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may significantly
             alter the absorption of BKM120 (e.g., ulcerative diseases, uncontrolled nausea,
             vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or extensive small bowel resection).
             Participants with unresolved diarrhea will be excluded as previously indicated.

          -  Participants who have undergone major systemic surgery ≤ 2 weeks prior to starting
             study drug or who have not recovered from side effects of such therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Y Wen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrick Y Wen, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>617-632-2166</phone>
    <email>Patrick_Wen@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emese Filka</last_name>
      <phone>310-794-3521</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Cloughesy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emelia Clow, RN</last_name>
      <phone>415-353-2652</phone>
      <email>ClowE@neurosurg.ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael D Prados</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Doherty, NP</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-5925</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick Y Wen, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Hahn, RN</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-9579</phone>
      <email>shahn16@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Chi, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ingo Mellinghoff, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-2766</phone>
      <email>mellingi@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ingo Mellinghoff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT, MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Be-Lian Pei, RN, BSN, CRRN</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-1496</phone>
      <email>BPei@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>WK Alfred Yung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute, University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amiee Maxwell</last_name>
      <phone>801-587-5562</phone>
      <email>Amiee.Maxwell@hci.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Howard Colman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 24, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 18, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber/Brigham and Women's Cancer Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Patrick Y. Wen, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Center For Neuro-Oncology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>BKM120</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
