<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="311">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00939770</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000647587</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>COG-ADVL0912</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00939770</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT01182896</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Crizotinib in Treating Young Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Solid Tumors or Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of PF-02341066, an Oral Small Molecule Inhibitor of Anaplastic Lymphoma Kinase (ALK) and c-Met, in Children With Relapsed/Refractory Solid Tumors, Primary CNS Tumors, and Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Unspecified</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Crizotinib may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth.

      PURPOSE: This phase I/II trial is studying the side effects and best dose of crizotinib and
      to see how well it works in treating young patients with relapsed or refractory solid tumors
      or anaplastic large cell lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To estimate the maximum-tolerated dose and recommended phase II dose of crizotinib
           administered orally twice daily to children with relapsed or refractory solid tumors or
           anaplastic large cell lymphoma (ALCL).

        -  To define and describe the toxicities of this drug when administered on this schedule.

        -  To characterize the pharmacokinetics of this drug in these patients.

      Secondary

        -  To preliminarily define the antitumor activity of this drug within the confines of a
           phase I study.

        -  To obtain initial phase II data on the antitumor activity of this drug in children with
           relapsed or refractory neuroblastoma or ALCL.

        -  To preliminarily examine the relationship between response to treatment and anaplastic
           lymphoma kinase gene status (e.g., the presence of a mutation, duplication,
           amplification, and/or translocation) in children with relapsed or refractory
           neuroblastoma or ALCL.

        -  To preliminarily examine the relationship between minimal residual disease status and
           clinical response to treatment in children with ALCL.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter, phase I dose-escalation study followed by a phase II study.

      Patients receive oral crizotinib twice daily on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days
      in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Plasma and whole blood samples are collected for pharmacokinetic and pharmacogenomic
      analysis. Tumor tissue (from patients with neuroblastoma) and bone marrow and/or peripheral
      blood (from patients with anaplastic large cell lymphoma) samples are collected for further
      correlative laboratory studies.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up periodically.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum-tolerated dose and recommended phase II dose of crizotinib in children with relapsed or refractory solid tumors or anaplastic large cell lymphoma (ALCL)</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicities of crizotinib</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of crizotinib</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antitumor activity of crizotinib in children with relapsed or refractory solid tumors or ALCL</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antitumor activity of crizotinib in children with relapsed or refractory neuroblastoma or ALCL</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between response to treatment and anaplastic lymphoma kinase gene status in children with relapsed or refractory neuroblastoma or ALCL</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between minimal residual disease status and clinical response to treatment in children with ALCL</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">196</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Neuroblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Childhood Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>crizotinib</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacogenomic studies</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically confirmed* malignancy at original diagnosis or relapse, including the
             following:

               -  Solid tumors (phase I)

               -  CNS tumors (phase I)

                    -  Neurologic deficits must have been relatively stable for ≥ 1 week before
                       study enrollment

               -  Anaplastic large cell lymphoma (ALCL) (phase I or II)

                    -  No primary cutaneous ALCL

               -  Confirmed anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) fusion proteins, ALK mutations, or
                  ALK amplification (defined as &gt; 4-fold increase in the ALK signal number as
                  compared to reference signal number on chromosome 2q arm) (phase I)

               -  Neuroblastoma (phase I or II) NOTE: *Histologic confirmation is not required for
                  patients with diffuse intrinsic brain stem tumors, optic pathway tumors, or
                  pineal region tumors with elevations of serum or CSF tumor markers (e.g.,
                  alpha-fetoprotein or beta-HCG).

          -  Relapsed or refractory disease

          -  Measurable and/or evaluable disease

               -  Patients with neuroblastoma must have measurable tumor on MRI, CT scan, or x-ray
                  obtained within the past 2 weeks and/or evaluable tumor by MIBG scan and/or bone
                  marrow involvement with tumor cells seen on routine morphology

               -  Patients with ALCL enrolled in the phase II portion of the trial must have
                  measurable disease

          -  No known curative therapy or therapy proven to prolong survival with an acceptable
             quality of life exists

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Karnofsky performance status (PS) 50-100% (for patients &gt; 16 years of age) or Lansky
             PS 50-100% (for patients ≤ 16 years of age)

               -  Patients who are up in a wheelchair and are unable to walk due to paralysis will
                  be considered ambulatory for the purpose of assessing PS

          -  ANC ≥ 1,000/mm^3 (≥ 750/mm^3 in patients with metastatic bone marrow disease)

          -  Platelet count ≥ 75,000/mm^3 (transfusion independent, defined as no platelet
             transfusions within the past 7 days) in patients without bone marrow involvement OR ≥
             25,000/mm^3 (platelet transfusions allowed) in patients with metastatic bone marrow
             disease

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 8.0 g/dL (RBC transfusions allowed)

          -  Creatinine clearance or radioisotope GFR ≥ 70 mL/min OR serum creatinine based on
             age/gender as follows:

               -  ≤ 0.6 mg/dL (for patients 1 year of age)

               -  ≤ 0.8 mg/dL (for patients 2 to 5 years of age)

               -  ≤ 1.0 mg/dL (for patients 6 to 9 years of age)

               -  ≤ 1.2 mg/dL (for patients 10 to 12 years of age)

               -  ≤ 1.4 mg/dL (for female patients ≥ 13 years of age)

               -  ≤ 1.5 mg/dL (for male patients 13 to 15 years of age)

               -  ≤ 1.7 mg/dL (for male patients ≥ 16 years of age)

          -  Bilirubin (sum of conjugated and unconjugated) ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal for
             age

          -  SGPT ≤ 110 U/L

          -  Serum albumin ≥ 2 g/dL

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception

          -  Body surface area ≥ 0.4 mm² (for patients enrolled at dose levels 0 and 1 only)

          -  Able to swallow capsules or a liquid suspension/solution

          -  Able to comply with the safety monitoring requirements of the study, in the opinion
             of the investigator

          -  No uncontrolled infection

          -  No evidence of active graft vs host disease

          -  Not refractory to red cell or platelet transfusion (in patients with metastatic bone
             marrow disease)

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  Recovered from prior chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or radiotherapy

          -  No prior crizotinib

          -  At least 6 months since prior total-body radiotherapy (TBI), craniospinal
             radiotherapy, or radiotherapy to ≥ 50% of the pelvis

          -  At least 3 months since prior bone marrow or stem cell transplant (without TBI) (≥ 6
             weeks for patients with neuroblastoma or patients with confirmed ALK fusion proteins,
             ALK mutations, or ALK amplification)

               -  No evidence of active graft-vs-host disease

          -  At least 6 weeks since prior therapeutic doses of MIBG

          -  At least 6 weeks since other prior substantial bone marrow radiotherapy

          -  At least 2 weeks since prior local palliative radiotherapy (small port)

          -  More than 3 weeks since prior myelosuppressive chemotherapy (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas) for patients with solid tumors

          -  At least 14 days since prior cytotoxic therapy for patients with ALCL who relapse
             while receiving cytotoxic therapy

               -  Patients with lymphoma who relapse during standard maintenance therapy are
                  eligible at time of relapse

               -  Cytoreduction with hydroxyurea may be initiated and continued for up to 24 hours
                  before the start of study treatment

          -  At least 7 days since prior growth factor therapy

          -  At least 7 days since prior biological agents

          -  At least 7 days or 3 half-lives (whichever is longer) since prior monoclonal antibody

          -  More than 12 days since prior and no concurrent potent CYP3A4 inducers including, but
             not limited to carbamazepine, phenobarbital, phenytoin, rifabutin, rifampin,
             tipranavir, ritonavir, or St. John wort

          -  More than 7 days since prior and no concurrent potent CYP3A4 inhibitors including,
             but not limited to ketoconazole, itraconazole, miconazole, clarithromycin,
             erythromycin, ritonavir, indinavir, nelfinavir, saquinavir, amprenavir, delavirdine,
             nefazodone, diltiazem, verapamil, or grapefruit juice

          -  No concurrent medications known to be metabolized by CYP3A4 with narrow therapeutic
             indices, including pimozide, aripiprazole, triazolam, ergotamine, and halofantrine

          -  No other concurrent anticancer therapy (including chemotherapy, radiotherapy,
             immunotherapy, or biologic therapy), except for hydroxyurea for patients with ALCL or
             decadron for patients with CNS tumors

          -  No other concurrent investigational drugs

          -  Concurrent corticosteroids for CNS tumors allowed provided the dose has been stable
             or decreasing for the past 7 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yael P. Mosse, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UAB Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - UAB Comprehensive Cancer Center</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-0309</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Orange County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Violet Shen</last_name>
      <phone>714-532-8636</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical  Trials Office - UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensi</last_name>
      <phone>877-827-3222</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Colorado Center for Cancer and Blood Disorders</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly W. Maloney</last_name>
      <phone>720-777-6673</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010-2970</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Children's National Medical Center</last_name>
      <phone>202-884-2549</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AFLAC Cancer Center and Blood Disorders Service of Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Todd M. Cooper</last_name>
      <phone>404-785-1838</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Memorial Hospital - Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stewart Goldman</last_name>
      <phone>312-227-4844</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Riley's Children Cancer Center at Riley Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James M. Croop</last_name>
      <phone>317-944-8784</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Warren Grant Magnuson Clinical Center - NCI Clinical Trials Referral Office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892-1182</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Warren Grant Magnusen Clinical Center</last_name>
      <phone>888-NCI-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber/Harvard Cancer Center at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>2115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carlos Rodriguez-Galindo</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-4580</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>C.S. Mott Children's Hospital at University of Michigan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-0286</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - C.S. Mott Children's Hospital</last_name>
      <phone>800-865-1125</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Masonic Cancer Center at University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Masonic Cancer Center at University o</last_name>
      <phone>612-624-2620</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital - Saint Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert J. Hayashi</last_name>
      <phone>314-454-2041</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center at Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer C</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-8615</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229-3039</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medica</last_name>
      <phone>513-636-2799</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205-2696</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura T. Martin</last_name>
      <phone>614-722-3582</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Knight Cancer Institute at Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239-3098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Knight Cancer Institute at Oregon Hea</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-1080</phone>
      <email>trials@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Fox</last_name>
      <phone>267-425-3010</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh</last_name>
      <phone>412-692-7056</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</last_name>
      <phone>901-595-4644</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-6838</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center</last_name>
      <phone>800-811-8480</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Simmons Comprehensive Cancer Center at University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center - Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - Simmons Comprehensive Cancer Center a</last_name>
      <phone>866-460-4673; 214-648-7097</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor University Medical Center - Houston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030-2399</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrick A. Thompson</last_name>
      <phone>832-824-4029</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital and Regional Medical Center - Seattle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie R. Park</last_name>
      <phone>206-987-2106</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Children's Cancer Center at Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael E. Kelly</last_name>
      <phone>414-456-4170</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital for Sick Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sylvain Baruchel</last_name>
      <phone>416-813-7795</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/COG-ADVL0912</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 11, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 14, 2009</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Susan M. Blaney</name_title>
    <organization>Texas Children's Cancer Center and Hematology Service at Texas Children's Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>unspecified childhood solid tumor, protocol specific</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent neuroblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood anaplastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood brain stem glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood cerebellar astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood cerebral astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood anaplastic astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood anaplastic oligoastrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood anaplastic oligodendroglioma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood fibrillary astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood gemistocytic astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood gliomatosis cerebri</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood oligoastrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood oligodendroglioma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood pilocytic astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood pilomyxoid astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood protoplasmic astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood subependymal giant cell astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood visual pathway and hypothalamic glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood visual pathway glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood medulloblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood ependymoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood pineoblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood choroid plexus tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood craniopharyngioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood ependymoblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood medulloepithelioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood grade I meningioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood grade II meningioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood grade III meningioma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood central nervous system germ cell tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent childhood spinal cord neoplasm</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood infratentorial ependymoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood supratentorial ependymoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood high-grade cerebellar astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood high-grade cerebral astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood low-grade cerebellar astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood low-grade cerebral astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Anaplastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
