<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="276">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01290263</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-185</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01290263</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Amgen 386 for Recurrent Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Study of Amgen 386 With and Without Bevacizumab for Recurrent Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives

      Cohort A ‐‐ monotherapy:

      To determine the efficacy of AMG 386 in participants with recurrent glioblastoma (GBM) as
      measured by 6‐month progression‐free survival (PFS6)

      Cohort B - combination therapy:

      Phase I To determine the maximum tolerated dose of AMG 386 in combination with bevacizumab
      given at 10mg/kg every 2 weeks in participants with recurrent glioblastoma.

      Phase II To determine the efficacy of AMG 386 plus bevacizumab in participants with
      recurrent glioblastoma (GBM) as measured by 6‐month progression‐free survival (PFS6).

      Secondary Objectives:

      To evaluate radiographic response in both cohort populations. To evaluate overall survival
      in both cohort populations. To assess time‐to‐progression in both cohort populations. To
      investigate the safety profile in both cohort populations.

      Exploratory Objectives:

      To evaluate expression of factors associated with tumor angiogenesis using a multiples
      cytokine assay among participants undergoing therapy with AMG 386 with response to therapy
      and development of resistance.

      This is an open‐label Phase I/II study of AMG 386 monotherapy and AMG 386 in combination
      with bevacizumab. Two cohorts will accrue and will be assessed sequentially. Each cohort
      will enroll participants with recurrent GBM. Cohort A will assess recurrent GBM participants
      who receive AMG 386 monotherapy at 30 g/kg every week. (Cohort A initially accrued at a dose
      of 15mg/kg, but this was increased to 30 mg/kg every week following an amendment). Cohort B
      will assess recurrent GBM participants who receive weekly AMG 386 plus bi‐weekly bevacizumab
      (10mg/kg). Cohort B will start with a Phase I component to determine the MTD of AMG 386 that
      is safe when used in combination with bevacizumab. AMG 386 is administered intravenously,
      and, when used in combination with intravenous bevacizumab, will be administered first.

      Patients will be required to come to the clinic weekly for study drug administration.

      For study purposes, a cycle of therapy will be 4 weeks. Treatment will continue until either
      evidence of progressive disease, unacceptable toxicity, non‐compliance with study follow‐up,
      or withdrawal of consent.

      The estimated rate of accrual is 60 participants per year. The estimated date of accrual
      completion is 1.5 years from study initiation. The estimated date of study completion will
      be approximately 12 months from enrollment of the last study participant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiological response rates</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary outcome is 6 month progression-free survival. The primary basis for assessing efficacy will be the proportion of patients who survive 6 months without disease progression (PFS-6).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic response and Median progression free survival and overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Median progression free survival and overall survival. The primary measure of safety outcome will include a tabulation of all grade 2 or greater, treatment related toxicities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amgen 386</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort A will assess recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM) patients who receive AMG 386 monotherapy. For each cohort, AMG 386 will be administered intravenously at 15 mg/kg every week. The dose of bevacizumab will be 10 mg/kg and will be administered intravenously every other week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amgen 386 and Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort B will assess recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme(GBM) patients who receive AMG 386 plus bevacizumab. For each cohort, AMG 386 will be administered intravenously at 15 mg/kg every week. The dose of bevacizumab will be 10 mg/kg and will be administered intravenously every other week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amgen 386</intervention_name>
    <description>For each cohort, AMG 386 will be administered intravenously at 15 mg/kg every week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amgen 386</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Amgen 386 and Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>The dose of bevacizumab will be 10 mg/kg and will be administered intravenously every other week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amgen 386 and Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Avastin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Signed informed consent approved by the Institutional Review Board prior to
             participant entry

          -  Age ≥ 18 years.

          -  Karnofsky ≥ 70%

          -  Participant must be able and willing to comply with study and/or follow‐up procedures
             Participants must have histologically confirmed diagnosis of GBM patients with either
             grade III or IV malignant glioma are eligible to the Phase I portion of the study)
             and radiographic evidence of recurrence or disease  progression (defined as either a
             greater than 25% increase in the largest bidimensional product of enhancement, a new
             enhancing lesion, or significant increase in T2 FLAIR) following prior therapy (i.e.
             chemotherapy, XRT, other investigational therapies).

          -  No more than 3 prior episodes of progressive disease (patients with more than 3 prior
             episodes of progressive disease are eligible for the Phase I portion of this study)

          -  An interval of at least 4 weeks (to start of study agent) between prior surgical
             resection or one week from stereotactic biopsy

          -  An interval of at least 12 weeks (to start of study agent) from the end of prior
             radiotherapy unless there is a new area of enhancement consistent with recurrent
             tumor outside of the radiation field, or there is histological confirmation of
             unequivocal tumor progression

          -  From the projected start of scheduled study treatment, the following time periods
             must have relapsed: 4 weeks from any investigational agent, 4 weeks from cytotoxic
             therapy (except 23 days for temozolomide and 6 weeks from  nitrosoureas), 6 weeks
             from antibodies, or 4 weeks from other anti‐tumor therapies.

          -  Participants must have recovered to a grade 0 or 1 from the toxic effects of prior
             therapy (with the exception of lymphopenia, which is common after therapy with
             temozolomide, and alopecia).

          -  No evidence of hemorrhage on the baseline MRI or CT scan other than those that are ≤
             grade 1 and either post‐operative or stable on at least two consecutive scans.
             Clinical Labs - performed within 14 days prior to enrollment

          -  Hematocrit &gt; 29%, ANC &gt; 1,000 cells/μl, platelets &gt; 100,000 cells/μl ;

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dl, serum SGOT and bilirubin &lt; 2.5 times upper limit of
             normal;

          -  PTT or aPTT ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal and INR ≤ 1.5

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 40 mL/min according to the Cockcroft‐Gault formula
             OR per 24 hour urine collection

          -  Urinary protein quantitative value of &lt; 30 mg/dL in urinalysis or &lt;1+ on dipstick,
             unless quantitative protein is &lt; 1000 mg in a 24 hour urine sample;

          -  Participants of child‐bearing potential who have not undergone a bilateral
             salpingo‐oopherectomy and are sexually active must consent to use an accepted and
             highly effective non‐hormonal method of contraception (i.e. double barrier method
             [e.g., condom plus diaphragm]) from signing the informed consent through 6 months
             after last dose of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior anti‐angiogenic therapy targeting VEGF or VEGF receptor including prior
             bevacizumab.

          -  Prior AMG 386 therapy or other molecules that inhibit the angiopoietins or Tie2
             receptor.

          -  Co‐medication that may interfere with study results; e.g. immunosuppressive agents
             other than corticosteroids.

          -  Active infection requiring intravenous antibiotics

          -  Current or within 30 days prior to enrollment treatment with immune modulators such
             as systemic cyclosporine and tacrilomus.

          -  Current us of warfarin sodium or any other Coumadin‐derivative anticoagulant.
             Participant must be off Coumadin‐derivative anticoagulants for at least seven days
             prior to starting study drug. ow molecular weight heparin is allowed.

          -  Current, recent (within 4 weeks of the first infusion of this study), or planned
             participation in an experimental drug study other than supportive care or
             epidemiologic studies.

          -  History of clinically significant bleeding within 6 months of enrollment

          -  History of allergic reactions to bacterially produced proteins

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any component of bevacizumab (cohort B only)

          -  Known sensitivity to any of the products to be administered during dosing

          -  History of venous or arterial thromboembolism within 12 months prior to enrollment.

          -  Severe hepatic insufficiency (ongoing grade 3 or greater hepatic adverse events) or
             known active chronic hepatitis.

          -  Inadequately controlled hypertension (defined as systolic blood pressure &gt;140 and/or
             diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90 mmHg). The use of anti‐hypertensive medications to
             control hypertension is permitted.

          -  Any prior history of hypertensive crisis or hypertensive encephalopathy

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease within 12 months prior to enrollment,
             including myocardial infarction, unstable angina, grade 2 or greater peripheral
             vascular disease, cerebrovascular accident, transient ischemic attack, congestive
             heart failure, or arrhythmias not controlled by  outpatient medication, percutaneous
             transluminal coronary angioplasty/stent.

          -  Evidence of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy

          -  Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury within 28 days
             prior to study enrollment or anticipation of need for major surgical procedure during
             the course of the study

          -  Core biopsy or other minor surgical procedure, excluding placement of a vascular
             access device, within 7 days prior to study enrollment.

          -  History of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra-abdominal
             abscess within 6 months prior to study enrollment.

          -  Serious, non‐healing wound, ulcer (including gastrointestinal), or bone fracture.

          -  Any condition which in the investigator's opinion makes the subject unsuitable for
             study participation.

          -  Pregnant (positive pregnancy test) or lactating. Refusal or inability to use highly
             effective means of contraception (men and women) in participants of child‐bearing
             potential.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Reardon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Reardon, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>617-632-2166</phone>
    <email>dreardon3@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Cloughesy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Doherty, N.P.</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-5925</phone>
      <email>Lisa_Doherty@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jennifer Rifenburg, N.P.</last_name>
      <phone>617-582-8644</phone>
      <email>Jennifer_Rifenburg@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David A. Reardon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hosptial</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Faye Safavi</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-1990</phone>
      <email>fsafavi@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth R. Gerstner, MD, MMSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York - Presbyterian/Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francine Armentano, NP, NP</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-5969</phone>
      <email>fa2301@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew B. Lassman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fabio Iwamoto, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Monika Thielen</last_name>
      <phone>434-243-9900</phone>
      <email>MJT3C@hscmail.mcc.virginia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Schiff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 2, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 9, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Reardon, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>GBM</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
