<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="38">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00659126</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OHSU-2864</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5R01NS053468-02</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2864</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SOL-06077-L</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00659126</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ferumoxytol and Gadolinium Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) at 3T and 7T in Patients With Malignant Brain Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Ferumoxytol and Gadolinium Magnetic Resonance Imaging at 3T and 7T in Patients With Malignant Brain Tumors Either Before or After Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study the investigators would like to compare special magnetic resonance (MR) brain
      imaging techniques (called: dynamic perfusion, blood-brain barrier (BBB) permeability
      measurement) in two different magnetic fields (3 and 7 Tesla) in the evaluation of brain
      tumors. Two contrast agents will be used; the standard gadolinium, and ferumoxytol, a new,
      iron containing agent. The investigators think that these new methods will give us better
      assessment of brain tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will be scanned either before or after treatment (radiation and/or chemotherapy).
      There will be three visits on three consecutive days. On first day: MRI with and without
      gadolinium (the usual MR contrast agent) infusion (0.1 mmol/kg). On second day: MRI with
      ferumoxytol infusion (4 mg/kg). On the third day: MRI without additional contrast agent, 24
      hr post ferumoxytol infusion. On the first and third day scans will be done in both magnets,
      on the second day scans will be done either on 3T or 7T.

      Various types of MR measurements (Perfusion, blood-brain barrier permeability, tumor volume)
      will be measured using both contrast agents, in 3 and/or 7 Tesla. Certain regions will be
      described and the data will be evaluated throughout the study. The tumor volume will be
      evaluated by 2 radiologists, measuring the diameters of the largest areas of contrast
      enhancement and signal intensities will be also compared (semi-quantitatively).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objective of this project is to compare quantitative imaging measures of brain tumor vascularity obtained from 3 T and 7T MRI instruments</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare blood brain barrier permeabilities of Ferumoxytol and a standard  gadolinium based MRI contrast agent.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare cerebral blood volume (CBV) measurements obtained using a standard gadolinium MRI contrast agent and ferumoxytol CBV will be quantified using dynamic susceptibility contrast (DSC) techniques using both Gd and Ferumoxytol contrast agents.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare perfusion and permeability parameters between treated and untreated patients</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the microscopic distribution of ferumoxytol particles in tissue removed from patients undergoing surgery. .</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>MR imaging at 3T</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>MR imaging at 7T</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferumoxytol</intervention_name>
    <description>4mg/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ferumoxytol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed primary malignant brain
             tumors or brain metastasis

          -  Patients must have had radiographically evaluable or measurable disease with standard
             MR imaging, and the tumor must have an enhancing component.

          -  Patients may or may not have had prior surgery, radiation therapy, or chemotherapy.

          -  Age &gt;18 years

          -  Men and women and members of all races and ethnic groups will be included.

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 2 weeks.

          -  ECOG performance status &lt; 3.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document, or have a representative able to consent for the patient.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with clinically significant signs of uncal herniation

          -  Subjects who have a contraindication for MRI

          -  Subjects with known hepatic insufficiency or cirrhosis

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to ferumoxytol

          -  Subjects with known or suspected iron overload (genetic hemochromatosis or history of
             multiple transfusions)

          -  Patients expecting to undergo surgery between the imaging sessions.  Patients may
             undergo surgery at any time before the first, or after the last imaging session.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women are excluded from this study because of possible risk to
             the fetus or infant.

          -  Inability or unwillingness to undergo the complete series of imaging sessions.
             Inability or unwillingness to return to the neuro-oncology clinic at OHSU for the one
             month follow-up.

          -  Known immunosuppression or immunodeficiency.

          -  Patients with stage IV or V renal insufficiency.

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
    <email>neuwelte@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cynthia A Lacy, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
    <email>lacyc@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>April 10, 2008</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ferumoxytol</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic imaging</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ferumoxytol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
