<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="43">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00103038</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OHSU-813</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>3ROI CA 137488 15S1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>OHSU-813</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>OHSU-8097</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ONC-03095-LX</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00103038</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00980720</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MRI Using Ferumoxytol in Patients With Primary Brain Cancer or Brain Metastases</brief_title>
  <official_title>NCI-Sponsored Multidisciplinary Study of MR Imaging of Intravenous Superparamagnetic Crystalline Particle Ferumoxytol in Primary High-grade Brain Tumors and/or Cerebral Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol revision seeks to expand upon the data originally collected from 12 patients
      who received ferumoxytol. The results of the original protocol were published in 2007 in
      Neurosurgery. We found that maximal ferumoxytol enhancement intensity occurred at 24 to 28
      hours after administration, and the enhancing volume subsequently expanded with time into a
      non-gadolinium-enhancing, high T2-weighted signal region of tumor-infiltrated brain. Dynamic
      studies were assessed with both agents and demonstrated that gadolinium leaks out of blood
      vessels early after injection, whereas ferumoxytol stays intravascular in the &quot;early&quot; phase,
      thereby increasing the accuracy of tumor perfusion assessment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This protocol revision to the preliminary trial will characterize vascular properties of
      tumors in the CNS using ferumoxytol for DSC MRI to compare with those obtained using GBCA
      for DCE in a single MR imaging session. Furthermore, these imaging properties of various
      malignant CNS tumors will be characterized longitudinally with up to 6 imaging session over
      approximately 5 years. The information obtained in this study may guide the creation of a
      new imaging criteria to evaluate tumor progression and pseudoprogression secondary to
      Radiochemotherapy (RCT) in the context of wide-spread use of antiangiogenic agents. We
      expect that characterizing the vascular properties of tumors in the CNS using ferumoxytol
      for DSC MRI in order to compare with those obtained using GBCA for DCE MRI, will be
      achievable as in a single imaging session.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigate the utility of ferumoxytol and GBCA for improved imaging biomarkers of malignant brain tumors in a single imaging session by comparing DSC determined rCBV and DCE determined vascular permeability (Ktrans).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare and evaluate MRA with ferumoxytol between different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess number and size of tumors imaged</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess tumor vascularity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess histology and EM on tissue samples</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess differences in patients with prior therapy vs. no prior therapy (radiation and/or chemotherapy)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the long term imaging characteristics of different tumors using DSC and DCE.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MR imaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ferumoxytol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ferumoxytol</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose: 4 mg Fe/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>MR imaging</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Feraheme</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults must have either radiological or established histological diagnosis of the
             following general categories: high-grade glioma/CNS lymphoma or brain metastases.

          -  Previously untreated patients must have a lesion on an imaging study

          -  Post treatment patients will have radiographic abnormalities that may or may not be
             recurrent tumor

          -  Patients must be 18 years or older for inclusion in this study.

          -  After entry into the study, patients are expected to be followed for approximately
             4-6 weeks after the final infusion of ferumoxytol.

          -  All patients, or their legal guardians, must sign a written informed consent and
             HIPAA authorization in accordance with institutional guidelines.

          -  Sexually active women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
             contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; or abstinence) prior to
             study treatment and for the duration of study treatment. Should a female become
             pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she should
             inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  Pre-treatment radiological scans/studies for patients receiving ferumoxytol must be
             performed with approximately 16 weeks prior to study entry.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with clinically significant signs of uncal herniation, such as acute
             pupillary enlargement, rapidly developing motor changes (over hours), or rapidly
             decreasing level of consciousness

          -  Patients with known allergic or hypersensitivity reactions to parenteral iron,
             parenteral dextran, parenteral iron-dextran, or parenteral iron-polysaccharide
             preparations (Ferumoxytol Investigator's Drug Brochure, 2009). Patients with
             significant drug or other allergies or autoimmune diseases may be enrolled at the
             investigator's discretion.

          -  Patients who are pregnant or lactating or who suspect they might be pregnant.

          -  Adult patients who require monitored anesthesia for MRI scanning

          -  Patients with renal insufficiency; GFR &lt; 50.

          -  Subjects who have a contraindication for MRI: metal in their bodies (a cardiac
             pacemaker or other incompatible device), are severely agitated, or have an allergy to
             Gd contrast material.

          -  Subjects with known hepatic insufficiency or cirrhosis.

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of
             the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with ferumoxytol.

          -  Subjects with known or suspected iron overload (genetic hemochromatosis or history of
             multiple transfusions).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edward A. Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
    <email>neuwelte@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cynthia A Lacy, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
    <email>lacyc@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239-3098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Knight Clinical Trials Hotline</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-1080</phone>
      <email>trials@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 7, 2005</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ferumoxytol</keyword>
  <keyword>diagnostic imaging</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ferumoxytol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
