<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="187">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01305941</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCCC 1025</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-0242</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01305941</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Of Everolimus, Trastuzumab And Vinorelbine In HER2-Positive Breast Cancer Brain Metastases</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study Evaluating The Efficacy And Tolerability Of Everolimus (RAD001) In Combination With Trastuzumab And Vinorelbine In The Treatment Of Progressive HER2-Positive Breast Cancer Brain Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose:  This study is a single-arm, open-label phase II clinical trial testing the
      hypothesis that daily everolimus plus weekly vinorelbine and trastuzumab will be effective,
      safe, and tolerable among patients with HER2-positive breast cancer brain metastases.   Once
      enrolled, patients will receive everolimus PO daily in combination with weekly intravenous
      (IV) vinorelbine and trastuzumab.  Cycles will be repeated every 3 weeks (21 days).  At the
      time of progression, patients will come off study.

      Participants:  Up to 35 adults over 21 with HER-2 positive breast cancer that has
      metastasized to the brain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY OBJECTIVES Primary Objective -To determine the intracranial objective response rate of
      mTOR inhibition (everolimus) in combination with vinorelbine and trastuzumab in the
      treatment of HER2-positive, progressive breast cancer brain metastases as defined via
      modified RECIST criteria.

      Secondary Objectives

        -  To determine the intracranial objective response rate of mTOR inhibition (everolimus)
           in combination with vinorelbine and trastuzumab in the treatment of HER2-positive,
           progressive breast cancer brain metastases as defined by MacDonald criteria.

        -  To evaluate the safety and tolerability of everolimus in combination with trastuzumab
           and vinorelbine as assessed via the NCI CTCAE version 4.0

        -  To evaluate time to intracranial progression after administration of everolimus in
           combination with trastuzumab and vinorelbine as defined via modified RECIST criteria

        -  To evaluate the extracranial objective response rate as determined by RECIST 1.1
           criteria after administration of everolimus in combination with trastuzumab and
           vinorelbine.

        -  To evaluate the extracranial time to progression as determined by RECIST 1.1 criteria
           after administration of everolimus in combination with trastuzumab and vinorelbine.

        -  To evaluate progression free survival (PFS) and overall survival (OS) after
           administration of everolimus in combination with trastuzumab and vinorelbine.

        -  To evaluate the impact of everolimus in combination with trastuzumab and vinorelbine on
           quality of life as measured by the FACT-B and FACT-Br questionnaires.

      Exploratory Objective

      -To evaluate biomarkers in archival tumor tissue samples and correlate with therapeutic
      response to everolimus in combination with vinorelbine and trastuzumab.

      Following Hepatitis B antiviral prophylaxis if required, or following screening and informed
      consent if antiviral therapy is not needed, treatment will be initiated with everolimus PO
      daily in combination with weekly intravenous (IV) vinorelbine and trastuzumab (Days 1, 8,
      and 15)

      A cycle is defined as 3 weeks (21 days).  Cycles of therapy will be repeated until
      documented disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or patient withdrawal from study for
      other reasons, including death.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>intracranial response rate- modified RECIST Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>response will be evaluated via gadolinium-enhanced brain MRI using modified RECIST criteria for all evaluable patients.  A responder will be a patient whose best overall response is a CR or PR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intracranial Response Rate- MacDonald Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>intracranial response rate will be evaluated via gadolinium-enhanced MRI using MacDonald criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Extracranial response</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Extracranial response will be measured using RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity will be assessed according to the NCI CTCAE v4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>HER-2 Positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus with Vinorelbine and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>daily everolimus plus weekly (Days 1, 8, and 15) vinorelbine and trastuzumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>everolimus 5 mg PO daily as two 2.5-mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus with Vinorelbine and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RAD001</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vinorelbine</intervention_name>
    <description>vinorelbine 25 mg/m2 will be administered via IV infusion over 6-10 minutes weekly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus with Vinorelbine and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Navelbine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trastuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>2 mg/kg IV administered over 30 minutes weekly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus with Vinorelbine and trastuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Herceptin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Histologically-confirmed HER2-positive (IHC 3+ or fluorescence in situ hybridization
             [FISH] amplified; by clinical assay on either primary or metastatic tumor)
             adenocarcinoma of the breast with at least one progressive and/or new metastatic
             brain lesion (&gt;/=5 mm on radiographic imaging) after receipt of intracranial
             radiation therapy (whole brain radiation therapy, stereotactic radiosurgery, gamma
             knife, or equivalent).

          -  ECOG performance status of 0-2.

          -  Life expectancy &gt;12 weeks.

          -  At least 21 years of age.

          -  No limit to prior therapies with exception of mTOR inhibitors or Navelbine with last
             anti-cancer treatment (including any investigational drug) ≥2 weeks from initiation
             of protocol-based therapy, provided all AEs (other than alopecia) have resolved to
             ≤grade 1 at baseline.

          -  Prior navelbine allowed provided navelbine therapy discontinued &gt;/= 12 months from
             Day 1 of treatment under this protocol.

          -  No active serious infection or other comorbid illness which would impair ability to
             participate in the trial.

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction assessment (echocardiogram or MUGA scan) performed
             within 4 weeks prior to study initiation, showing a LVEF value ≥ lower limit of
             normal (LLN).

          -  If patient is on dexamethasone, must be on stable or decreasing dose of dexamethasone
             for ≥7 days.  If patient is on different glucocorticoid e.g., prednisone, must be
             converted to dexamethasone prior to enrollment.  Refer to dose modification of
             everolimus for patients taking dexamethasone.

          -  Interval ≥4 weeks between open brain biopsy and initiation of protocol-based therapy.

          -  INR ≤2.0.  Anticoagulation is allowed if target INR ≤2.0 on a stable dose of warfarin
             or if patient on a stable dose of LMW heparin for &gt;1 weeks at time of enrollment.

          -  Fasting serum cholesterol ≤300 mg/dL OR ≤7.75 mmol/L AND fasting triglycerides ≤2.5 x
             ULN.  NOTE: In case one or both of these thresholds are exceeded, the patient can
             only be included after initiation of appropriate lipid lowering medication.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ function as evidenced by:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥1.5/µL

          -  Platelet count ≥100,000/µL

          -  Hg ≥9 g/dL

          -  Bilirubin ≤1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  AST or ALT ≤2.5 x ULN (≤5 x ULN if liver metastases are present)

          -  Serum creatinine ≤1.5 x ULN

          -  Archived, paraffin-embedded tissue block (primary or metastatic) available for
             genomic studies is required.

          -  Signed, IRB-approved written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Patients who have received prior treatment with an mTOR inhibitor (e.g., sirolimus,
             temsirolimus, everolimus) or vinca alkaloids.

          -  Patients with a known hypersensitivity to everolimus or other rapamycins (e.g.,
             sirolimus, temsirolimus); patients who have received prior treatment with navelbine
             within prior 12 months.

          -  patients with a known hypersensitivity to everolimus or other rapamycins (e.g.
             sirolimus, temsirolimus) or to its excipients.

          -  Patients requiring treatment with any other systemic glucocorticoid.  NOTE: This
             restriction regarding choice of glucocorticoid does not apply should patient need &lt;2
             week course of glucocorticoid for treatment of non-infectious pneumonitis during
             study (see section 4.5.2).

          -  Patients with a known hypersensitivity to vinorelbine or to its excipients.

          -  Prior allergic reaction to trastuzumab for the treatment of metastatic breast cancer.

          -  Concurrent or planned radiation, hormonal, chemotherapeutic, experimental or targeted
             biologic therapy.

          -  Peripheral neuropathy ≥grade 3.

          -  Evidence of frank hemorrhage or impending herniation on baseline brain imaging.NOTE:
             asymptomatic micro-hemorrhage is allowed.

          -  Evidence of diffuse leptomeningeal disease on brain MRI or by previously documented
             CSF cytology.  NOTE: discrete dural metastases are permitted.

          -  Active cardiac disease including any of the following:

               -  Angina pectoris that requires the use of anti-anginal medication;

               -  Ventricular arrhythmias except for benign premature ventricular contractions;

               -  Supraventricular and nodal arrhythmias requiring a pacemaker or not controlled
                  with medication;

               -  Conduction abnormality requiring a pacemaker;

               -  Valvular disease with documented compromise in cardiac function;

               -  Symptomatic pericarditis

          -  History of cardiac dysfunction including any one of the following:

               -  Myocardial infarction documented by elevated cardiac enzymes or persistent
                  regional wall abnormalities on assessment of LV function;

               -  History of documented congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association
                  functional classification III-IV);

               -  Documented cardiomyopathy

          -  Patients who have had a major surgery or significant traumatic injury within 4 weeks
             of start of study drug, patients who have not recovered from the side effects of any
             major surgery (defined as requiring general anesthesia), or patients that may require
             major surgery during the course of the study.

          -  Patients should not receive immunization with attenuated live vaccines within 1 week
             of study entry or during study period.  Close contact with those who have received
             attenuated live vaccines should be avoided during treatment with everolimus.
             Examples of live vaccines include intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral
             polio, BCG, yellow fever, varicella, and TY21a typhoid vaccines.

          -  Other malignancies within the past 3 years except for adequately treated carcinoma of
             the cervix or basal or squamous cell carcinomas of the skin.

          -  Patients who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or other
             conditions that could affect their participation in the study such as:

               -  severely impaired lung function, defined as spirometry and diffusion lung
                  capacity for carbon monoxide (DLCO) that is 50% of the normal predicted value
                  and/or 02 saturation that is ≤88% at rest on room air

               -  uncontrolled diabetes, defined as fasting serum glucose &gt;1.5 x ULN (Note:
                  Optimal glycemic control should be achieved before starting trial therapy)

               -  active (acute or chronic) or uncontrolled severe infections

               -  liver disease such as cirrhosis or severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class
                  C).

        Note: A detailed assessment of Hepatitis B/C medical history and risk factors must be done
        at screening for all patients.  HBV DNA and HCV RNA PCR testing are required at screening
        for all patients with a positive medical history based on risk factors and/or confirmation
        of prior HBV/HCV infection.

          -  A known history of HIV seropositivity.

          -  Impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of everolimus (e.g., ulcerative disease,
             uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or small bowel
             resection).

          -  Patients with an active, bleeding diathesis or on oral anti-vitamin K medication
             (except low-dose warfarin and aspirin or equivalent, as long as the INR ≤2.0).

          -  Unable or unwilling to discontinue use of prohibited fruit (or its juices) and
             prohibited medications listed in Appendices II and III for at least 14 days or 5
             half-lives of a drug (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of study drug and
             for the duration of the study.

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding, or adults of reproductive
             potential who are not using effective birth control methods. Adequate contraception
             must be used throughout the trial and for 8 weeks after the last dose of study drug,
             by both sexes.  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative urine or
             serum pregnancy test within 7 days prior to everolimus initiation.

          -  Male patients whose sexual partner(s) are WOCBP who are not willing to use adequate
             contraception, during the study and for 8 weeks after the end of treatment

          -  Contraindication to gadolinium-enhanced MRI imaging.

          -  Inability to comply with study and/or follow-up procedures.

          -  History of noncompliance to medical regimens.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carey K Anders, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Donna Rowe, RN</last_name>
    <phone>(919) 966-7359</phone>
    <email>donna_rowe@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lisle Nabell, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center- Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nikita Shah, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Of Chicago Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rita Nanda, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Phipps, RN</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carey K Anders, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carolinas Healthcare System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kinston Medical Specialists, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kinston</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Watson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Marion L. Shepard Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27889</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vandana Abramson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick Dillon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.med.unc.edu</url>
    <description>Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 11, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 25, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>everolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>trastuzumab</keyword>
  <keyword>vinorelbine</keyword>
  <keyword>RAD001</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Herceptin</keyword>
  <keyword>Navelbine</keyword>
  <keyword>Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Metastases</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vinorelbine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vinblastine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
