<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="111">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01592968</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011-0884</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01592968</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Phase III Trial to Compare Stereotactic Radiosurgery Versus Whole Brain Radiation Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Phase III Randomized Trial to Compare Stereotactic Radiosurgery Versus Whole Brain Radiation Therapy for &gt;/= 4 Newly Diagnosed Non-Melanoma Brain Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to compare stereotactic radiosurgery to whole
      brain radiation therapy in patients with 4-10 non-melanoma brain tumors.

      Stereotactic radiosurgery is the delivery of focused, high-dose radiation given in a single
      session to the tumors with a minimal dose given to uninvolved areas of the brain.

      Whole brain radiation is the delivery of lower dose radiation to the entire brain given
      daily over 2 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be randomly assigned
      (as in the flip of a coin) to 1 of 2 study groups.  You will have an equal chance of being
      assigned to either group:

        -  If you are in Group 1, you will receive whole brain radiation treatment.

        -  If you are in Group 2, you will receive stereotactic radiosurgery.

      Study Procedures:

      If you are in Group 1, you will receive whole brain radiation treatment each day,
      Monday-Friday starting on Day 1.  If you are an inpatient, you may receive radiation
      treatment on weekends as well.  You will continue to receive radiation treatment up to Day
      14.

      If you are in Group 2, you will receive stereotactic radiosurgery on Day 1.  As part of the
      stereotactic radiosurgery procedure, you will receive a very accurate kind of MRI scan on
      the morning of the procedure.  If this MRI scan identifies more tumors, you may still
      continue to participate in the study with up to 15 tumors.  If there are more than 15 tumors
      found on the treatment planning MRI scan on the day of the SRS treatment, then you are not
      eligible to participate in the study.  In this case, your study doctor will discuss with you
      other treatment options off of the study, which may include stereotactic radiosurgery and/or
      whole brain radiation therapy.

      No matter which group you are in, you will sign a separate consent form for whole brain
      radiation or stereotactic radiosurgery that will explain the procedures and risks in detail.

      Study Visits:

      At 1, 4, 6, 9, and 12 months (+/- 14 days) after your assigned treatment, you will return to
      the clinic:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  You will be asked about any drugs you may be taking.

        -  You will have an MRI scan to check the status of the disease.

        -  You will complete the 7 cognitive function tests.

        -  You will complete 3 questionnaires that ask about your quality of life and any symptoms
           you may be having.

      Length of Study Participation:

      Your active participation on the study will be over when you have completed the follow-up
      visits.

      Follow-Up Visits:

      If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will return to the clinic for follow-up visits.
       The following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  You will be asked about any drugs you may be taking.

        -  You will have an MRI  to check the status of the disease.

      This is an investigational study.   It is considered investigational to compare stereotactic
      radiosurgery to whole brain radiation therapy in patients with 4-10 non-melanoma brain
      tumors.

      Up to 100 patients will take part in this study.  All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Local Tumor Control</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Local control rates estimated at 4 months for each treatment arm with 95% confidence intervals based on the Kaplan-Meier estimates of time to local failure.  Logrank test stratified by stratification factors used at randomization to compare the 2 treatment arms with respect to time to local failure. Lesions assessed using contrast-enhanced MRI scans. Progressive disease (PD) is considered local failure, or stable disease with deterioration of the neurological examination with a grade III or worse toxicity on the CTC AE v.4.0 scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Decline</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Baseline HVLT-R score compared to HVLT-R score in patients surviving 4 months.  Preservation of function defined as improvement of HVLT-R score or decline by 4 points or less.  Failure defined as decline by 5 or more points.  Time to neurocognitive decline estimated for each treatment arm using product limit estimator of Kaplan and Meier.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic Radiosurgery (SRS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose based on largest diameter lesion as measured on volumetric MRI, modified from RTOG 90-05 as follows: 20-24 Gy for lesions 2 cm or less in size, 16-18 Gy for lesions &gt;2-2.5 cm in size, and 12-16 Gy for lesions &gt;2.5-3.5 cm in size.  All sizes based on diameter in greatest dimension.  SRS performed on day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Whole Brain Radiation Therapy (WBRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fractionated radiation delivered to whole brain daily to deliver a dose of 30 Gy in 10 fractions Monday-Friday (M-F) with weekends off for all patients except inpatients (who may receive treatment through the weekend), and thus will be performed on day 1 through days 10-14.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stereotactic Radiosurgery (SRS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose based on largest diameter lesion as measured on volumetric MRI, modified from RTOG 90-05 as follows: 20-24 Gy for lesions 2 cm or less in size, 16-18 Gy for lesions &gt;2-2.5 cm in size, and 12-16 Gy for lesions &gt;2.5-3.5 cm in size. All sizes based on diameter in greatest dimension. SRS performed on day 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic Radiosurgery (SRS)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>XRT</other_name>
    <other_name>Radiation therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Whole Brain Radiation Therapy (WBRT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Fractionated radiation delivered to whole brain daily to deliver a dose of 30 Gy in 10 fractions Monday-Friday (M-F) with weekends off for all patients except inpatients (who may receive treatment through the weekend), and thus will be performed on day 1 through days 10-14.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Whole Brain Radiation Therapy (WBRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>XRT</other_name>
    <other_name>Radiation therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>3 quality of life (QOL)questionnaires completed 1, 4, 6, 9, and 12 months  after assigned treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic Radiosurgery (SRS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Whole Brain Radiation Therapy (WBRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Function Tests</intervention_name>
    <description>7 cognitive function tests completed 1, 4, 6, 9, and 12 months after assigned treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stereotactic Radiosurgery (SRS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Whole Brain Radiation Therapy (WBRT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients must have histological proof of malignant cancer, which is metastatic.
             Histological proof may be obtained from the primary tumor or another metastatic site.
             However, cytology alone is not an acceptable method of diagnosis.

          2. All patients must have greater than 3 but less than or equal to 10 metastatic lesions
             seen on a contrast enhancing MRI scan obtained not less than one month prior to study
             enrollment. Patients who are found to have 11-15 metastatic lesions at the time of
             treatment planning (on volumetric MRI once the head frame is in place) may still
             participate in the trial.

          3. All patients must be &gt;/= 18 years of age.

          4. All patients must sign informed consent verifying that they are aware of the
             investigational nature of this study in keeping with the rules and policies of M.D.
             Anderson Cancer Center. The only acceptable consent form is the one attached at the
             end of this protocol, and it must have been approved and amended by the M.D. Anderson
             IRB.

          5. All patients must be eligible to have all lesions treated with SRS (i.e. maximum
             diameter of largest lesion &lt; 3.5cm) as determined by the study radiation oncologist .

          6. All patients must have adequate liver, renal, and hematologic function as defined by
             Aspartate Amino Transferase (AST)/Alanine Amino Transferase (ALT)/Alkaline
             Phosphatase &lt; 2.5 times normal, calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 30ml/min, and
             platelet count &gt; 50,000.

          7. All patients should have normal coagulation, with international normalized ratio
             (INR) &lt; 1.3 and able to withhold anti-coagulation medications a minimum of 24 hours
             prior to radiosurgery (or until INR normalizes), on the day of treatment and 24 hours
             after radiosurgery has concluded. Those patients getting WBRT may continue these
             medications.

          8. Patients can be undergoing concurrent systemic therapy, such as temozolomide, at the
             discretion of their treating oncologist.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients are excluded from this trial if they have melanoma, small cell carcinoma,
             lymphoma/leukemia, or germ cell histology (note, melanoma patients will be eligible
             for the sister trial to this trial which will be open simultaneously).

          2. Patients will be excluded if they have had prior surgical resection of metastatic
             cancer from the brain.

          3. Patients will be excluded if there are one or more lesions in the brainstem.

          4. Patients will be excluded if there is radiographic or CSF cytological evidence of
             leptomeningeal disease.

          5. Patients will be excluded if they have had prior radiation to the brain (either WBRT,
             prophylactic cranial irradiation (PCI), or SRS).

          6. Female patients of childbearing age will be excluded if they are pregnant as assessed
             by serum b-HCG or urine pregnancy test. A serum b-HCG test or urine pregnancy test
             will be performed no greater than 14 days prior to study registration.

          7. Patients will be excluded if they are unable to obtain an MRI scan.

          8. Patients will be excluded if they have &lt; 4 lesions, or &gt; 10 lesions at enrollment or
             &gt; 15 lesions at the time of treatment (note: patients who qualify for enrollment
             based on having 4-10 lesions, but who are discovered to have 11-15 lesions on the
             volumetric MRI used for treatment planning will be allowed to continue on study).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jing Li, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jing Li, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-2300</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Andreson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 9, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 3, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-melanoma brain metastases</keyword>
  <keyword>Stereotactic radiosurgery</keyword>
  <keyword>SRS</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole brain radiation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>WBRT</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
