<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="267">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00301418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>501007705</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00301418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Tarceva Study for Recurrent/Residual Glioblastoma Multiforme and Anaplastic Astrocytoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Trial of Oral Erlotinib (Tarceva, OSI-774) for Treatment of Relapsed/Refractory Glioblastoma Multiforme and Anaplastic Astrocytoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will offer a safe  treatment for patients with relapsing recurring glioblastoma
      (GBM) or anaplastic astrocytoma (AA).  The trial will test the hypothesis that Erlotinib
      (Tarceva, OSI-774) can be safely used up to a dose of 150 mg two times a day for 12 months
      to ultimately enhance survival of patients with relapsed/refractory GBM/AA.  Correlation of
      response to Tarceva with particular genetic alterations including epidermal growth factor
      receptor variant type III (EGFRvIII) amplification and phosphatase and tensin homolog
      (mutated in multiple advanced cancers 1) (PTEN) loss will be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The high-grade malignant brain tumors, glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) and anaplastic
      astrocytoma (AA), comprise the majority of all primary brain tumors in adults.  This group
      of tumors also exhibits the most aggressive behavior, resulting in median overall survival
      durations of only 9-12 months for GBM, and 3-4 years for AA, from initial diagnosis, despite
      multimodal treatment approaches.  Initial therapy consists of either surgical resection,
      external beam radiation or both.  The role of adjuvant or concomitant chemotherapy in the
      initial therapy of GBM and AA has not, as yet, been clearly defined.  Since most of these
      patients experience a recurrence after first-line therapy, improvements in both first-line
      and salvage therapy are critical to enhancing quality-of-life and prolonging survival.  In
      August 2003, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) granted orphan drug status for
      Erlotinib in patients with malignant glioma.   Erlotinib (OSI-774) has been shown to be
      active in a range of tumors including GBM, AA and non small cell lung cancer.  Because of
      the promising results in preliminary studies of Erlotinib and because of significant
      experience with the safety of the dosages proposed in this study, this study will offer a
      safe adjuvant treatment for patients with relapsing recurring glioblastoma or anaplastic
      astrocytoma.  Therefore, this phase I/II clinical research trial will test the hypothesis
      that Erlotinib can be safely used up to a dose of 150 mg bid for 12 cycles to ultimately
      enhance survival of patients with relapsed/refractory GBM/AA with particular genetic
      alterations including EGFRvIII amplification and PTEN loss.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of twice a day oral 150 mg Erlotinib dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>duration of the  trial</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite overall response rate (CORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the trial</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-month progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the trial</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the trial</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erlotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Tarceva®: Will be given at a starting dose of 150mg QD dose for the first cycle which is 28 days.  This will be followed by 14 days of 100mg PO on a bid schedule and 150mg PO on a bid schedule for the final 14 days of the second cycle.  Assuming no dose limiting toxicity, 150 mg PO tid will be continued for up to 10 more cycles.   This is an outpatient regimen, in which the drug is admininistered orally.  Tumor response will be assessed after every 2nd treatment cycle.  Patients may receive a maximum of 12 cycles of treatment under this research protocol.</description>
    <other_name>Tarceva</other_name>
    <other_name>OSI-774</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients of ≥ 18 years of age.

          -  Patients with a documented histologic diagnosis of relapsed or refractory
             glioblastoma multiforme (GBM), anaplastic astrocytoma (AA) or anaplastic mixed
             oligoastrocytoma (AOA).  All patients will have samples of their tissue evaluated for
             EGFRvIII overexpression and PTEN loss.

          -  Patients with a histologically confirmed low grade brain tumor who relapse with an
             enhancing tumor on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) can be evaluated for toxicity
             only.

          -  Patients must have at least one confirmed and evaluable tumor site.*

             *A confirmed tumor site is one which is biopsy-proven.  NOTE: Radiographic procedures
             (e.g., Gd-enhanced MRI or computed tomography [CT] scans) documenting existing
             lesions must have been performed within three weeks of treatment on this research
             study.

          -  Patients must have a Karnofsky performance status ≥ 60% (or the equivalent Eastern
             Cooperative Oncology Group [ECOG] level of 0-2) and an expected survival of ≥ three
             months.

          -  No chemotherapy for six weeks prior to treatment under this research protocol and
                                                                               no external beam
             radiation for eight weeks prior to treatment under this research protocol.

          -  Patients must have adequate hematologic reserve with WBC ≥ 3000/mm3, absolute
             neutrophils ≥ 1500/mm3 and platelets ≥ 100,000/mm3.  Patients who are on Coumadin
             must have a platelet count of ≥ 150,000/mm3

          -  Pre-enrollment chemistry parameters must show: bilirubin &lt; 1.5X the institutional
             upper limit of normal (IUNL); AST or ALT &lt; 2.5X IUNL and creatinine &lt; 1.5X IUNL.

          -  Pre-enrollment coagulation parameters (PT and PTT) must be ≤ 1.5X the IUNL.

          -  Concomitant Medications:

               -  Growth factor(s): Must not have received within 1 week of entry onto this study.

               -  Steroids: Systemic corticosteroid therapy is permissible in patients with
                  centrail nervous system (CNS) tumors for treatment of increased intracranial
                  pressure or symptomatic tumor edema. Patients with CNS tumors who are receiving
                  dexamethasone must be on a stable or decreasing dose for at least 1 week prior
                  to study entry.

               -  Study Specific: Patients on enzyme-inducing anticonvulsants will be changed to
                  non-enzyme inducing anticonvulsants or will not be allowed on this study.
                  Patients receiving proton pump inhibitor or H2 blockers will not be allowed on
                  study. Patients taking antacids will be allowed on study although they should
                  not take the antacid for two hours before or two hours after taking erlotinib.

          -  Patients must agree to use a medically effective method of contraception during and
             for a period of three months after the treatment period.  A pregnancy test will be
             performed on each premenopausal female of childbearing potential immediately prior to
             entry into the research study.

          -  Patients should not have received a CYP3A4 inhibitor within 1 week of study entry and
             should not have received a CYP3A4 inducer within 4 weeks of study entry.

          -  Patients should not have received proton-pump inhibitors within 5 days of study entry
             or H2 blockers within 2 days of study entry.

          -  Patients on steroids must receive prophylaxis for Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia
             (PCP) with Bactrim, unless they have a history of allergy to sulfa drugs.

          -  Patients must be able to understand and give written informed consent.  Informed
             consent must be obtained at the time of patient screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous treatment with Tarceva®.

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  Women of childbearing potential and fertile men will be informed as to the
             potential risk of procreation while participating in this research trial and will be
             advised that they must use effective contraception during and for a period of three
             months after the treatment period.

          -  Patients with significant intercurrent medical or psychiatric conditions that would
                  place them at increased risk or affect their ability to receive or comply with
             treatment or post-treatment clinical monitoring.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John A Boockvar, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John A Boockvar, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-1996</phone>
    <email>jab2029@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Susan Pannullo, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-2436</phone>
    <email>scp2002@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The New York Hospital/ Weill Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John A. Boockvar, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-1996</phone>
      <email>jab2029@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Susan Pannullo, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-2436</phone>
      <email>scp2002@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Theodore Schwartz, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philip Stieg, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susan Pannullo, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John A. Boockvar, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cornellphysicians.com/jboockvar/index.html</url>
    <description>Principal Investigator Web Site</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cornellphysicians.com/scpannullo/index.html</url>
    <description>Sub-Investigator Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mellinghoff IK, Wang MY, Vivanco I, Haas-Kogan DA, Zhu S, Dia EQ, Lu KV, Yoshimoto K, Huang JH, Chute DJ, Riggs BL, Horvath S, Liau LM, Cavenee WK, Rao PN, Beroukhim R, Peck TC, Lee JC, Sellers WR, Stokoe D, Prados M, Cloughesy TF, Sawyers CL, Mischel PS. Molecular determinants of the response of glioblastomas to EGFR kinase inhibitors. N Engl J Med. 2005 Nov 10;353(19):2012-24. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2006 Feb 23;354(8):884.</citation>
    <PMID>16282176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 18, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 9, 2006</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John A. Boockvar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma Multiforme</keyword>
  <keyword>Anaplastic Astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>High Grade Glial Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Erlotinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
