<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="288">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001686</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980037</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-C-0037</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001686</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00445536</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation, Treatment, and Natural History of Children With Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Children With Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol is designed to evaluate children with cancer who appear to be probable
      candidates for future protocol entry or have disease manifestations that are of unique
      scientific importance or educational value.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Children are referred to the Pediatric Oncology Branch (POB) for possible enrollment in
      clinical protocols for the treatment of cancer. While some children are not eligible for a
      specific protocol, they may present with disease manifestations that offer the potential for
      important new insights into the pathogenesis or clinical behavior of their underlying
      disease. In addition, children who have completed participation in a clinical protocol but
      do not currently have therapeutic protocol alternatives may continue to provide POB with
      important information. Diseases of interest to the POB include, but are not limited to
      lymphoma, brain tumors, Ewings sarcoma, leukemia, neuroectodermal tumors, osteosarcoma, and
      rhabdomyosarcoma. Hence, serial clinical evaluation of such patients, including the
      performance of clinical, laboratory, and diagnostic studies to help elucidate longitudinally
      the underlying disease mechanisms, and when clinically indicated standard care therapies,
      will assist POB meet its overall mission.

      Objectives:

      To be able to follow and evaluate children with cancer or pre-cancer syndromes referred to
      the Pediatric Oncology Branch who present with disease manifestations that lend themselves
      to clinical evaluation and are of unique scientific import.

      Eligibility:

      Patients who are evaluated by the Pediatric Oncology Branch and are: Children with cancer
      (or a pre-cancer syndrome), between the age(s) of 3 months - 40 years who present with
      disease manifestations of special interest to Pediatric Oncology Branch investigators,
      because they are likely to shed led light on disease pathogenesis or the clinical behavior
      of the disorder. Patients between the ages of 30 and 40 years may be evaluated on this
      protocol if their cancer (or pre-cancer syndrome) is of specific interest to the Pediatric
      Oncology Branch.

      Design:

      The medical procedures or tests will be selected for each patient on the basis of his/her
      individual diagnosis (or presumed diagnosis). When clinically indicated, standard therapy
      will be administered and patients will be followed according to standard medical practice.
      Specimens may be collected for clinical care purposes only to evaluate the patient's status.

      No investigational tests, drugs or therapies will be administered in this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 1997</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>N/A</study_design>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Ewing's Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients who are evaluated by the Pediatric Oncology Branch and are:

        Children with cancer (or a precancer syndrome), between the age(s) of 3 months to 40
        years.

        Patients between the ages of 30 and 40 years may be evaluated on this protocol if their
        cancer (or precancer syndrome) is of specific interest to the Pediatric Oncology Branch.

        Patients with cancer (or a precancer syndrome), who present with disease manifestations of
        special interest to Pediatric Oncology Branch investigators, including but not limited to,
        lymphoma, brain tumors, Ewings sarcoma, leukemia, neuroectodermal tumors, osteosarcoma,
        rhabdomysarcoma.

        If indicated, availability of a parent or legal guardian to give informed consent.

        Patients, and, when indicated, parent or legal guardian who are deemed sufficiently
        reliable to return for recommended follow-up visits.

        Patients greater than or equal to 18 years of age must be able to give informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients younger than 3 months of age.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Crystal L Mackall, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lauren M Long, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-0486</phone>
    <email>longl@exchange.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Crystal L Mackall, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-5940</phone>
    <email>mackallc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>(888) NCI-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1998-C-0037.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 3, 1999</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Sarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Ewing's Sarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroectodermal Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Rhabdomyosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoplasm</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Ewing's</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors, Primitive, Peripheral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
