<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="261">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00390299</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC0671</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015083</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC0671</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>06-004440</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00390299</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Viral Therapy in Treating Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Trial of a Measles Virus Derivative Producing CEA (MV-CEA) in Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: The measles virus, that has been changed in a certain way, may kill tumor cells
      without damaging normal cells.

      PURPOSE: This phase I trial is studying the side effects and best dose of viral therapy in
      treating patients with recurrent glioblastoma multiforme.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  Determine the safety and toxicity of intratumoral and/or resection cavity
           administration of a recombinant, attenuated Edmonston B vaccine strain derivative of
           measles virus genetically engineered to produce human carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) in
           patients with recurrent glioblastoma multiforme.

        -  Determine the maximum tolerated dose of this oncolytic virus in these patients.

        -  Determine viral gene expression at each dose level as manifested by CEA titers in
           patients treated with this oncolytic virus.

        -  Assess viremia, viral replication, and measles virus shedding/persistence after
           intratumoral administration of this oncolytic virus.

        -  Assess humoral and cellular immune response to the injected virus in these patients.

      Secondary

        -  Determine, preliminarily, the antitumor efficacy of this vaccine in these patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study. Patients are assigned to 1 of 2 sequential
      treatment groups.

        -  Group 1 (resection cavity administration): Patients undergo en block resection of their
           tumor (after confirming diagnosis) on day 1, followed by recombinant measles virus
           encoding human carcinoembryonic antigen (MV-CEA) administered into the resection cavity
           over 10 minutes.

        -  Group 2 (intratumoral and resection cavity administration): Patients undergo placement
           of a catheter within the tumor, followed by MV-CEA administration into the tumor
           through the catheter over 10 minutes on day 1. Patients undergo en block resection of
           their tumor with computer-assisted stereotactic techniques on day 5, followed by MV-CEA
           administered around the tumor bed.

      In both groups, cohorts of 1-6 patients receive escalating doses of MV-CEA until the maximum
      tolerated dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2
      of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. Once the MTD in group 1 has been
      determined, patients are assigned to group 2. The MTD in group 1 is used to determine the
      starting dose in group 2. At least 10 patients are treated at the MTD determined in group 2.

      Biopsy specimen, resected tumor, normal tissue, and peripheral blood are collected during
      study for immunologic and biomarker correlative studies, including analysis of CD46 receptor
      levels (by immunohistochemistry [IHC]), measles virus N protein (by IHC), measles and viral
      gene expression and replication (by in situ hybridization), CEA monitoring (by immunoassay),
      measles virus N mRNA (by reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction), and measles virus
      immunity. Assessments of immune competence and peripheral response to viral administration
      are also performed.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed periodically for up to 15 years.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 40 patients will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2006</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events profile, in terms of number and severity of all adverse events, as assessed by NCI CTCAE v3.0</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall toxicity incidence and toxicity profile (by dose level, patient, and tumor site) as assessed by NCI CTCAE v3.0</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until any treatment related toxicity</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until treatment-related toxicity ≥ grade 3</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until hematologic nadirs (WBC, absolute neutrophil count, platelet count)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of vaccine   as assessed by  NCI CTCAE v3.0</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlate viremia, human CEA titers, viral propagation in tumor, viral shedding, CD46 status, delayed-type hypersensitivity  results, CD4 and CD8 counts, lymphoproliferative assay,  and ELISPOT assay with response and toxicity</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Viral gene expression at each dose level as assessed by CEA titer</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Viremia following intratumoral administration of vaccine as assessed by quantitative reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) of peripheral blood mononuclear cells</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measles virus shedding/persistence following intratumoral administration of vaccine as assessed by RT-PCR</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Viral replication following intratumoral administration of vaccine as assessed by in situ hybridization and Vero cell overlay</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CR,   PR, regress, stable dis, &amp; prog dis by neur exam, MRI, and/or CT scan for bidimens. meas. dis &amp;  eval dis. at baseline, 28 days after resection, and then every 2 mo. until progr.</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral and cell. imm. resp. by antimeasles virus-specific antibody level (IgG) at baseline,  28 days after resection, and every 2 mo until prog</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral and cell. imm. resp. by lymphoproliferative assay and interferon-gamma ELISPOT assay performed at baseline and at 28 days after tumor resection</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival  at 3 and 6 months</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to disease progression</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to treatment failure (due to progression, unacceptable toxicity, or refusal to continue participation by the patient)</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carcinoembryonic antigen-expressing measles virus</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorescence in situ hybridization</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>immunohistochemistry staining method</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>immunologic technique</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>adjuvant therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional surgery</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>needle biopsy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>neoadjuvant therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically confirmed grade 4 astrocytoma (glioblastoma multiforme) at primary
             diagnosis and/or recurrence

          -  Recurrent disease

          -  Candidate for gross total or subtotal resection

               -  No expected communication between ventricles and resection cavity as a result of
                  surgery

          -  Antimeasles virus immunity as demonstrated by IgG antimeasles antibody levels of ≥ 20
             EU/mL as determined by enzyme immunoassay

          -  Human carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) &lt; 3 ng/mL

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm^3

          -  Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  AST ≤ 2 times ULN

          -  Creatinine ≤ 2.0 times ULN

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

          -  PT and aPTT ≤ 1.3 times ULN

          -  Willing to provide biological specimens as required by the study

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception

          -  No active infection within the past 5 days

          -  No history of tuberculosis or purified protein derivative positivity

          -  No New York Heart Association class III or IV cardiac disease

          -  Adequate seizure control

          -  HIV negative

          -  No history of other immunodeficiency

          -  No history of chronic hepatitis B or C

          -  No exposure (household contacts) to children ≤ 15 months of age or to people with
             known immunodeficiency

          -  No allergy to measles vaccine or history of severe reaction to prior measles
             vaccination

          -  No requirement for blood product support

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  More than 4 weeks since prior chemotherapy (6 weeks for nitrosourea-based
             chemotherapy) and recovered

          -  More than 4 weeks since prior immunotherapy

          -  More than 4 weeks since prior biologic therapy

          -  More than 2 weeks since prior noncytotoxic antitumor drugs (i.e., small molecule cell
             cycle inhibitors)

          -  More than 6 weeks since prior radiotherapy

          -  No prior viral or gene therapy

          -  No history of organ transplantation

          -  No concurrent chemotherapy, other immunotherapy, radiotherapy, or any other ancillary
             therapy considered investigational (utilized for a non-FDA-approved indication and in
             the context of a research investigation)

          -  No concurrent enrollment on any other study involving a pharmacologic agent (e.g.,
             drugs, biologics), immunotherapy approaches, or gene therapy whether for symptom
             control or therapeutic intent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evanthia Galanis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Office - All Mayo Clinic Locations</last_name>
      <phone>507-538-7623</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/MAYO-MC0671</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 28, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 18, 2006</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Evanthia Galanis, M.D.</name_title>
    <organization>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>recurrent adult brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
