<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="254">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01390571</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000702605</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CRUK-CR0901-11</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EUDRACT-2010-018615-15</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01390571</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Olaparib and Temozolomide in Treating Patients With Relapsed Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Cancer Research UK Phase I Trial of Olaparib (AZD2281), an Oral PARP Inhibitor, in Combination With Extended Low-Dose Oral Temozolomide in Patients With Relapsed Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cancer Research UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cancer Research UK</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Research Ethics Committee</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Olaparib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as temozolomide, work in different
      ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from
      dividing. Olaparib may help temozolomide kill more tumor cells by making tumor cells more
      sensitive to the drug.

      PURPOSE: This phase I trial is studying the side effects and best dose of olaparib and
      temozolomide in treating patients with relapsed glioblastoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To determine whether olaparib crosses the blood-brain barrier (BBB) and achieves tumor
           penetration in patients with relapsed glioblastoma. (Stage 1)

        -  To determine the safety and tolerability of the combination of olaparib and
           temozolomide in patients with relapsed glioblastoma. (Stage 2)

      Secondary

        -  To assess BBB disruption and BBB permeability in patients with relapsed glioblastoma.
           (Stage 1 and stage 2 maximum-tolerated dose [MTD] expansion cohort)

        -  To assess the possible anti-tumor activity of the combination of olaparib and
           temozolomide in patients with relapsed glioblastoma. (Stage 2)

      Tertiary

        -  To assess biological markers as possible predictors of olaparib efficacy in patients
           with glioblastoma.

        -  To optimize techniques for measuring DNA damage responses to PARP inhibition in tumor
           tissue.

        -  To determine plasma concentration of olaparib at the time of surgery in patients with
           glioblastoma.

        -  To evaluate the PARP inhibition at the time of surgery in peripheral blood mononuclear
           cells (PBMCs).

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter, dose-escalation study.

        -  Stage 1: Patients receive fixed-dose oral olaparib twice daily for 3 days prior to
           resection and then receive a dose of oral olaparib on the morning of the resection.
           After the surgical resection, patient receive standard of care treatment. Patients
           undergo dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (DCE-MRI) and
           diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI) scans to assess the disruption and permeability of the
           blood-brain barrier (BBB).

      If it is proven that olaparib can cross the BBB and achieve tumor penetration as measured by
      liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS) in at least one out of six patients, then
      new patients are recruited to stage 2 of the study.

        -  Stage 2: Patients receive escalating doses of oral olaparib once or twice daily for 3
           days prior to resection and then receive a dose of oral olaparib on the morning of the
           resection. After recovery from surgery, patients receive oral olaparib once or twice
           daily and oral temozolomide once daily on days 1-42. Treatment repeats every 8 weeks
           for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
           Patients may receive 3 additional courses of treatment in the absence of disease
           progression.

      Once the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is established, 10 more patients are treated at the
      MTD as stage 2 MTD expansion cohort. These patients also undergo DCE-MRI and DWI scans.

      All patients undergo blood collection periodically for pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic
      studies.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 28 days and then monthly
      until resolution of study drug-related adverse events.

      Peer Reviewed and Funded or Endorsed by Cancer Research UK.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of olaparib in tumor tissue using liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS) seen in at least 1  out of the 6  patients treated in stage 1 of the study</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum-tolerated dose of  olaparib in combination with  temozolomide (stage 2)</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity profile and  dose-limiting toxicity as  assessed by NCI CTCAE Version 4.02 (stage 2)</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of blood-brain barrier (BBB) disruption and permeability biomarkers by dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (DCE-MRI) and diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI) (stage 1 and stage 2 MTD expansion cohort)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival at 6  months post-surgery as assessed by  the Response Assessment in Neuro-Oncology Working Group (RANO) criteria from conventional MRI and clinical assessment (stage 2)</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gene copy number analysis of DNA repair genes</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantification of DNA repair gene expression</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of methylation of the MGMT promoter gene by bisulfite modification of DNA and pyrosequencing</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of microsatellite instability by Multiplex PCR</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of mismatch repair (MMR) gene expression by quantitative real time polymerase chain reaction (QRT-PCR) analysis</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN) protein and gene expression</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantification of global DNA strand breaks in tumour tissue by Immunostaining for γH2AX</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of Rad51 foci and nuclear staining intensity as markers of homologous recombination (HR) repair activity</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma levels of olaparib measured by LC-MS</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PARP inhibition measured by validated assays</measure>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>olaparib</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>temozolomide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gene expression analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>protein expression analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic conventional surgery</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically confirmed grade IV glioblastoma

          -  Radiological diagnosis of recurrent or progressive disease according to Response
             Assessment in Neuro-Oncology Working Group (RANO) criteria, which is suitable for
             palliative resection

          -  Must have an adequate amount of tumor tissue available

          -  Previously received first-line treatment with radical radiotherapy, or chemoradiation
             followed by adjuvant chemotherapy

               -  No prior chemotherapy for recurrent disease

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  WHO performance status 0-2

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Platelet count ≥ 100 x 10^9/L

          -  Serum bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  ALT or AST ≤ 2.5 times ULN

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min OR isotope clearance measurement ≥ 50
             mL/min (uncorrected)

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use one (male) or two (female) highly effective forms of
             contraception 4 weeks prior to, during, and for 6 months after completion of study
             therapy

          -  Able to swallow and retain oral medications

          -  Not at high medical risk due to non-malignant systemic disease, including active
             uncontrolled infection

          -  No known hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or HIV seropositivity

          -  No concurrent congestive heart failure, prior history of NYHA class III-IV cardiac
             disease, prior history of cardiac ischemia, or prior history of cardiac arrhythmia
             within the past 12 months

          -  No grand mal seizures occurring ≥ 3 times per week over the past month

          -  No gastrointestinal disorders likely to interfere with absorption of the study
             medication

          -  No known hypersensitivity to any of the components of olaparib

          -  No known hypersensitivity to temozolomide (TMZ) or any of its components, or to
             dacarbazine (DTIC) (for patients enrolled in stage 2 study only)

          -  No known lactose intolerance (for patients enrolled in the stage 2 study only)

          -  No metal fragments in the eyes (shrapnel or bullet injuries are excluded on the basis
             of their unsuitability to undergo MRI scans)

          -  No other condition which, in the Investigator's opinion, would not make the patient a
             good candidate for the clinical trial

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  No ongoing toxic manifestations from previous treatments except for alopecia or grade
             1 toxicities which, in the opinion of the Investigator and the Drug Development
             Office (DDO), should not exclude the patient

          -  At least 12 weeks since prior radiotherapy, endocrine therapy, or immunotherapy

          -  At least 6 weeks since prior major surgery

          -  At least 4 weeks since prior chemotherapy

          -  At least 4 weeks since prior immunizations with live vaccines (or expected to receive
             vaccines during the trial and up to at least 6 months after receiving last study
             treatment), including BCG and yellow fever vaccines

          -  No prior PARP inhibitors, including olaparib

          -  No prior major thoracic or abdominal surgery from which the patient has not yet
             recovered

          -  No prior heart surgery

          -  No pacemakers

          -  No change to systemic steroids dose within 5 days prior to enrollment (i.e., must be
             on a stable dose at time of enrollment and remain on a stable dose throughout the
             treatment period)

          -  No herbal supplements and/or ingestion of foods known to modulate CYP3A4 enzyme
             activity from time entered on screening period until 28 days after the last dose of
             study medication

          -  No concurrent drugs known to be potent inducers of CYP3A4, including phenytoin,
             carbamazepine, phenobarbital, rifampicin, rifapentine, rifabutin, nevirapine,
             modafinil, or St. John wort (wash-out period for phenobarbital is 5 weeks, 3 weeks
             for all others)

          -  No concurrent drugs known to be potent inhibitors of CYP3A4, including ketoconazole,
             itraconazole, ritonavir, indinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin, clarithromycin, or
             nelfinavir (wash-out period is 1 week)

          -  No concurrent or planned participation in another interventional clinical study

               -  Participation in an observational study is acceptable

          -  No concurrent warfarin (patients requiring anticoagulation should be given
             subcutaneous low molecular weight heparin)

          -  No other concurrent anticancer therapy (including radiotherapy) or investigational
             drugs

               -  Patients in stage 1 of the study only may receive additional anticancer
                  therapies as soon as the resection has been performed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony Chalmers, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beatson West of Scotland Cancer Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bristol Haematology and Oncology Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bristol</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>BS2 8ED</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Contact Person</last_name>
      <phone>01173423008</phone>
      <email>Kristen.Hopkins@UHBristol.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristen Hopkins, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Addenbrooke's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>CB2 0QQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Contact Person</last_name>
      <phone>01223586705</phone>
      <email>sarah.jefferies@addenbrookes.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Jefferies, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christie Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Contact Person</last_name>
      <phone>0161 446 3495</phone>
      <email>catherine.mcbain@christie.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine McBain, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Marsden Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sutton</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Contact Person</last_name>
      <phone>020 8661 3988</phone>
      <email>Rhoda.molife@icr.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rhoda Molife, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beatson West of Scotland Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <state>Scotland</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Contact Person</last_name>
      <phone>0141 301 7097</phone>
      <email>anthony.chalmers@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anthony Chalmers, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <zip>B15 2TH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Contact Person</last_name>
      <phone>0121 697 8231</phone>
      <email>Garth.Cruickshank@uhb.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Garth Cruikshank, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <zip>EH4 2XU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Contact Person</last_name>
      <phone>0131 537 1052</phone>
      <email>serridge@staffmail.ed.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sara Erridge, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/CRUK-CR0901-11</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 24, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 7, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult brain tumor</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
