<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="278">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01491893</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00031169</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NS20023</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01491893</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Poliovirus Vaccine for Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PVS-RIPO</acronym>
  <official_title>Dose-finding and Safety Study of PVSRIPO Against Recurrent Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Matthias Gromeier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose of the Study:

      To determine the maximally tolerated dose (MTD) and dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) of PVSRIPO
      when delivered intracerebrally by convection-enhanced delivery. To estimate progression-free
      and overall survival in resectable, recurrent supratentorial glioblastoma multiforme (GBM)
      patients. To evaluate immunologic, virologic and histopathologic parameters of the effect of
      virus infection on GBM tumors.

      Agent: PVSRIPO is the live attenuated, oral (SABIN) serotype 1 poliovirus (PV) vaccine
      containing a heterologous internal ribosomal entry site (IRES) from human rhinovirus type 2
      (HRV2). PVSRIPO recognizes Necl-5, an oncofetal cell adhesion molecule and tumor antigen
      widely expressed ectopically in malignancy, e.g. glioblastoma multiforme (GBM), as host cell
      receptor. PVSRIPO has been manufactured at NCI-Frederick, NCI, NIH.

      Catheter Implantation: PVS-RIPO will be delivered directly into the tumor. A stereotactic
      biopsy will be performed prior to virus administration for frozen section confirmation of
      viable tumor and further analysis. The biopsy needle will be placed with stereotactic
      guidance by an MRI-compatible, stereotactic head frame. Immediately following the
      stereotactically-guided tumor biopsy, a catheter will be implanted in the OR at a site
      different from that used for the biopsy. A CT or MRI scan may be used to confirm catheter
      placement post-operatively.

      Agent infusion: The entire volume of the agent to be delivered will be pre-loaded into a
      syringe by the investigational pharmacist and connected to the catheter under sterile
      conditions in the OR at the time of the biopsy procedure. Drug infusion will occur in the
      NICU so that all other emergency facilities will be available. Patients will be infused
      through a Medfusion 3500 infusion pump pre-programmed to a delivery rate of 0.5 l/hr. The
      total amount of the inoculum delivered to the patient will be 3 ml. The virus injection
      procedure will be completed within 6.5 hrs. The catheter will be removed immediately
      following the delivery of PVSRIPO.

      Biopsy sampling and analyses: Biopsy material will be obtained from tumor tissue prior to
      virus administration. This tissue material will be subjected to routine histology to confirm
      tumor recurrence by the study neuropathologist, Dr. R. McLendon or his designate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post administration of PVS-RIPO</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The highest dose level for which the estimated probability that a patient  experiences a dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) is less than 20%.  Any grade 3 or any Grade 4 toxicity that is not reversible within 2 weeks, or any life-threatening event, or treatment-related death will be considered a DLT.  Any grade 2 or higher serious autoimmune toxicities particularly those affecting vital organs (e.g. cardiac, renal, CNS) will be considered a DLT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed at a min of 2,4,8,16,24, 32,40 and 48 week intervals after infusion.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Progression Free Survival is defined as the time between initiation of protocol treatment and the first occurrence of disease or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Infusion until 5 years post-infusion</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Time between infusion and 5 years from infusion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic Response</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Best radiographic response observed within 6 months of infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Supratentorial Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <condition>GBM</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PVS - RIPO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PVSRIPO intratumoral dosing schedule and number of patients that will be treated.
N=18
1.0 x 10^8 TCID50
3.3 x 10^8 TCID50
1.0 x 10^9 TCID50
3.3 x 10^9 TCID50
1.0 x 10^10 TCID50</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Live attenuated, oral (Sabin) serotype 1 poliovirus vaccine (PVSRIPO)</intervention_name>
    <description>PVSRIPO intratumoral dosing schedule and number of patients that will be treated.
N=18
1.0 x 10^8 TCID50
3.3 x 10^8 TCID50
1.0 x 10^9 TCID50
3.3 x 10^9 TCID50
1.0 x 10^10 TCID50</description>
    <arm_group_label>PVS - RIPO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Disease Status. Patients must have a resectable, recurrent supratentorial GBM based
             on imaging studies with measurable disease (≥ 1 cm or ≤ 5 cm of contrast-enhancing
             tumor). Prior histopathology consistent with a World Health Organization (WHO) Grade
             IV GBM confirmed by the study pathologist, Roger McLendon, or his designate.

          2. Age. Due to the potential implications of the treatment on the developing CNS, all
             patients must be ≥ 18 years of age at the time of entry into the study.

          3. Prior Therapy. Patients may be included in the study independent of the regimen of
             previous surgical, radiation, or chemotherapy treatments administered.  However, the
             exclusions listed in #5 of the Exclusions below must be followed.

          4. Performance Status. The patient must have a Karnofsky Performance Score (KPS) of ≥
             70% at the time of entry.

          5. Laboratory Studies

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/ml

               -  Prothrombin and Partial Thromboplastin Times ≤ 1.2 x normal

               -  Positive serum anti-poliovirus titer

               -  Creatinine ≤ 1.2 x normal

               -  Total bilirubin, SGOT, SGPT, alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 x normal

               -  Neutrophil count ≥ 1000

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9

          6. Poliovirus Immunization Booster.  The subject must have received a boost immunization
             with monovalent inactivated (Salk) poliovirus vaccine type 1 at least 2 weeks prior
             to administration of the study agent.

          7. Disease Confirmation. At the time of biopsy, prior to administration of virus, the
             presence of recurrent tumor must be confirmed by histopathological analysis of frozen
             sections.

          8. Informed Consent. A signed informed consent form approved by the Duke University
             Institutional Review Board (IRB) will be required for patient enrollment into the
             study. Patients must be able to read and understand the informed consent document and
             must sign the informed consent indicating that they are aware of the investigational
             nature of this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy. Because of the unknown risk of virus administration potentially affecting
             a developing fetus or growing infant, females who are pregnant or breast-feeding
             during the study period will be excluded. Adults of reproductive potential not
             employing an effective method of birth control will be excluded. Barrier
             contraceptives must be used throughout the trial in both sexes.

          2. Disease Status. Because patients will receive drug intracerebrally, patients with an
             impending, life-threatening cerebral herniation syndrome, based on the assessment of
             the study neurosurgeons, Allan Friedman or John Sampson, or their designate, will be
             excluded.

          3. Medical Conditions. Because the potential toxicities from the agent being studied in
             this protocol may be similar to some known diseases or may be more dangerous in the
             context of certain known diseases, the following patients will be excluded to avoid
             confounding the study results:

               -  Patients with an active infection requiring treatment or having an unexplained
                  febrile illness (Tmax &gt; 99.5 F).

               -  Patients with known immunosuppressive disease or known human immunodeficiency
                  virus infection.

               -  Unstable or severe intercurrent medical conditions such as severe heart (New
                  York Heart Association Class 3 or 4) or lung (FEV1 &lt; 50%) disease, uncontrolled
                  diabetes mellitus.

               -  Albumin allergy. Albumin is added to the agent as a stabilizer. Patients with a
                  known allergy will be excluded.

               -  Gadolinium allergy. Gadolinium is used as contrast for the MRI.

          4. Previous Poliomyelitis. A history of neurological complications due to poliovirus
             infection would imply previous virus replication in the CNS. Based on animal studies,
             previous exposure to poliovirus administered intracerebrally can reduce subsequent
             virus replication in the CNS.

          5. Prior Therapy. Patients who have not recovered from the toxic effects of prior
             chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy will be excluded. Guidelines for this recovery
             period are dependent upon the specific therapeutic agent being used.

               -  Patients may not have received chemotherapy ≤ 4 weeks [except for nitrosourea (6
                  weeks) or metronomic dosed chemotherapy such as daily etoposide or
                  cyclophosphamide (1 week)] prior to starting the study drug or patients have
                  recovered from side effects of such therapy.

               -  Patients may not have received immunotherapy ≤ 4 weeks prior to starting the
                  study drug or patients have recovered from side effects of such therapy.

               -  Patients may not have received investigational drugs ≤ 4 weeks prior to starting
                  the study drug or must have recovered from side effects of such therapy.

             Patients must have completed all standard of care treatments including resection and
             concurrent chemo-radiation prior to participating in this trial.

          6. Location and Extent of Tumor. Because of the potential toxicities from the agent,
             patients with neoplastic lesions in the brainstem, cerebellum or spinal cord,
             radiological evidence of multifocal disease, or leptomeningeal disease. Patients with
             evidence of diffuse subependymal disease or tumor in the brainstem, cerebellum,
             spinal cord, or CSF will be excluded.

               -  Since the study agent is a local treatment, patients with radiological evidence
                  of multifocal disease, tumors extending into or crossing the corpus callosum or
                  leptomeningeal disease, will be excluded.

               -  Patients with contrast-enhancing tumors of &lt; 1 cm or &gt; 5 cm diameter in any
                  plane will be excluded.

               -  Patients with tumor ≤ 1 cm in proximity to the ventricle.

          7. Subjects must not have diagnosis of agammaglobulinemia. Patients with the following
             will be excluded:

               -  IgG levels &lt; 400 mg/dL [4 g/L]

               -  Undetectable anti-tetanus toxoid IgG

               -  Known history of agammaglobulinemia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Annick Desjardins, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stevie Threatt</last_name>
    <phone>919-684-3657</phone>
    <email>stevie.threatt@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Susan Boulton, RN</last_name>
    <phone>919-668-0896</phone>
    <email>susan.boulton@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Carter</last_name>
      <phone>919-668-2329</phone>
      <email>karen.carter@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 29, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 1, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matthias Gromeier</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GBM</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Poliovirus Vaccine</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
