<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="39">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00978562</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OHSU-5405</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>3 RO1 CA137488 15S1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SOL-09064-LX</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>5405</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00978562</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging Vascular Properties of Pediatric Brain Tumors Using Ferumoxytol and Gadolinium in a Single Imaging Session</brief_title>
  <official_title>Imaging Vascular Properties of Pediatric Brain Tumors Using DSC-MRI With Ferumoxytol (Code 7228) and DCE-MRI With Gadolinium in a Single Imaging Session: An NCI Sponsored Exploratory Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Current imaging techniques often do not demonstrate the true amount and location of brain
      tumors, which are both critical factors for treatment decision-making.  This purpose of this
      study is to assess the safety and effectiveness of a new iron containing agent called
      &quot;ferumoxytol&quot; in improving our ability to image pediatric brain tumors.  Ferumoxytol, as
      well as the usual contrast agent, gadolinium, together will be used to image the blood
      vessels in pediatric brain tumors. After contrast agent injection into the veins, special
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans will be performed to see changes in blood vessels in
      the brain and tumor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will be scanned at five different time-points (5 MRI series).  Each patient will
      have a baseline MRI study (gadolinium only, with no ferumoxytol).  MRI scans with both
      ferumoxytol and gadolinium contrast will be performed beginning at least 3 weeks after the
      baseline scan.  The timing of all MRIs will not occur more frequently than every 3 weeks,
      and all five ferumoxytol/gadolinium scans will take place within 2 years from study entry.
      There will be a final outpatient clinic visit approximately 1 month after the final
      ferumoxytol/gadolinium MRI.

      Measurements such as size of tumor, blood flow to tumor (perfusion), and leakiness of blood
      vessels within the tumor (permeability) will be described at each time-point and the
      information will be evaluated throughout the study. The tumor size will be evaluated by 2
      radiologists.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Diagnostic</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe vascular properties of pediatric brain tumors using ferumoxytol for DSC-MRI and GBCA for DCE-MRI in a single MRI session. Describe evolving imaging characteristics of tumor vasculature using DSC-MRI with ferumoxytol and DCE-MRI with GBCA.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare and evaluate MRA with ferumoxytol between different time points.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe number and size of tumors imaged</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess histology and EM on tissue samples</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demonstrate differences in patients with prior therapy vs. no prior therapy (radiation and/or chemotherapy).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ferumoxytol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MR imaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ferumoxytol</intervention_name>
    <description>Level 1 = 2mg Fe/kg Level 2 = 4mg Fe/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>ferumoxytol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Feraheme</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  5-18 years of age

          -  radiological (presumptive) or established (proven) histological diagnosis of a brain
             tumor or lesion

          -  previously untreated patients must have a measureable lesion on an imaging study

          -  Baseline MRI studies for patients receiving ferumoxytol must be performed within 6
             weeks of study entry

          -  Patients undergoing active treatment, or who have completed treatment, will have
             radiographic abnormalities that may or may not be recurrent tumor

          -  patients requiring surgical intervention for diagnostic and/or therapeutic purposes
             as necessary for their disease are eligible

          -  Patients may have had prior therapy for the primary brain tumor, including surgery,
             radiotherapy or chemotherapy

          -  agree to be followed for up to 6 weeks after the final infusion of ferumoxytol

          -  patients, or their legal guardians, must sign a written informed consent and HIPAA
             authorization in accordance with institutional guidelines

          -  Sexually active women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
             contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control;abstinence) prior to study
             treatment and for the duration of study treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with clinically significant signs of uncal herniation, such as acute
             pupillary enlargement, rapidly developing motor changes (over hours), or rapidly
             decreasing level of consciousness

          -  Patients with known allergic or hypersensitivity reactions to parenteral
             iron,parenteral dextran, parenteral iron-dextran, or parenteral iron-polysaccharide
             preparations (Ferumoxytol Investigator's Drug Brochure, 2009)

          -  Patients who are pregnant, lactating, or who suspect they might be pregnant

          -  Patients with known liver function insufficiency (AST and/or ALT greater than 2.5x
             upper limits of normal) or stage IV (GFR 15-29 mL/min/1.73 m2) or stage V (GFR &lt;15
             mL/min/1.73 m2) renal insufficiency

          -  Subjects who have a contraindication for MRI: metal in their bodies (a cardiac
             pacemaker or other incompatible device), are severely agitated, or have an allergy to
             GBCA

          -  Subjects with known hepatic insufficiency or cirrhosis

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of
             the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with ferumoxytol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
    <email>neuwelte@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cynthia A Lacy, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
    <email>lacyc@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
      <email>neuweltn@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Cynthia A Lacy, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-5626</phone>
      <email>lacyc@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edward A Neuwelt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 30, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 16, 2009</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ferumoxytol</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic Imaging</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ferumoxytol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
