<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="359">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01180816</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0912010814</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01180816</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial Of Super-Selective Intraarterial Cerebral Infusion Of Temozolomide (TEMODAR) For Treatment Of Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma Multiforme And Anaplastic Astrocytoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>PHASE I TRIAL OF SUPER-SELECTIVE INTRAARTERIAL CEREBRAL INFUSION OF TEMOZOLOMIDE (TEMODAR) FOR TREATMENT OF NEWLY DIAGNOSED GLIOBLASTOMA MULTIFORME AND ANAPLASTIC ASTROCYTOMA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The high-grade malignant brain tumors, glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) and anaplastic
      astrocytoma (AA), comprise the majority of all primary brain tumors in adults.  This group
      of tumors also exhibits the most aggressive behavior, resulting in median overall survival
      durations of only 9-12 months for GBM, and 3-4 years for AA. Initial therapy has consisted
      of surgical resection, external beam radiation or both.  More recently, a Phase 3 clinical
      published by Stupp et al in 2005 showed a benefit for using radiotherapy plus concomitant
      and adjuvant Temozolomide.  Still, all patients experience a recurrence after first-line
      therapy, so improvements in both first-line and salvage therapy are critical to enhancing
      quality-of-life and prolonging survival.  It is unknown if currently used intravenous (IV)
      therapies even cross the blood brain barrier (BBB). Superselective Intra-arterial Cerebral
      Infusion (SIACI) is a technique that can effectively increase the concentration of drug
      delivered to the brain while sparing the body of systemic side effects.   One currently used
      drug called Temozolomide (Temodar) has been shown to be active in human brain tumors but its
      actual CNS penetration is unknown.  This phase I clinical research trial will test the
      hypothesis that following the standard 42 day Temozolomide/radiotherapy regimen,
      Temozolomide can be safely used by direct intracranial superselective intra-arterial
      cerebral infusion (SIACI) up to a dose of 250mg/m2, followed by the standard maintenance
      cycle of temozolomide to ultimately enhance survival of patients with newly diagnosed
      GBM/AA. The investigators will determine the toxicity profile and maximum tolerated dose
      (MTD) of SIACI Temozolomide. The investigators expect that this project will provide
      important information regarding the utility of SIACI Temozolomide therapy for malignant
      gliomas, and may alter the way these drugs are delivered to our patients in the near future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current standard of care for newly diagnosed GBM is radiation therapy plus concomitant
      oral Temozolomide of doses of 75mg/m2 up to 150mg/m2. Because of the blood brain barrier
      (BBB) where drugs do not penetrate the blood vessel walls well to get into the brain, no one
      knows for sure if these oral drugs actually get into the brain after infusion.  Previous
      studies have shown that intra-carotid artery (intra-arterial) delivery is superior to
      standard intravenous or oral delivery for increasing the penetration of drug to the brain.
      Previous techniques using intra arterial (intracarotid) infusion still were non-selective as
      drug delivery still went to all blood vessels in the brain, so patients still had
      significant adverse events, such as blindness.  Newer techniques in interventional
      neuroradiology have allowed for a more selective delivery of catheters into the arterial
      tree where chemotherapies can be delivered without the risk of adverse affects such as
      blindness.  In fact, studies here at WCMC and MSKCC have developed very new and exciting
      super selective intra-arterial delivery treatment for Pediatric Eye Tumors with little
      toxicity and a clinical trial of intra-arterial delivery of Avastin is currently underway
      for GBM. Therefore, this trial will ask one simple question:  Is it safe to deliver a dose
      of Temozolomide intrarterially using these super selective delivery techniques in addition
      to the standard oral route of administration?  This should not only increase the amount of
      drug that gets to the tumor but also spare the patient many of the adverse effects from a
      less selective delivery.  Prior to this single dose of intra-arterial Temozolomide, the
      patient will also receive a dose of mannitol that will increase the permeability of the
      blood brain barrier to improve delivery of the agent to the brain.   After this single dose
      of mannitol and Temozolomide, the patient will be evaluated for 4 weeks to assess for
      toxicity. If there is no toxicity at this point, then the patient will proceed with oral
      maintenance Temozolomide chemotherapy.  In summary, this is a Phase I trial that is designed
      to test the safety of a single dose of intra-arterial delivery of Temozolomide immediately
      following 42 days of radiotherapy/oral temozolomide and prior to starting oral maintenance
      Temozolomide. :  PCP prophylaxis with Bactrim will be provided to subjects on steroid
      therapy unless they are allergic to sulfa where alternate form of prophylaxis will be
      provided.  Dapsone 100 mg orally once daily is usually effective, but methemoglobinemia and
      hemolysis in G6PD-deficient individuals can occur.[1] Inhalation with pentamidine is another
      option.[2] Similar to treatment of HIV patients, it is administered by aerosol every month
      but can cause wheezing from bronchoconstriction. Both agents are less effective than
      TMP-SMX, and breakthrough PCP cases have been reported. The third option is atovaquone,
      which is given orally, 750-1500 mg daily.[3,4] This agent has been used for treatment of
      non-acutely ill patients with PCP, and in recent years has been used for PCP prophylaxis.
      Rash has been reported, but usually is well tolerated.  Therefore the prophylaxis will vary
      on a case to case basis.

      To summarize:

      Current Standard of Care Therapy:

      Days 1-42: Adjuvant dose of Temozolomide 75mg/m2 for 42 days concomitant with focal
      radiotherapy Day 42: 4 week rest period Day 70:  Maintenance dose of Temozolomide 150mg/m2
      once daily for Days 1-5 of a 28 day cycle for 6 cycles

      Experimental portion of this proposal:

      Days 1-42:  Adjuvant dose of Temozolomide 75mg/m2 for 42 days concomitant with focal
      radiotherapy Day 42: Single Intra-arterial Mannitol to increase the permeability of the
      blood brain barrier followed by Intra-arterial Temozolomide single dose (starting at 75mg/m2
      and up to 250mg/m2) followed by 4 week rest period Day 70: Maintenance dose of Temozolomide
      150mg/m2 once daily for Days 1-5 of a 28 day cycle for 6 cycles

      Therefore the experimental aspects of this treatment plan will include:

        1. On day 42, subjects will first be treated with Mannitol prior to chemotherapy infusion
           (Mannitol 25%; 3-10 mLs for 30seconds) in order to disrupt the blood brain barrier.
           This technique has been used in several thousand patients in previous studies for the
           IA delivery of chemotherapy for malignant glioma.

        2. Following the addition of mannitol, the investigators will deliver a single SIACI dose
           of Temozolomide for patients with high-grade glioma.  After a one-cycle observation
           period to assess for toxicity from the IA infusion, the subject will receive the
           standard oral maintenance regimen of Temozolomide chemotherapy. The Intra-Arterial
           Infusion Procedure will be done under general anesthesia and standard monitoring will
           occur.

      The dose escalation algorithm is as follows:  The investigators will use a single
      intracranial superselective intra-arterial infusion of Temozolomide, starting at a dose of
      75mg/m2 in the first three patients.   Assuming no dose limiting toxicity during the next 28
      days after the infusion, the patient will then begin standard maintenance oral Temozolomide
      chemotherapy regimen.  The doses will be escalated from 75 to 100, to 150, 200, and finally
      250mg/m2 in this Phase I trial.

      Inclusion criteria Include: Males or females, =&gt;18 years of age, with newly documented
      histologic diagnosis of glioblastoma multiforme (GBM), anaplastic astrocytoma (AA) or
      anaplastic mixed oligoastrocytoma (AOA).

      Both hematologic and non-hematologic toxicity from the IA infusion of Temozolomide will be
      determined and scored according to the NCI Common Toxicity Criteria (version 4.02).
      Monitoring will also include a MRI of the brain at 4 weeks post infusion.

      Most patients with GBM are also monitored every two months with serial history, neurological
      and physical examinations together with serial blood counts, prothrombin time (PT), partial
      thromboplastin time (PTT) and chemistries. In addition, most patients with GBM have an MRI
      performed every two cycles or approximately every two months to assess for tumor
      progression.  .

      Since this is a Phase I trial, response is not a primary endpoint.  However, the
      investigators will evaluate response to the one time IA Temozolomide therapy with a MRI with
      the injection of contrast approximately 4 weeks after infusion.  Follow-up of all patients
      in the trial after the IA Temozolomide therapy will continue until disease progression or
      death. Survival will be measured from the time of the dose of IA Temozolomide®.  The
      investigators expect patients in the trial to be monitored for 12 months.

      This treatment may be harmful to a fetus if you were pregnant.  If you are a female of
      childbearing potential, you will be asked to practice medically accepted birth control
      methods while participating in this research study and for 3 months following your
      treatment.  These methods include oral contraceptives, contraceptive shots, and barrier
      methods, such as condom use, sponges, and diaphragms.  Fertile males are required to use
      these barrier methods.

      The patient may be responsible for any additional costs associated with enrollment in the
      trial.  All costs of the IA delivery and the cost of the drug will be submitted to the
      patient's insurance provider.  WCMC will not be named as a sponsor of the study nor will it
      cover the cost of the experimental procedure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the safety of superselective intra-arterial cerebral infusion of Temozolomide up to a dose of 250 mg/m2 IA.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite overall response rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Six-month progression-free survival (PFS) and overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout the study.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Temodar</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Super-Selective Intraarterial Intracranial Infusion of Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>This phase I clinical research trial will test the hypothesis that temozolomide can be safely used by direct intracranial superselective intraarterial infusion up to a dose of 250mg/m2 to ultimately enhance survival of patients with newly diagnosed GBM/AA.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Temodar</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        A. Criteria for Inclusion:

          1. Male or female patients of =&gt;18 years of age.

          2. Patients with a newly documented histologic diagnosis of glioblastoma multiforme
             (GBM), anaplastic astrocytoma (AA) or anaplastic mixed oligoastrocytoma (AOA).

          3. Patients must have at least one confirmed and evaluable tumor site. A confirmed tumor
             site is one in which is biopsy-proven.  NOTE: Radiographic procedures (e.g.,
             Gd-enhanced MRI or CT scans) documenting existing lesions must have been performed
             within three weeks of treatment on this research study.

          4. Patients must have a Karnofsky performance status =&gt;60% (or the equivalent ECOG level
             of 0-2)  (see Appendix A; Performance Status Evaluation) and an expected survival of
             =&gt; three months.

          5. No chemotherapy for two weeks prior to treatment under this research protocol and no
             external beam radiation for two weeks prior to treatment under this research
             protocol.

          6. Patients must have adequate hematologic reserve with WBC=&gt;3000mm3, absolute
             neutrophils =&gt;1500mm3 and platelets =&gt;100,000 mm3.  Patients who are on Coumadin must
             have a platelet count of =&gt;150,000 mm3

          7. Pre-enrollment chemistry parameters must show: bilirubin&lt;1.5X the institutional upper
             limit of normal (IUNL); AST or ALT&lt;2.5X IUNL and creatinine&lt;1.5X IUNL.

          8. Pre-enrollment coagulation parameters (PT and PTT) must be &lt;=1.5X the IUNL. Patients
             taking Coumadin must have an INR less than 2.0.

          9. Concomitant Medications:

             Growth factor(s): Must not have received within 1 week of entry onto this study.

             Steroids: Systemic corticosteroid therapy is permissible in patients with CNS tumors
             for treatment of increased intracranial pressure or symptomatic tumor edema. Patients
             with CNS tumors who are receiving dexamethasone must be on a stable or decreasing
             dose for at least 1 week prior to study entry.  We do not believe that study
             procedures place subjects with increased intracranial pressure at any additional
             risk.

         10. Study Specific: Patients on enzyme-inducing anticonvulsants or non-enzyme inducing
             anticonvulsants will be allowed in the study. Patients receiving proton pump
             inhibitor or H2 blockers will be allowed in the study. Patients taking antacids will
             be allowed in the study.

         11. Patients who experience dose delays or interruptions in first 42 days of treatment
             will still be eligible for the one time dose of SIACI Temozolomide

         12. Patients must agree to use a medically effective method of contraception during and
             for a period of three months after the treatment period.  A pregnancy test will be
             performed on each premenopausal female of childbearing potential immediately prior to
             entry into the research study.

         13. Women of childbearing potential and fertile men will be informed as to the potential
             risk of procreation while participating in this research trial and will be advised
             that they must use effective contraception during and for a period of three months
             after the treatment period.

         14. Patients on steroids must receive prophylaxis for PCP pneumonia with Bactrim, unless
             they have a history of allergy to sulfa drugs in which case, alternate prophylaxis
             will be used.

         15. Patients able to understand and give written informed consent and those patients that
             are cognitively impaired (which is common in GBM) are eligible for the trial.
             Informed consent must be obtained at the time of patient screening (prior to Day 0 of
             the procedure) either by the patient or a legalized authorized representative (LAR)
             of the patient (healthcare proxy). All subjects must ascent to therapy. If they are
             able to understand and provide written informed consent, then consent must be
             obtained from the Legally Authorized Representative (LAR)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - 1. Women who are pregnant or lactating.

        2. Patients with significant intercurrent medical or psychiatric conditions that would
        place them at increased risk or affect their ability to receive or comply with treatment
        or post-treatment clinical monitoring.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Boockvar, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-1996</phone>
    <email>jab2029@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College Department of Neurological Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Boockvar, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-1996</phone>
      <email>jab2029@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Trisha Ali-Shaw</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-7373</phone>
      <email>tra2002@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Boockvar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ehud Lavi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pierre Gobin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Athos Patsalides, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susan C. Pannullo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philip Stieg, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Theodore Schwartz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kane Prior, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ronald Scheff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 18, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 10, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John A. Boockvar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GBM</keyword>
  <keyword>AA</keyword>
  <keyword>AO</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Malignant</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiforme</keyword>
  <keyword>Anaplastic</keyword>
  <keyword>Astrocytoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
