<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="93">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01931098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BTTC12-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01931098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Pazopanib Plus Topotecan for Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Oral Pazopanib Plus Oral Topotecan Metronomic Antiangiogenic Therapy for Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (A) Without Prior Bevacizumab Exposure and (B) After Failing Prior Bevacizumab</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BRAIN TUMOR TRIALS COLLABORATIVE (BTTC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if pazopanib when given in combination
      with topotecan can help to control glioblastoma.  The safety of this drug combination will
      also be studied.

      The study doctor can explain how the study drugs are designed to work.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be assigned to a study
      group based on if you have received bevacizumab or not:

        -  You will be in Group A if you have not received bevacizumab in the past.

        -  You will be in Group B if you have received bevacizumab in the past.

      Both groups will receive pazopanib and topotecan at the same dose level and on the same
      schedule.   Up to 34 participants will be enrolled in Group 1 and up to 32 participants will
      be enrolled in Group 2.

      Study Drug Administration:

      Each cycle is 28 days.

      You will take capsules of topotecan by mouth 1 time everyday at about the same time each
      day.  You should swallow the capsules whole with at least 1 cup (8 ounces) of water, with or
      without food.

      You will take tablets of pazopanib by mouth 1 time every day at about the same time each
      day.  They should be taken on an empty stomach (at least 1 hour before and 2 hour after
      eating) with about 1 cup (8 ounces) of water.

      If you vomit while taking the study drugs, you should not take more capsules before the next
      scheduled dose.

      You will be given a study drug diary to record the times that you take the study drugs and
      if you vomit.  You should bring the diary to each study visit.

      Study Visits:

      At Week 1, your blood pressure will be measured.

      At Week 2, your blood pressure will be measured and blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn
      for routine tests.

      At Week 4, you will have an EKG.

      Every 4 weeks:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine and biomarker testing.

        -  Urine will be collected to check your kidney function.

      Every 8 weeks:

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn to check thyroid function.

        -  You will have an EKG.

      If you are in Group A, you will have a brain MRI or CT scan at Week 4 of Cycle 2, and then
      every other cycle after that (Cycles 4, 6, 8 and so on) to check the status of the disease.
      You will also complete the symptom questionnaire at these visits.

      If you are in Group B, you will have a brain MRI or CT scan at Week 4 of Cycles 1, 2, 3, and
      then every other cycle after that (Cycles 5, 7, 9 and so on)  to check the status of  the
      disease.  You will also complete the symptom questionnaire at these visits.

      At any time during the study, extra tests may be performed if the doctor thinks they are
      needed for your safety.  The study doctor will tell you more about any extra tests.

      End-of-Treatment Visit:

      Within 14 days after your last dose of the study drugs, you will have an end-of-treatment
      visit.  The following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine and biomarker testing.  This blood
           draw will also include a pregnancy test if you can become pregnant.

      Length of Treatment:

      You may take the study drugs for up to 1 year.  You will no longer be able to take the study
      drugs if the disease gets worse, if intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to
      follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the long-term follow-up phone calls.

      Long-Term Follow-Up Calls:

      After you have stopped taking the study drugs and completed your end-of-treatment visit, the
      study staff will call you 1 time every 3 months from then on to check on how you are doing.
      Each phone call should last about 5 minutes.

      This is an investigational study.  Pazopanib is FDA approved and commercially available for
      the treatment of renal cell cancer.  Topotecan is FDA approved and commercially available
      for the treatment of lung cancer.  In this study, the combination of pazopanib and topotecan
      is being used for research purposes only.

      Up to 66 participants will be enrolled in this multicenter study.  Up to 15 will take part
      at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival Rate for Recurrent Glioblastoma (rGBM) Patients with No Prior Bevacizumab (BEV)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>A maximum of 34 patients observed in a two-stage Simon optimum design.  In the first stage, 9 patients accrued.  If two or more patients are progression-free at 6 months (PFS6), an additional 25 patients accrued.   Registration halted  after 9 patients until at least 2 patients are progression free at six months.  If 9 or more out of 34 have PFS6, then the study declared promising.  Study has a 5% chance of declaring promise if the PFS6 rate is at most 15%.  It has an 80% chance of declaring promise if the PFS rate is at least 35%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival Rate for Recurrent Glioblastoma (rGBM) Patients with Prior Bevacizumab</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>In the group that failed bevacizumab, a maximum of 32 patients observed in a two-stage Simon optimum design.  In the first stage, 14 patients accrued.  If one or more patients is progression-free at 3 months (PFS3), an additional 18 patients accrued.  Registration halted after 14 patients until at least 1 patient is progression free at 3-months.  If 2 or more out of 32 have PFS3, then study will be declared promising.  This study has a 5% chance of declaring promise if the PFS3 rate is at most 1%.  It has an 80% chance of declaring promise if the PFS rate is at least 12%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - Recurrent Glioblastoma - No Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients treated with the combination of topotecan and pazopanib at the following doses:
Pazopanib: Starting dose is 600 mg (3x200mg) per day to be taken orally, daily, continuous, without food at least one hour before or two hours after a meal.
Topotecan:  Starting dose of topotecan is 0.25 mg orally, daily, continuous.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Recurrent Glioblastoma with Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients treated with the combination of topotecan and pazopanib at the following doses:
Pazopanib: Starting dose is 600 mg (3x200mg) per day to be taken orally, daily, continuous, without food at least one hour before or two hours after a meal.
Topotecan:  Starting dose of topotecan is 0.25 mg orally, daily, continuous.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pazopanib</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose: 600 mg by mouth daily for a 28 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - Recurrent Glioblastoma - No Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Recurrent Glioblastoma with Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GW786034</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Topotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose: 0.25 mg by mouth daily for a 28 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - Recurrent Glioblastoma - No Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Recurrent Glioblastoma with Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hycamtin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Symptom Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Symptom questionnaire completed at baseline for both Groups. Group A: Completion at week 4 of cycle 2, then every odd cycle after that. Group B: Completion at week 4 of cycle 1, 2, 3, then every other cycle after that.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - Recurrent Glioblastoma - No Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Recurrent Glioblastoma with Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phone Calls</intervention_name>
    <description>After study drugs stopped and end-of-treatment visit completed, study staff will call patient 1 time every 3 months.  Each phone call should last about 5 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - Recurrent Glioblastoma - No Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Recurrent Glioblastoma with Prior Bevacizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with histologically proven intracranial glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) or
             gliosarcoma (GS). Patients will be eligible if the original histology was low-grade
             glioma and a subsequent histological diagnosis of a GBM or GS is made. Patients must
             have evidence of progression of the GBM or GS on MRI or CT scan.

          2. Patient must have failed prior chemoradiation with temozolomide and any other
             therapies except BEV (group A), or must have failed primary chemoradiation and a
             BEV-incorporating treatment (group B).

          3. Patients may have had treatment for no more than 2 prior relapses. Relapse is defined
             as progression following initial therapy (i.e. radiation+/- chemo if that was used as
             initial therapy). The intent therefore is that patients had no more than 3 prior
             therapies (initial and treatment for 2 relapses). If the patient had a surgical
             resection for relapsed disease and no anti-cancer therapy was instituted for up to 12
             weeks, and the patient undergoes another surgical resection, this is considered as 1
             relapse. For patients who had prior therapy for a low-grade glioma, the surgical
             diagnosis of a high-grade glioma will be considered the first relapse

          4. Patients must be greater than 12 weeks following completion of chemoradiation or any
             additional radiation to reduce the chance of pseudoprogression.

          5. Measurable disease is required unless patient is post-operative and in that case
             patient can have no evidence of disease.

          6. All patients must sign an informed consent indicating that they are aware of the
             investigational nature of this study. Patients must have signed an authorization for
             the release of their protected health information. Patients must be registered in the
             MD ANDERSON CANCER CENTER Office of Multicenter Clinical Research (OMCR) database
             prior to treatment with study drugs.

          7. Archived tumor tissue must be available for all subjects for biomarker analysis
             before or during treatment. Samples must be provided within 4 weeks of enrollment.

          8. Tissue to be analyzed for MGMT (if not already performed) and additional analyses
             noted in correlative biomarker section.

          9. Patients must be &gt;/= 18 years old.

         10. Patients must have a Karnofsky performance status of &gt;/= 60.

         11. At the time of registration: Patients must have recovered from the toxic effects of
             prior therapy: &gt;/= 28 days from any investigational agent, &gt;/=28 days from prior
             cytotoxic therapy, &gt;/=14 days from vincristine, &gt;/=42 days from nitrosoureas, &gt;/=21
             days from procarbazine administration, &gt;21 days from bevacizumab administration and
             &gt;/=7 days for non-cytotoxic agents, e.g., interferon, tamoxifen, thalidomide,
             cis-retinoic acid, etc. (radiosensitizer does not count). Any questions related to
             the definition of non-cytotoxic agents should be directed to the Study Chair.

         12. Patients must have adequate organ function: 1) Bone marrow function (WBC &gt;/=3,000/µl,
             ANC &gt;/=1,500/mm3, platelet count of &gt;/=100,000/mm3, and hemoglobin &gt;/=10 gm/dl).
             Eligibility level for hemoglobin may be reached by transfusion. 2) Liver function
             (alanine amino transferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt;2.5XULN(upper
             limit of normal), and total bilirubin &lt;1.5XULN), prothrombin time (PT) or
             international normalized ratio (INR), and activated partial thromboplastin time
             (aPTT) &lt;/=1.2XULN. Concomitant elevations in bilirubin and AST/ALT above 1.0xULN are
             not permitted. Subjects receiving anticoagulant therapy are eligible if their INR is
             stable and within the recommended range for the desired level of anticoagulation. 3)
             Renal function (creatinine &lt;/=1.5mg/dL (133 µmol/L), or if &gt;1.5mg/dL, calculated
             creatinine clearance &gt;/=50cc/min), and urine protein to creatinine ratio of &lt;1 before
             starting therapy. 4) These tests must be performed within 14 days prior to
             registration.

         13. Patients must have shown unequivocal radiographic evidence for tumor progression by
             MRI or CT scan. A scan should be performed within 14 days prior to registration and
             on a steroid dose that has been stable or decreasing for at least 5 days. If the
             steroid dose is increased between the date of imaging and registration a new baseline
             MR/CT is required. The same type of scan, i.e., MRI or CT must be used throughout the
             period of protocol treatment for tumor measurement.

         14. Patients having undergone recent resection of recurrent or progressive tumor will be
             eligible as long as all of the following conditions apply: 1) They have recovered
             from the effects of surgery and be &gt; 28 days from surgery. 2) Residual disease
             following resection of recurrent GBM or GS is not mandated for eligibility into the
             study. To best assess the extent of residual disease post-operatively, a CT/ MRI
             should be done no later than 96 hours in the immediate post-operative period or at
             least 4 weeks post-operatively, within 14 days prior to registration. If the 96-hour
             scan is more than 14 days before registration, the scan needs to be repeated. If the
             steroid dose is increased between the date of imaging and registration, a new
             baseline MRI/CT is required on a stable steroid dosage for at least 5 days.

         15. Patients must have failed prior radiation therapy and must have an interval of
             greater than or equal to 12 weeks from the completion of radiation therapy to study
             entry.

         16. Patients with prior therapy that included interstitial brachytherapy or stereotactic
             radiosurgery must have confirmation of true progressive disease rather than radiation
             necrosis based upon either PET or Thallium scanning, MR spectroscopy or
             surgical/pathological documentation of disease.

         17. A female is eligible to enter and participate in this study if she is of: 1)
             Non-childbearing potential (i.e., physiologically incapable of becoming pregnant),
             including any female who has had: A hysterectomy; A bilateral oophorectomy
             (ovariectomy); A bilateral tubal ligation; Is post-menopausal: a) Subjects not using
             hormone replacement therapy (HRT) must have experienced total cessation of menses for
             &gt;/= 1 year and be greater than 45 years in age, OR, in questionable cases, have a
             follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) value &gt;40 mIU/mL and an estradiol value &lt; 40pg/mL
             (&lt;140 pmol/L).b) Subjects using HRT must have experienced total cessation of menses
             for &gt;= 1 year and be greater than 45 years of age OR have had documented evidence of
             menopause based on FSH and estradiol concentrations prior to initiation of HRT.

         18. ( 17. continued) 2) Childbearing potential, including any female who has had a
             negative serum pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to the first dose of study
             treatment, preferably as close to the first dose as possible, and agrees to use
             adequate contraception. GSK acceptable contraceptive methods, when used consistently
             and in accordance with both the product label and the instructions of the physician,
             are as follows: a) Complete abstinence from sexual intercourse for 14 days before
             exposure to investigational product, through the dosing period, and for at least 21
             days after the last dose of investigational product. Oral contraceptive, either
             combined or progestogen alone. b) Injectable progestogen. c) Implants of
             levonorgestrel. d) Estrogenic vaginal ring.

         19. (18. continued) e) Percutaneous contraceptive patches. f) Intrauterine device (IUD)
             or intrauterine system (IUS) with a documented failure rate of less than 1% per year.
             g) Male partner sterilization (vasectomy with documentation of azoospermia) prior to
             the female subject's entry into the study, and this male is the sole partner for that
             subject. h) Double barrier method: condom and an occlusive cap (diaphragm or
             cervical/vault caps) with a vaginal spermicidal agent
             (foam/gel/film/cream/suppository). Female subjects who are lactating should
             discontinue nursing prior to the first dose of study drug and should refrain from
             nursing throughout the treatment period and for 14 days following the last dose of
             study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must not have any significant medical illnesses that in the investigator's
             opinion cannot be adequately controlled with appropriate therapy or would compromise
             the patient's ability to tolerate this therapy.

          2. Patients with a history of any other cancer (except non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma in-situ of the cervix), unless in complete remission and off of all therapy
             for that disease for a minimum of 3 years are ineligible.

          3. Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may increase the risk for
             gastrointestinal bleeding including, but not limited to: Active peptic ulcer disease;
             Known intraluminal metastatic lesion/s with risk of bleeding; Inflammatory bowel
             disease (e.g. ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease), or other gastrointestinal
             conditions with increased risk of perforation; History of abdominal fistula,
             gastrointestinal perforation, or intra abdominal abscess within 28 days prior to
             beginning study treatment.

          4. Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may affect absorption of
             investigational product including, but not limited to: Malabsorption syndrome; Major
             resection of the stomach or small bowel.

          5. Presence of uncontrolled infection.

          6. Corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 480 msecs using Bazett's formula.

          7. History of any one or more of the following cardiovascular conditions within the past
             6 months: Cardiac angioplasty or stenting; Myocardial infarction; Unstable angina;
             Coronary artery bypass graft surgery; 4Symptomatic peripheral vascular disease..

          8. Class III or IV congestive heart failure, as defined by the New York Heart
             Association (NYHA).

          9. Poorly controlled hypertension [defined as systolic blood pressure (SBP) of &gt;/=140
             mmHg or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) of &gt;/= 90mmHg]. Note: Initiation or adjustment
             of antihypertensive medication(s) is permitted prior to study entry. BP must be
             re-assessed on two occasions that are separated by a minimum of 1 hour; on each of
             these occasions, the mean (of 3 readings) SBP / DBP values from each BP assessment
             must be ≤ 140/90 mmHg in order for a subject to be eligible for the study.

         10. History of cerebrovascular accident including transient ischemic attack (TIA),
             pulmonary embolism or untreated deep venous thrombosis (DVT) within the past 6
             months. Note: Subjects with recent DVT who have been treated with therapeutic
             anti-coagulating agents for at least 6 weeks are eligible.

         11. Prior major surgery or trauma within 28 days and/or presence of any non-healing
             wound, fracture, or ulcer (procedures such as catheter placement not considered to be
             major).

         12. Evidence of active bleeding or bleeding diathesis.

         13. Known endobronchial lesions and/or lesions infiltrating major pulmonary vessels.

         14. Hemoptysis in excess of 2.5 mL (or one half teaspoon) within 8 weeks of first dose of
             study drug.

         15. Any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical, psychiatric, or other condition
             that could interfere with subject's safety, provision of informed consent, or
             compliance to study procedures.

         16. Unable or unwilling to discontinue use of inducers and inhibitors of CYP450 listed
             for at least 14 days or five half-lives of a drug (whichever is longer) prior to the
             first dose of study drug and for the duration of the study. CYP3A4 substrates can be
             administered, but investigators will need to be aware of possible increased or
             decreased effectiveness of the non-study drug and this should be recorded in
             concomitant medications. BCRP and PgP inducers and inhibitors will be also
             prohibited.

         17. Any ongoing toxicity from prior anti-cancer therapy that is &gt; Grade 1 and/or that is
             progressing in severity, except alopecia.

         18. Ongoing use of enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic agents (EIAEDs), unless 2 week washout
             has elapsed form last dose of EIAED.

         19. Patients must not have any significant medical illnesses that in the investigator's
             opinion cannot be adequately controlled with appropriate therapy or would compromise
             the patient's ability to tolerate this therapy

         20. Patients with a known hypersensitivity to pazopanib or topotecan or to their
             excipients.

         21. Patients on total daily dose of dexamethasone greater than 16 mg/day.

         22. Patients must not have received prior therapy with topotecan, pazopanib, or related
             drugs such as tyrosine kinase inhibitors, VEGF inhibitors (except bevacizumab).

         23. Patients must not have any disease that will obscure toxicity or dangerously alter
             drug metabolism.

         24. Patients on steroid dose greater than 16 mg daily are not eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marta Penas-Prado, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morris Groves, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Texas Oncology - Austin Brain Tumor Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marta Penas-Prado, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-2883</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedar-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Hollywood</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center - Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University, Feinberg School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27523</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MUSC Hollings Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Oncology Austin Brain Tumor Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>U.T. Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Methodist Hospital System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84102-1959</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aurora Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 18, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 23, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>CNS</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>rGBM</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Intracranial glioblastoma multiforme</keyword>
  <keyword>GBM</keyword>
  <keyword>Gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>GS</keyword>
  <keyword>Pazopanib</keyword>
  <keyword>GW786034</keyword>
  <keyword>Topotecan</keyword>
  <keyword>Hycamtin</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptom questionnaire</keyword>
  <keyword>Phone calls</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Topotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
