<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="15">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01124461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-1625</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01NS066905-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01124461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BIRN (Biomedical Informatics Research Network) Resources Facilitate the Personalization of Malignant Brain Tumor</brief_title>
  <acronym>CONDR</acronym>
  <official_title>BIRN (Biomedical Informatics Research Network)Resources Facilitate the Personalization of Malignant Brain Tumor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to create a comprehensive database of Magnetic Resonance Imaging
      (MRI) and of pathology for patients with brain tumors. Both standard, advanced, and research
      MRI components may be included, these will be analyzed in comparison with pathology results
      if/when a biopsy is obtained, and also used to predict/evaluate responses to therapy. This
      study will create a database of de-identified MRI images which include these techniques so
      that brain tumors can be studied over time (longitudinally) in an organized manner.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Glioblastoma (GBM) is the most common primary malignant neoplasm of the adult brain. Even
      after multimodal therapy, treatment outcomes remain poor, with a median survival of
      approximately one year. A central challenge facing investigators in the modern era is how to
      resolve the heterogeneity inherent in GBM pathology using technology and how to identify
      individual genetic or molecular markers that indicate how treatment can be individualized to
      improve outcomes with an emphasis on using this heterogeneity to improve patient care. With
      advances in imaging and the potential for genetic sequence analysis, increasingly clinicians
      and researchers have focused on specific clinical, imaging, and genetic biomarkers to allow
      the personalization of brain tumor treatment in an attempt to improve the limitations we
      have faced in extending patient survival from this devastating disease. Specific
      methodologies have been developed to allow genetic microarray analysis of patient's tumor
      tissue, and this type of research is ongoing at one of our participating institutions,
      Swedish Medical Center. In addition, centers such as Washington University School of
      Medicine in St. Louis, Missouri have extensive experience pursuing advanced imaging
      biomarkers and their applications to clinical neuro-oncology research.

      Of importance, however, although clinicians and researchers have come to recognize that
      in-vivo imaging technologies may have as much if not more relevance than genetic biomarkers
      in the personalization of brain tumor treatment, clinical trials attempting to validate
      these biomarkers and correlate them with particular outcomes have been limited by a lack of
      technology infrastructure that would allow multi-site image acquisition, processing, data
      analysis, subsequent correlation with clinical and genetic data, and ultimately sharing of
      anonymized data with other researchers from a central archiving site. BIRN infrastructure
      will integrate neuroimaging, genetic microarray, and clinical data with a focus on
      integrating imaging biomarkers into prospective clinical research in patients with malignant
      brain tumors.

      In this project, a consortium of neuro-oncology research centers will be federated to obtain
      a unified set of clinical, genetic, and imaging data. In the initial phase, 100 patients
      with malignant brain tumors at two participating sites will be studied. Our ultimate goal
      will be to use the developed protocols and informatics infrastructure to expand the
      consortium to include a large number neuro-oncology clinical sites suitable for executing
      large scale clinical trials that will facilitate the generation of data to identify which
      imaging biomarkers are relevant for the personalization of brain tumor treatment and
      ultimately improvement of outcomes for patients with this devastating disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>GLIOBLASTOMA MULTIFORME</condition>
  <condition>Brain Neoplasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brain Tumor</arm_group_label>
    <description>Brain neoplasms, malignant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Brain tumor tissue, Whole Blood.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Neurology clinic
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be enrolled in this clinical trial pre-operatively      anticipating a
             surgical resection with anticipation that the patient carries a likely diagnosis of
             malignant glioma.

          -  Patients will only be enrolled if it is anticipated that the resection will give
             significant tissue for subsequent genetic analysis (1 cm of tumor tissue)

          -  If patients at surgery are found to carry an alternative tissue diagnosis, the
             patient's preoperative imaging, clinical, and pathological information will be
             uploaded into the database, but the patient will not  be counted as one of the
             participants

          -  Ability to undergo serial MR studies

          -  Enrollment KPS &gt; 70

          -  Anticipation that surgery will allow subtotal resection or gross total  resection,
             facilitating removal of tissue specimens for genomic analysis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to participate in serial MR studies

          -  KPS &lt; 70

          -  &gt; 70 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Marcus, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anna Carlson, RN</last_name>
    <phone>314-747-8273</phone>
    <email>carlsona@mir.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna Carlson, RN</last_name>
      <phone>314-747-8273</phone>
      <email>carlsona@mir.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Marcus, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 2, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 13, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Daniel Marcus/ Research Assistant Professor of Rad</name_title>
    <organization>Washington University-RADIOLOGY RADIATION-SCIENCES-SCHOOL OF MEDICINE</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant Brain Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer of the Brain</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
