<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="435">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00054756</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030098</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-DK-0098</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00054756</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Thyrotropin-Releasing Hormone in Normal Volunteers and in Patients With Thyroid or Pituitary Abnormalities</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of Thyrotropin Releasing Hormone in Patients With Thyroid or Pituitary Abnormalities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will determine the safety and activity of a new formulation of
      thyrotropin-releasing hormone (TRH), a drug used for diagnosing and evaluating patients with
      certain thyroid gland abnormalities.  Normal thyroid gland function depends on proper
      chemical signaling between the thyroid gland, the hypothalamus (the part of the brain where
      TRH is made), and the pituitary (another part of the brain).  The TRH test helps assess this
      interaction.  Production of the only FDA-approved preparation of TRH was stopped in July
      2002.  As a result, to have a continuous source of TRH available for NIH clinical and
      research purposes, the NIH Clinical Center (CC) Pharmacy Department produced a
      pharmaceutical grade formulation of TRH for patient use.  This study will test the CC
      formulation in healthy volunteers to show that its activity and side effects are similar to
      those of the previously available commercial test preparation.  It will then be studied in
      CC patients for whom the diagnostic test is recommended.

      Healthy volunteers between 18 and 65 years of age and all patients requiring TRH evaluation
      of hypothalamic-pituitary-thyroid gland interaction may be eligible for this study.
      Patients include those with pituitary reserve, inconsistent thyroid function test,
      inappropriate TSH secretion, or pre- and post-operative evaluation of pituitary tumors.
      Normal volunteers will be screened with a medical history, physical examination, and blood
      tests.  Women of child-bearing potential will be given a pregnancy test; pregnant and
      breast-feeding women may not participate.

      The TRH test procedure will be the same for healthy volunteers and patients.  All
      participants fast from midnight before the morning of the test. In the morning, a catheter
      (flexible plastic tube) is inserted into an arm vein for easy injection of the TRH and
      collection of blood samples.  Blood pressure is monitored before and during the test.  A
      blood sample is drawn, and then TRH is given through the catheter over a 1-minute period.
      Another nine blood samples are collected over a 3-hour period from the time of the TRH
      injection for measuring levels of various hormones.  A total of less than 4 tablespoons of
      blood is taken for the test.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Thyrotropin releasing hormone (TRH) is a neuropeptide used in the diagnostic evaluation of
      patients with dysfunction of the hypothalamic-pituitary-thyroid (HPT) axis. In healthy
      individuals, administration of TRH intravenously results in pituitary secretion of
      thyrotropin [thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH)], which in turn stimulates the thyroid gland
      release of thyroid hormones; thyroxine (T4) and triiodothyronine (T3). TRH stimulates the
      secretion of other pituitary hormones under normal physiologic as well as pathologic
      conditions. The purpose of this study is to test the safety and activity of a new
      preparation of TRH produced by the Pharmaceutical Development Section of the Clinical Center
      Pharmacy at the NIH. This preparation is similar to a previously commercially available
      preparation. Normal, healthy adults will be recruited to undergo a standard TRH test using
      the new preparation. TSH, prolactin and thyroid hormones are measured after the
      administration of TRH. After the safety, activity and diagnostic comparability are
      established, the preparation will be used for routine diagnostic testing and research in
      adults and children.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2099</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2099</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>TSH response to TRH</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">99999999</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Pituitary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Thyroid Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TRH (Thyrotropin Releasing Hormone)</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Diagnostic Study Protocol

        All adults and children requiring dynamic testing of the hypothalamic-pituitary axis for
        the evaluation of pituitary reserve, inconsistent thyroid function test, inappropriate TSH
        secretion, or pre-and post-operative evaluation of pituitary adenomas (glycoprotein
        hormone secreting tumors, growth hormone secreting tumors and TSH secreting tumors).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension;

          -  Uncontrolled seizure disorder;

          -  Unstable coronary disease;

          -  Known allergy to TRH.

        Research protocols

        TRH is available for use in other IRB approved research protocols either using the
        standard diagnostic testing protocol or the modified TRH test.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Untreated hypertension;

          -  Coronary artery disease;

          -  History of asthma;

          -  History of seizures;

          -  Pregnancy;

          -  Known allergy to TRH.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monica C Skarulis, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Craig S Cochran, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-1880</phone>
    <email>craigc@bdg10.niddk.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Monica C Skarulis, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-6087</phone>
    <email>monicas@intra.niddk.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2003-DK-0098.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jackson IM. Thyrotropin-releasing hormone. N Engl J Med. 1982 Jan 21;306(3):145-55. Review. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>6798440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haigler ED Jr, Pittman JA Jr, Hershman JM, Baugh CM. Direct evaluation of pituitary thyrotopin reserve utilizing synthetic thyrotopin releasing hormone. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1971 Oct;33(4):573-81. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>4999252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faglia G. The clinical impact of the thyrotropin-releasing hormone test. Thyroid. 1998 Oct;8(10):903-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9827657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 1, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 7, 2003</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypothalamic Releasing Factor</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropeptide</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Pituitary Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Central Hypothyroidism</keyword>
  <keyword>Pituitary Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Thyroid Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyrotropin-Releasing Hormone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
