<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="426">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01014195</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEULS</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH085849</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01014195</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk of Psychopathology and Neurocognitive Impairment in Leukemia Survivors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Risk of Psychopathology and Neurocognitive Impairment in Leukemia Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. This study will evaluate the association between changes in basic cognitive and
           behavioral functioning by the end of chemotherapy treatment, and the later development
           of higher order executive functions in pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL).

        2. The association between acute treatment-related changes in brain integrity and
           subsequent brain maturation in long-term survivors of pediatric ALL will be evaluated.

        3. The association between patterns of behavioral and executive dysfunction and brain
           maturation in long-term survivors of pediatric ALL will be examined.

        4. The association between genetic polymorphisms in key enzyme pathways and higher order
           brain development in long-term survivors of pediatric ALL will be explored.

        5. The associations between biologic and behavioral indices of fatigue/sleep and higher
           order brain development in long-term survivors of pediatric ALL will be explored.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Survival rates for pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) now exceed 80%. With this
      growing population of long-term survivors comes recognition that a considerable proportion
      experience one or more significant late effects. For children undergoing central nervous
      system (CNS) treatment, common late effects include neurocognitive impairment and
      neurobehavioral problems. Although these problems first manifest as subtle difficulties with
      attention and processing speed, they can evolve into deficits in higher order brain
      functions that significantly impact functional skills in a subset of long-term survivors.
      There currently is no method to accurately identify patients at greatest risk for these
      long-term behavioral and neurocognitive problems. Through this proposal, this study  plans
      to utilize existing data collected during acute treatment to identify predictors of
      long-term neurocognitive and brain maturation outcomes. The study also proposes to collect
      data on attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and associated comorbidities, higher
      order executive functions, and structural and functional brain imaging in survivors who are
      at least 8 years of age and greater than 5 years from diagnosis.

      All patients will undergo a single neurocognitive evaluation focused on assessment of higher
      order executive functions. Patients will be evaluated during their regularly scheduled
      annual follow-up visit, when health-related monitoring will also occur. Parents of
      participants will be asked to complete questionnaires designed to assess the family
      environment and the impact of cancer diagnosis on family functioning and parent stress.

      Brain Imaging: To better demonstrate untoward treatment effects upon cortical brain
      development, quantitative MR imaging of myelin integrity using diffusion tensor imaging
      (DTI) and cortical thickness assessment using high resolution volumetric imaging will be
      utilized. All patients will also be evaluated using functional MRI procedures during resting
      state and participation in attention and working memory tasks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Only, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurocognitive assessment of attention, processing speed, and executive functions.</measure>
    <time_frame>Once, at least 5 years post ALL diagnosis and 2 years off treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and DTI and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) of brain structure and function.</measure>
    <time_frame>Once, at least 5 years post ALL diagnosis and 2 years off treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family and parental stress as reported by primary caregiver.</measure>
    <time_frame>Once, at least 5 years post ALL diagnosis and 2 years off treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Associations between genetic polymorphisms in key enzyme pathways and higher order brain development in long-term survivors of pediatric ALL.</measure>
    <time_frame>Once, at least 5 years post ALL diagnosis and 2 years off treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Associations between fatigue and neurocognitive performance and between sleep problems and neurocognitive performance.</measure>
    <time_frame>Once, at least 5 years post ALL diagnosis and 2 years off treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">270</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurocognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Survivors of pediatric leukemia treated on Total Therapy Protocol XV (TOTXV) at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital (SJCRH), who are ≥ 8 years of age and ≥ 5 years from diagnosis.
Intervention:  Neurocognitive and behavioral evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurocognitive  and behavioral evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>The primary neurocognitive outcome will be performance on measures of cognitive flexibility and cognitive fluency. Functional behavior will be evaluated via the child or adult version of the Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function, using parent respondent for each version. The presence of ADHD and common comorbid conditions (i.e. depression, anxiety) will be determined with structured diagnostic interviews. Quality of life will be re-assessed with the PedQL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neurocognitive  and behavioral evaluation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Children originally enrolled and treated on the SJCRH TOTXV protocol. The study has
        reviewed  TOTXV patient database and has identified 343 patients (189 males and 154
        females) who will meet the inclusion criteria (assuming no additional deaths or relapse).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled on SJCRH TOTXV ALL protocol

          -  ≥ 5 years post diagnosis of ALL

          -  ≥ 8.0 years of age at time of follow-up evaluation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of cranial or total-body radiation therapy

          -  History of bone marrow transplant

          -  History of relapse

          -  History of head injury, neurological condition unrelated to ALL treatment, or
             diagnosis of a genetic disorder associated with neurocognitive impairment (e.g. Down
             Syndrome)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin Krull, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kevin Krull, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>info@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kevin Krull, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
      <email>info@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 21, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 13, 2009</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurocognitive function</keyword>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <keyword>brain imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>genetic polymorphisms</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychopathology and neurocognitive Impairment in Leukemia Survivors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
