<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="126">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00602667</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SJYC07</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00602667</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk-Adapted Therapy for Young Children With Embryonal Brain Tumors, Choroid Plexus Carcinoma, High Grade Glioma or Ependymoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Risk-Adapted Therapy for Young Children With Embryonal Brain Tumors, Choroid Plexus Carcinoma, High Grade Glioma or Ependymoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: In this study a combination of anti-cancer drugs (chemotherapy) is used to treat
      brain tumors in young children. Using chemotherapy gives the brain more time to develop
      before radiation is given. The chemotherapy in this study includes the drug methotrexate.
      This drug was an important part of the two clinical trials which resulted in the best
      survival results for children less than 3 years of age with medulloblastoma. Most patients
      treated on this trial will also receive radiation which is carefully targeted to the area of
      the tumor. This type of radiation (focal conformal or proton beam radiotherapy) may result
      in fewer problems with thinking and learning than radiation to the whole brain and spinal
      cord.

      PURPOSE: This clinical trial is studying how well giving combination chemotherapy together
      with radiation therapy works in treating young patients with newly diagnosed central nervous
      system tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To identify patterns of tumor gene expression that are associated with progression-free
           survival among young pediatric patients with newly diagnosed medulloblastoma treated
           with risk-adapted therapy.

        -  To estimate the event-free survival distribution of young medulloblastoma patients
           treated with risk-adapted therapy.

      Secondary

        -  To perform high-resolution genome-wide analyses of chromosomal abnormalities and gene
           expression patterns, and evaluate the relationship of these to other
           clinicopathological variables.

        -  To evaluate specific tumor types for molecular abnormalities with suspected prognostic
           or therapeutic significance.

        -  To evaluate the feasibility of collecting frozen and fixed tumor samples for analysis
           using high-resolution molecular biology tools.

        -  To estimate the event-free and overall survival of patients treated with the proposed
           risk-adapted therapy regimen, and compare these survival rates to historical controls.

        -  To estimate the rates of local and distant disease progression in patients treated with
           focal radiotherapy to the post-operative tumor bed using a 5 mm clinical target volume
           margin.

        -  To estimate the objective response rate (sustained for 8 weeks) to induction
           chemotherapy including high-dose intravenous methotrexate for patients with residual or
           metastatic disease.

        -  To evaluate the feasibility and toxicity of administering low-dose intravenous
           vinblastine in conjunction with induction chemotherapy to patients with metastatic
           disease.

        -  To evaluate the feasibility and toxicity of administering consolidation therapy
           including cyclophosphamide and pharmacokinetically targeted topotecan to patients with
           metastatic disease, and to estimate the sustained (for 8 weeks) objective response rate
           (complete response and partial response) to such therapy in patients with measurable
           residual disease after induction.

        -  To evaluate the feasibility and toxicity of administering oral maintenance therapy in
           young children.

        -  To use quantitative magnetic resonance (MR) measures (volumetric, diffusion, and
           perfusion) of young brain tumor patients receiving chemotherapy including high-dose
           intravenous methotrexate to assess impact of treatment on developing brain.

        -  To estimate the event free survival of average risk (M0 with gross total resection)
           medulloblastoma patients who were ≥3-&lt;5 years of age at the time of diagnosis and
           treated on the intermediate risk arm of the study.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter study. Patients are stratified according to disease risk
      (low-risk vs intermediate-risk vs high-risk).  Therapy consists of risk adapted induction,
      consolidation and maintenance chemotherapy.  Focal irradiation is given to intermediate risk
      patients who have reached at least 12 months of age upon completion of induction.
      Intermediate risk patients who have not will receive low risk chemotherapy to delay RT until
      the age of 12 months.

      Patients may consent to provide tumor tissue and blood samples for biological studies. Tumor
      tissues are analyzed for the activation of the wnt signaling pathway (β-catenin), activation
      of the shh signaling pathway (Gli-1/SFRP1), and ERBB2; validation of novel patterns of gene
      expression via immunohistochemical (IHC) analysis; loss of chromosomes 6, 8p, 9q22,
      isochromosome 17q; amplification of MYCC, MYCN, and MYCL; validation of genetic
      abnormalities via interphase fluorescence in situ hybridization (iFISH); construction of
      gene expression profiles via microarray analysis; single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)
      analysis for DNA purity and integrity using UV spectrophotometry and agarose gel
      electrophoresis; amplification of DNA via PCR and a combination of previously published and
      'in-house' generated primers; potential oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes via DNA
      sequence analysis; expression of a number of cell signal proteins implicated in the biology
      of medulloblastoma via western blot; expression of additional proteins encoded by genes
      associated through SNP and gene expression array analysis with clinical disease behavior;
      and differential expression pattern of genes detected using microarray analysis via RT-PCR.
      DNA extraction and construction of tissue microarrays (TMAs) from tumor tissue will also be
      used for future IHC and FISH analysis. Blood samples are analyzed for constitutional DNA
      from patients whose tumors contain gene mutations via sequence analysis of constitutional
      DNA; cyclophosphamide and its metabolites via liquid chromatography mass spectroscopy
      method; topotecan lactone via isocratic high-performance liquid chromatography assay with
      fluorescence detection; and alpha-1-acid glycoprotein (AAGP) concentrations via
      immunoturbidimetric assay.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed every 6 months for 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify patterns of tumor gene expression that are associated with progression-free survival among patients with medulloblastoma younger than three years of age at diagnosis treated with risk-adapted therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate the event free survival distribution of medulloblastoma patients younger than three years of age at diagnosis treated with risk-adapted therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Risk Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with GTR/M0 medulloblastoma, nodular desmoplastic or high grade glioma histology will receive induction chemotherapy and low-risk therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-Risk Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with CNS metastatic disease will receive induction chemotherapy and high-risk therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intermediate-Risk Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with M0 medulloblastoma or nodular desmoplastic histology with less than a GTR, other histologic diagnoses with no metastatic disease, will receive induction chemotherapy and intermediate-risk therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Induction Chemotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive 4 identical cycles of induction chemotherapy including highdose (5 g/m2 or 2.5g/m2 for patients less than or equal to 31 days of age at enrollment) intravenous methotrexate and standard dose vincristine, cisplatin, and cyclophosphamide.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Risk Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-Risk Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intermediate-Risk Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MTX (methotrexate)</other_name>
    <other_name>Oncovin(R) (vincristine)</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ(R) (cisplatin)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytoxan(R) (cyclophosphamide)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-Risk Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction will be followed by further conventional chemotherapy with carboplatin, cyclophosphamide, and etoposide. After consolidation, patients will receive 6 cycles of oral maintenance chemotherapy with cyclophosphamide, topotecan, and depending on the diagnosis, either erlotinib or etoposide (VP-16).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Risk Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytoxan(R) (cyclophosphamide)</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin(R) (carboplatin)</other_name>
    <other_name>Vepesid(R), VP-16 (etoposide)</other_name>
    <other_name>Hycamptin(R) (topotecan)</other_name>
    <other_name>Tarceva(TM) (erlotinib)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-Risk Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>High risk patients will also receive vinblastine with each course of induction chemotherapy. Induction will be followed by either chemotherapy with targeted intravenous topotecan and cyclophosphamide or optional craniospinal irradiation (CSI). CSI will be offered only to patients who reach 3 years of age by the end of induction only. After consolidation, all patients will receive 6 cycles of oral maintenance chemotherapy with cyclophosphamide, topotecan, and depending on the diagnosis, either erlotinib or etoposide (VP-16).</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-Risk Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velban(R) (vinblastine)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytoxan(R) (cyclophosphamide)</other_name>
    <other_name>Hycamptin(R) (topotecan)</other_name>
    <other_name>Tarceva(TM) (erlotinib)</other_name>
    <other_name>Vepesid(R), VP-16 (etoposide)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intermediate-Risk Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction will be followed by consolidation focal radiotherapy (RT) to the tumor bed. Patients less than 12 months old upon completion of induction will receive low risk chemotherapy to delay RT until the age of 12 months. After consolidation, patients will receive 6 cycles of oral maintenance chemotherapy with cyclophosphamide, topotecan, and depending on the diagnosis, either erlotinib or etoposide (VP-16).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intermediate-Risk Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytoxan(R) (cyclophosphamide)</other_name>
    <other_name>Hycamptin(R) (topotecan)</other_name>
    <other_name>Tarceva(TM) (erlotinib)</other_name>
    <other_name>Vepesid(R), VP-16 (etoposide)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Histologically confirmed newly diagnosed CNS tumors of any of the following :

          -  Medulloblastoma (all histologic subtypes, including medullomyoblastoma and melanotic
             medulloblastoma)

          -  Supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET) (including CNS neuroblastoma or
             ganglioneuroblastoma, medulloepithelioma, and ependymoblastoma)

          -  Pineoblastoma

          -  Atypical teratoid rhabdoid tumor (ATRT)

          -  Choroid plexus carcinoma

          -  High grade glioma (including anaplastic astrocytoma, anaplastic oligodendroglioma,
             anaplastic ganglioglioma, pleomorphic xanthoastrocytoma with anaplastic features,
             high-grade astroblastoma , anaplastic pilocytic astrocytoma, malignant glioneuronal
             tumor, glioblastoma multiforme), or gliosarcoma,

          -  Ependymoma (including all ependymoma histological variants)

          -  Age &lt; 3 years at time of diagnosis for all histological diagnosis. Medulloblastoma
             patients ≥ 3 and &lt; 5years old at diagnosis who have non-metastatic disease with no
             more than 1cm2 of residual tumor are also eligible.

               -  Meets criteria for 1 of the following risk groups:

          -  Low-risk group:

               -  Histologically confirmed nodular desmoplastic medulloblastoma, including
                  medulloblastoma with extensive nodularity

                    -  Focal areas of anaplasia or other atypical features suggesting more
                       aggressive phenotype in a tumor otherwise considered nodular desmoplastic
                       should be treated on the intermediate-risk group, with final risk
                       stratification at the discretion of principal investigator and study
                       pathologist

               -  No evidence of CNS metastasis 7 to 28 days after surgery by MRI and cytologic
                  examination of lumbar cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)

                    -  Ventricular CSF from a shunt or Ommaya reservoir may be used to rule out M1
                       disease when lumbar puncture is medically contraindicated

                    -  Intermediate-risk group assignment when there is no other evidence of
                       metastasis and CSF sampling is not possible

               -  Gross total resection, defined as residual tumor or imaging abnormality (not
                  definitive for residual tumor) with a size of &lt; 1 cm2 confirmed on postoperative
                  CT scan or MRI

               -  Brain stem invasion by the tumor in the absence of imaging evidence of residual
                  tumor (tumor size &lt; 1 cm2) and otherwise meets criteria for the low-risk group,
                  the patient will be classified as low-risk

               -  Desmoplastic medulloblastoma patients who are ≥3 -&lt;5 years of age will NOT be
                  eligible for the low risk arm of the protocol.

          -  Intermediate-risk group:

               -  Histologically confirmed nodular desmoplastic medulloblastoma with less than
                  gross total resection and no evidence of metastasis

               -  Any eligible histologic diagnosis other than desmoplastic medulloblastoma with
                  no evidence of CNS metastasis

               -  Medulloblastoma patients who are ≥3 and &lt; 5 yrs of age irrespective of histology
                  and with no evidence of CNS metastasis

          -  High-risk group:

               -  Any eligible histologic diagnosis with evidence of CNS metastasis

               -  Patients with extraneural metastasis are eligible for treatment on the high-risk
                  group

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Lansky performance status ≥ 30 (except for posterior fossa syndrome)

          -  WBC &gt; 2,000/mm3

          -  Platelets &gt; 50,000/mm3 (without support)

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 8 g/dL (with or without support)

          -  ANC &gt; 500/mm3

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 3 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  ALT &lt; 5 times ULN

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 3 times ULN

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  No more than 31 days since prior definitive surgery

          -  No prior radiotherapy or chemotherapy other than corticosteroid therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amar Gajjar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amar Gajjar, MD</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>info@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lucile Packard Children's Hospital at Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul G. Fisher, MD, MHS</last_name>
      <phone>650-497-8953</phone>
      <email>pfisher@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rady Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92123</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Crawford, MD, MS</last_name>
      <phone>858-576-1700</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota - St. Paul</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Paul</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne E. Bendel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>651-220-6732</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amar Gajjar, MD</last_name>
      <phone>901-495-5007</phone>
      <email>amar.gajjar@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel C. Bowers, MD</last_name>
      <phone>214-456-6139</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brisbane</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4029</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tim Hassall, MBBS, FRACP</last_name>
      <phone>61-7-3636-9115</phone>
      <email>tim_hassall@health.qld.gov.au</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 14, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 10, 2008</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>untreated childhood medulloblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated childhood supratentorial primitive neuroectodermal tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>untreated childhood pineoblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood choroid plexus tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>childhood high grade glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>newly diagnosed childhood ependymoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ependymoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vinblastine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Topotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erlotinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
