<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="331">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01269424</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CASE6307</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2011-02566</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>8274</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01269424</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>O6-Benzylguanine and Temozolomide in Combination With Genetically Modified Peripheral Blood Stem Cells in Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma Multiforme</brief_title>
  <official_title>O6-Benzylguanine (BG) and Temozolomide (TMZ) Therapy of Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM) With Infusion of Autologous P140KMGMT+ Hematopoietic Progenitors to Protect Hematopoiesis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanton Gerson MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as temozolomide, work in different ways to stop
      the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.
      O6-benzylguanine may help temozolomide work better by making tumor cells more sensitive to
      the drug. Giving genetically modified peripheral blood stem cells during or after treatment
      may prevent side effects caused by chemotherapy.

      PURPOSE: This clinical trial studies O6-benzylguanine and temozolomide in combination with
      genetically modified peripheral blood stem cells in treating patients with newly diagnosed
      glioblastoma multiforme.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To evaluate the feasibility of introducing and expressing P140K MGMT cDNA from a
           lentiviral-based provirus in autologous hematopoietic stem cells harvested from GBM
           patients.

        -  To assess the safety associated with infusion of autologous hematopoietic stem cells
           transduced ex vivo with a lentiviral vector expressing P140K MGMT in patients with GBM.

      Secondary

        -  To determine whether any patients who receive P140K MGMT-transduced CD34 cells tolerate
           O6-benzylguanine (BG) and dose-escalated temozolomide (TMZ) without myelosuppression.

        -  To evaluate the ability to detect P140K-transduced BG and TMZ-resistant hematopoietic
           cells from the bone marrow and peripheral blood in patients infused with
           P140K-transduced CD34 progenitors.

        -  To evaluate the feasibility of in vivo enrichment of P140K-expressing hematopoietic
           cells by repeated treatments of BG and TMZ at doses that appear therapeutic for GBM.

        -  To evaluate tumor response, progression-free survival, and overall survival.

      OUTLINE: Patients are assigned to 1 of 3 treatment cohorts.

        -  Cohort 1 (LV P140K MGMT gene transfer after concurrent chemoradiotherapy): Patients
           receive concurrent radiotherapy 5 days a week and oral temozolomide (TMZ) daily for 6
           weeks. Patients then undergo cell reinfusion of autologous P140K MGMT-transduced
           hematopoietic cells over 5-10 minutes at week 7. Beginning 4 weeks later, patients
           receive O6-benzylguanine (BG) IV over 1 hour on days 1-28 and oral TMZ on days 1-5.
           Treatment with BG and TMZ repeats every 28 days for up to 6 courses in the absence of
           disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

        -  Cohort 2 (LV P140K MGMT gene transfer prior to concurrent chemoradiotherapy): Patients
           receive BG IV over 1 hour and a single dose of oral TMZ 2-3 days prior to reinfusion of
           autologous P140K MGMT-transduced hematopoietic cells over 5-10 minutes on day 0.
           Patients then undergo radiotherapy 5 days a week and receive concurrent BG daily and
           TMZ 5 days a week beginning on days 28 and 56. Beginning on day 56, treatment with BG
           and TMZ repeats every 28 days for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression
           or unacceptable toxicity.

        -  Cohort 3 (intra-patient dose escalation of TMZ in patients with evidence of
           P140K-marked cells [using the preferred treatment schema determined from Cohorts 1 and
           2 above]): After completion of radiotherapy, patients receive BG and TMZ and undergo
           cell infusion as in cohort 1 (cohort 3a) or 2 (cohort 3b). TMZ dose may be increased,
           as tolerated, during the 6 courses after radiotherapy.

      Blood samples are collected periodically for replication-competent lentivirus detection and
      other laboratory biomarker studies.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed up every 2 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of infusing autologous P140K MGMT-transduced hematopoietic progenitors into patients with GBM</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients will be assessed for clinical symptoms and side-effects from time of treatment until protocol is stopped due to toxicity, progression, patient choice, or patient election to enroll on new therapeutic option.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety (grade IV toxicity)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>CTCAE v 4.0 will be used as the criteria for evaluating infusion-related events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful transduction rate</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quantitate P140K transduced hematopoietic cells from the bone marrow and peripheral blood in patients infused with P140K transduced CD34 progenitors</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the in vivo enrichment of P140K expressing hematopoietic cells by repeated treatments of BG and TMZ</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the in vivo enrichment of P140K expressing hematopoietic cells by repeated treatments of BG and TMZ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival defined as the time interval between the date of initial histological diagnosis and the date of disease progression or death, whichever comes first</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with radiological progression</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>New tumor or increased tumor size on T1WI + Gd of &gt; 25% as measured by the sum of two perpendicular diameters compared to the smallest measurements ever recorded for the same lesion by the same technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>From the date of enrollment to death, last contact or last tumor assessment before further anti-tumor therapy, assessed up to 5 years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>LV gene transfer after concurrent chemo-radiotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>LV gene transfer prior to concurrent chemo-radiotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intra patient dose escalation of TMZ in patients with evidence of P140K marked cells</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MGMTP140K-encoding retroviral vector</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>O6-benzylguanine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>in vitro-treated peripheral blood stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically confirmed, newly diagnosed, supratentorial GBM who have
             undergone gross total tumor resections or near gross total resection (resection of
             &gt;90% of enhancing tumor demonstrated by MRI) are eligible up to their third
             post-operative week. Patients with infratentorial disease, multifocal or
             leptomeningeal disease will be excluded. In general, patients will not have &gt; 1 cm
             residual measurable or evaluable disease after surgical tumor resection.

          -  Patients aged 18-70. Patients &gt;70 will be excluded due to difficulties in
             mobilization and collection of adequate numbers of peripheral progenitors.

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2 or Karnofsky ≥ 60.

          -  Patients must have received no myelosuppressive chemotherapy prior to the diagnosis
             of GBM.

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          -  Adequate hematologic (ANC ≥ 1500/mm3, platelets ≥ 100,000/mm3, Hgb ≥ 9.5 , hepatic
             (Bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dl, AST and ALT less than or equal to 3 times upper limit of
             normal, prothrombin time &lt;1.2 times normal), and renal (Serum creatinine ≤ 2.0 mg/dl
             or Creatinine Clearance ≥ 60mL/min/1.73 m2 for subjects with serum creatinine levels
             above institutional normal) . These tests will be repeated within 2 weeks of
             treatment with BG and TMZ, and must meet the same criteria.

          -  EKG without evidence of acute cardiac disease.

          -  Post-operative steroids are tapered to ≤ 24 mg decadron/d

          -  Patients of child-bearing potential must be using single barrier contraception

          -  Willingness and ability to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Medical condition associated with immunosuppression, active infection or medical
             illness which may jeopardize patient safety.

          -  HIV seropositivity. This exclusion is included for two reasons. First, there is
             evidence of decreased marrow reserve in HIV+ patients and antiviral treatment is
             associated with myelosuppression. Thus, drug treatment designed to be
             myelosuppressive may be more toxic in this patient population. Second, extensive
             laboratory culturing of the bone marrow and peripheral blood progenitor cells is
             required. No preclinical samples which are HIV+ have been evaluated with the gene
             transfer modality proposed and thus the feasibility and safety of gene transfer and
             selection in HIV+ samples cannot yet be advocated. Such studies are planned so as to
             not preclude HIV+ patients in later studies.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women. There is data to indicate that TMZ is teratogenic and
             carcinogenic. Thus, its use in pregnant women would confer unnecessary risk to the
             fetus.

          -  Patients with symptomatic pulmonary disease and other severe co-morbid conditions

          -  Prior chemotherapy (including gliadel wafers) or hematopoietic cell transplantation.

          -  Inability to undergo repeated MRI evaluation.

          -  Prior diagnosis of malignant disease within a three year period with the exception of
             surgically cured basal cell carcinoma or carcinoma in situ of the cervix

          -  Mental incapacity or psychiatric illness preventing informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew E. Sloan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Medical Center, University Hospitals Seidman Cancer Center, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Medical Center, University Hospitals Seidman Cancer Center, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106-5047</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew E. Sloan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-5432</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/CWRU-CASE-6307</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 6, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 31, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stanton Gerson MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adult giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>O(6)-benzylguanine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
