<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="307">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00992602</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6954</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2009-01309</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00992602</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High-dose Methotrexate and Liposomal Cytarabine in Treating Patients With CNS Metastases From Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of the Combination of High-dose Methotrexate and Intrathecal Liposomal Cytarabine in Patients With Leptomeningeal Metastases With or Without Parenchymal Brain Involvement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial is studying how well giving high-dose methotrexate together with
      liposomal cytarabine works in treating patients with central nervous system (CNS) metastases
      from metastatic breast cancer. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as methotrexate and
      liposomal cytarabine, work in different ways to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by
      killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Giving high-dose systemic methotrexate
      with intra-cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) liposomal cytarabine may kill more tumor cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To show that treatment with high-dose methotrexate (HD-MTX) in combination with
      intrathecal (IT) liposomal cytarabine will result in median progression-free survival (PFS)
      greater than 7 weeks for patients with breast cancer and leptomeningeal metastases with or
      without parenchymal brain involvement.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the overall survival of patients with CNS metastatic breast cancer treated
      with the combination of intravenous (IV) HD-MTX and IT liposomal cytarabine.

      II. To describe the safety of the combination therapy, in terms of toxicity, adverse events,
      and the need for dose reductions or schedule modification.

      III. To estimate the best overall response rate achieved during treatment with IV HD-MTX and
      IT liposomal cytarabine. Radiographic response will be measured by the Macdonald Criteria
      using imaging (magnetic resonance imaging [MRI]), and cytologic response will be measured by
      CSF cytology.

      IV. To determine the number of treatment cycles needed to achieve radiographic and cytologic
      response. Time to progression and duration of the response will also be measured.

      V. To describe response duration in patients who achieve at least partial radiographic
      response and cytologic clearance.

      VI. To define time to clinical progression as measured by Karnofsky performance status (KPS)
      and neurological exam.

      VII. To describe functional status and quality of life of patients, through clinical
      evaluations of neurological status and patient-reported quality of life (QOL) measured by
      the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy (FACIT) brain and/or CNS
      questionnaires.

      VIII. To correlate response rates with the extent of patient's systemic disease and tumor
      receptor status (estrogen receptor [ER], progesterone receptor [PR], human epidermal growth
      factor receptor 2 [Her2]).

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To correlate response rates with the extent of patient's systemic disease and tumor
      receptor status (ER, PR, Her2/neu).

      OUTLINE:

      INDUCTION THERAPY (weeks 1-6): Patients receive high-dose methotrexate IV over 4 hours on
      days 1, 15, and 29 and liposomal cytarabine IT or lumbar puncture (LP) over 5 minutes on
      days 8, 22, and 36.

      CONSOLIDATION THERAPY (weeks 7-11): Patients achieving complete response (CR), partial
      response (PR), or stable disease (SD) then receive high-dose methotrexate IV over 4 hours on
      days 43 and 57. Patients also receive liposomal cytarabine IT or LP over 5 minutes on days
      50 and 64.

      MAINTENANCE THERAPY (weeks 13-37): Patients achieving CR, PR, or SD receive high-dose
      methotrexate IV over 4 hours once monthly and beginning in week 15, patients receive
      liposomal cytarabine IT or LP over 5 minutes once monthly. Treatment repeats once monthly
      for 5-6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 30 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Described using Kaplan-Meier survival curves, and confidence intervals for median PFS will be computed. A 95% confidence interval lower bound greater than 7 weeks would be strong evidence for efficacy of the combined treatment regimen. However, an observed median PFS of 12 weeks or greater would also show promise for the combined therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP) Common Toxicity Criteria grade 3+ neurological and systemic toxicity that persists following dose reductions or schedule modifications</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Described using Kaplan-Meier survival curves. Measured as time from start of therapy until death, censored on the last date the patient was known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Described using Kaplan-Meier survival curves. Radiographic response will be measured by the RECIST criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cytologic response as measured by CSF cytology (positive or negative for malignant cells)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to week 37</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FACT-Brain (Br) total score and subscales (physical well-being, social/family well-being, emotional well-being, functional well-being, symptom index) using standard scoring</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed every 4 weeks until withdrawal from study</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Central Nervous System Metastases</condition>
  <condition>Leptomeningeal Metastases</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Tumors Metastatic to Brain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION THERAPY (weeks 1-6): Patients receive high-dose methotrexate IV over 4 hours on days 1, 15, and 29 and liposomal cytarabine IT or LP over 5 minutes on days 8, 22, and 36.
CONSOLIDATION THERAPY (weeks 7-11): Patients achieving CR, PR, or SD then receive high-dose methotrexate IV over 4 hours on days 43 and 57. Patients also receive liposomal cytarabine IT or LP over 5 minutes on days 50 and 64.
MAINTENANCE THERAPY (weeks 13-37): Patients achieving CR, PR, or SD receive high-dose methotrexate IV over 4 hours once monthly and beginning in week 15, patients receive liposomal cytarabine IT or LP over 5 minutes once monthly. Treatment repeats once monthly for 5-6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>amethopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Folex</other_name>
    <other_name>methylaminopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Mexate</other_name>
    <other_name>MTX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>liposomal cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cytarabine liposome</other_name>
    <other_name>DepoCyt</other_name>
    <other_name>DepoCyte</other_name>
    <other_name>DepoFoam-encapsulated cytarabine</other_name>
    <other_name>DTC 101</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>questionnaire administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are not pregnant (contraception must be used throughout the study)

          -  Diagnosis of breast cancer with metastases to CNS (regardless of receptor status),
             leptomeningeal disease must be present with/without parenchymal brain involvement

          -  Ability to provide informed consent

          -  No prior treatment with whole brain radiotherapy (WBRT)

          -  If patient received stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS) prior to enrollment it must be
             well documented which lesions were treated and index lesions (untreated) for follow
             up must be identified, no treatment with SRS will be permitted while on the study

          -  CNS disease must be documented by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and cerebrospinal
             fluid (CSF) cytology

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status &gt; 60

          -  White blood cells (WBC) &gt; 3.0 K

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1.5 K

          -  Platelets (PLT) &gt; 100 K

          -  Hematocrit (HCT) &gt; 30%

          -  Acceptable renal function (glomerular filtration rate [GFR] &gt;= 60 mL/min)

          -  Acceptable liver function (see exclusion criteria)

          -  Therapy for systemic disease allowing for addition of systemic HD-MTX and IT Depocyt
             (in general patients receiving trastuzumab or lapatinib at the time of enrollment
             will be allowed to continue); bisphosphonates (i.e., zoledronic acid) and denosumab
             will be allowed; other non-CNS active chemotherapies might be allowed if no known
             interactions with study drugs are present; this will be reviewed on case-by-case
             basis

          -  Mini-mental status examination score of 24 or above

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serum bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x the upper limit of reference range (ULRR)

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 x ULRR or creatinine clearance =&lt; 60 mL/minute (calculated by
             Cockcroft-Gault formula)

          -  Potassium, &lt; 3.7 mmol/L despite supplementation; serum calcium (ionized or adjusted
             for albumin,) or magnesium out of normal range despite supplementation

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 2.5 x ULRR

          -  Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) &gt; 2.5 x ULRR or &gt; 5x ULRR if judged by the investigator to
             be related to liver metastases

          -  Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic disease or any concurrent condition which
             in the Investigator's opinion makes it undesirable for the patient to participate in
             the trial or which would jeopardize compliance with the protocol

          -  Patients with known pleural effusion or ascites

          -  Prior treatment with whole brain radiotherapy, prior treatment with stereotactic
             radiosurgery (SRS) is allowed under conditions provided in the inclusion criteria

          -  Previous allergic or adverse reaction to methotrexate or cytarabine

          -  Prior treatment with systemic HD-MTX or IT liposomal cytarabine

          -  Prior IT therapy of any kind

          -  Women who are currently pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Previous or current malignancies of other histologies within the last 5 years, with
             the exception of cervical carcinoma in situ and adequately treated basal cell or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

          -  Receipt of any investigational agents within 30 days prior to commencing study
             treatment

          -  Last dose of prior chemotherapy discontinued less than 4 weeks before the start of
             study therapy; patients who had no toxicities with prior chemotherapy can start study
             treatment earlier than 4 weeks

          -  Last radiation therapy to the brain in the form of SRS within the last 2 weeks before
             the start of study therapy

          -  Any unresolved toxicity greater than Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) grade 1 from
             previous anti-cancer therapy

          -  Previous enrollment in the present study

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks prior to starting therapy, Ommaya reservoir can be used
             for introduction of chemotherapy within 48-72 hours after placement
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maciej Mrugala</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rhode Island Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Suriya Jeyapalan</last_name>
      <phone>401-444-1488</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Suriya Jeyapalan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maciej M. Mrugala</last_name>
      <phone>206-598-9487</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maciej M. Mrugala</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 7, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 7, 2009</firstreceived_date>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Meningeal Carcinomatosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
