<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="83">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01849146</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2013-00858</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00858</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ABTC 1202</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ABTC-1202</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA137443</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01849146</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>WEE1 Inhibitor MK-1775, Radiation Therapy, and Temozolomide in Treating Patients With Newly Diagnosed or Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study of MK-1775 With Radiation and Temozolomide in Patients With Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma and Evaluation of Intratumoral Drug Distribution in Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 when
      given together with radiation therapy and temozolomide in treating patients with newly
      diagnosed or recurrent glioblastoma multiforme. WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 may stop the growth
      of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Radiation therapy
      uses high energy x rays to kill tumor cells. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as
      temozolomide, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing
      the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Giving WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 together with
      radiation therapy and temozolomide may be an effective treatment for glioblastoma
      multiforme.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximum tolerated doses (MTD) of MK-1775 (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775) in
      combination with the current standard of care (radiotherapy/temozolomide for concomitant
      therapy and temozolomide for adjuvant therapy) for treating patients with newly diagnosed
      glioblastoma.

      II. To define the MTD of MK-1775 in combination with 6 weeks of daily (Monday-Friday [M-F])
      radiotherapy (RT) and concomitant temozolomide (TMZ) administered at 75 mg/m^2/day in
      patients with newly diagnosed glioblastoma. (Arm 1) III. To define the MTD of MK-1775 in
      combination with adjuvant TMZ administered at 150 mg/m^2/day-200 mg/m^2/day for 5 days every
      28 days in patients with glioblastoma after concurrent RT/TMZ. (Arm 2)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To characterize the safety profile of MK-1775 in combination with RT and concomitant TMZ
      (Arm 1) and MK-1775 with adjuvant TMZ (Arm 2) in patients with newly diagnosed glioblastoma.

      II. To assess the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of MK-1775 in combination with upfront
      radiation/TMZ and adjuvant TMZ in patients with newly diagnosed glioblastoma.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the intratumoral concentration of MK-1775 achieved in patients treated with
      the putative MTD.

      II. To characterize the time course of MK-1775 in extracellular fluid within brain tumors
      following a single oral dose of drug by microdialysis.

      III. To characterize O6-methylguanine deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)-methyltransferase (MGMT)
      methylation and tumor protein p53 (P53) pathway status, also P-glycoprotein (P-gp) and wee1
      expression levels in patients with newly diagnosed glioblastoma treated with standard
      therapy in combination with MK-1775.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775. Patients are assigned to
      1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM I:

      INITIATION COURSE: Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 orally (PO) on days 1, 3, and 5
      or 1-5 weekly and temozolomide PO once daily (QD) for 6 weeks. Patients also undergo
      concurrent radiation therapy 5 days per week for 6 weeks.

      MAINTENANCE COURSES: Beginning in week 10, patients receive temozolomide PO QD on days 1-5.
      Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 PO QD on days 1, 3, and 5 or 1-5, and
      temozolomide PO QD on days 1-5. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 6 courses in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 2 months for 2 years and
      then every 6 months thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 with 6 weeks of RT and temozolomide, graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v4.0 (Arm I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Severity and frequency of toxicity will be tabulated by the tested dose or doses using descriptive statistics. The proportion of subjects who experience grade 3 or above toxicities will be estimated, along with 95% confidence intervals by each type of toxicity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 with adjuvant temozolomide, graded according to the NCI CTCAE v4.0 (Arm II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Severity and frequency of toxicity will be tabulated by the tested dose or doses using descriptive statistics. The proportion of subjects who experience grade 3 or above toxicities will be estimated, along with 95% confidence intervals by each type of toxicity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicities, graded according to the NCI CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Severity and frequency of toxicity will be tabulated by the tested dose or doses using descriptive statistics. The proportion of subjects who experience grade 3 or above toxicities will be estimated, along with 95% confidence intervals by each type of toxicity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>The time from the date of initial diagnosis to the date of death, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Calculated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>The time from the date of initial diagnosis to the date progressive disease was defined and also patient was alive, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Calculated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of MK-1775 in combination with radiation and temozolomide and adjuvant TMZ</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8 and 24 hours of weeks 1 and 4 of course 1 (Arm I) and at baseline, 0.5, 1, 2. 4, 6, 8, and 24 hours of course 1 (Arm II)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Individual subject plasma concentration-time curves will be analyzed by non-compartmental methods using routines supplied in the WinNonlin Professional Version 5.0 software package (Pharsight Corp., Cary, NC). The geometric mean ± standard deviation of the estimated values of the pharmacokinetic parameter for groups of subjects evaluated at MTD dose level will be calculated. Parametric statistical tests (i.e., single factor ANOVA, Student's t-test) of pharmacokinetic variables will be performed after logarithmic transformation of the data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Giant Cell Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Gliosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Brain Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide, radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INITIATION COURSE: Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 PO on days 1, 3, and 5 or 1-5 weekly and temozolomide PO QD for 6 weeks. Patients also undergo concurrent radiation therapy 5 days per week for 6 weeks.
MAINTENANCE COURSES: Beginning in week 10, patients receive temozolomide PO QD on days 1-5. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775 PO QD on days 1, 3, and 5 or 1-5, and temozolomide PO QD on days 1-5. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide, radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MK-1775</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide, radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>irradiation</other_name>
    <other_name>radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>therapy, radiation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide, radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SCH 52365</other_name>
    <other_name>Temodal</other_name>
    <other_name>Temodar</other_name>
    <other_name>TMZ</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide, radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide, radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (WEE1 inhibitor MK-1775, temozolomide)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have a tumor tissue form indicating availability of archived tissue
             from initial resection at diagnosis of glioblastoma completed and signed by a
             pathologist

          -  Patients must have a Karnofsky performance status &gt;= 60% (i.e. the patient must be
             able to care for himself/herself with occasional help from others)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 3 × institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 60
             ml/min/1.73m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of
             normal

          -  Patients must be able to provide written informed consent

          -  Patients must have magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) within 21 days of starting
             treatment

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test prior to
             study entry; women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use two birth
             control methods (either two barrier methods or a barrier method plus a hormonal
             method) or abstinence prior to study entry and for the duration of study
             participation; should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Patients must have no concurrent malignancy except curatively treated basal or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or carcinoma in situ of the cervix, breast, or
             bladder; patients with prior malignancies must be disease-free for &gt;= five years

          -  Patients must be maintained on a stable corticosteroid regimen (no increase for 5
             days) prior to the start of treatment

          -  Patients must be able to swallow whole capsules

          -  PHASE I PATIENTS:

          -  Must have histologically proven glioblastoma

          -  Must have recovered from the immediate post-operative period

          -  Patients going on Arm 1 or combination dose cohort must not have received prior
             radiation therapy, chemotherapy, immunotherapy or therapy with biologic agent
             (including immunotoxins, immunoconjugates, antisense, peptide receptor antagonists,
             interferons, interleukins, tumor infiltrating lymphocytes [TIL], lymphokine-activated
             killer [LAK] or gene therapy), or hormonal therapy for their brain tumor;
             glucocorticoid therapy is allowed

          -  Patients going on Arm 2 must have received planned treatment with radiation therapy
             and concomitant temozolomide at least 28 days but no more than 49 days prior to
             starting treatment on this study; patients must have received at least 80% of planned
             temozolomide and radiation therapy with no grade 3 or grade 4 toxicity attributed to
             the temozolomide; Arm 2 patients may not have received any other prior chemotherapy,
             immunotherapy or therapy with biologic agent (including immunotoxins,
             immunoconjugates, antisense, peptide receptor antagonists, interferons, interleukins,
             TIL, LAK or gene therapy), or hormonal therapy for their brain tumor; prior Gliadel
             Wafers are allowed; glucocorticoid therapy is allowed

          -  INTRATUMORAL DRUG DISTRIBUTION STUDY PATIENTS:

          -  Patients must have prior histologically proven glioblastoma that is progressive or
             recurrent following radiation therapy +/- chemotherapy

          -  Patients must be undergoing repeat surgery that is clinically indicated as determined
             by their care providers

          -  Patients must have measurable contrast-enhancing progressive or recurrent
             glioblastoma by MRI within 21 days of starting treatment; patient must be able to
             tolerate MRIs

          -  Patients may have an unlimited number of prior therapy regimens

          -  Patients must have recovered from severe toxicity of prior therapy; the following
             intervals from previous treatments are required to be eligible:

               -  12 weeks from the completion of radiation

               -  6 weeks from a nitrosourea chemotherapy

               -  3 weeks from a non-nitrosourea chemotherapy

               -  4 weeks from any investigational (not Food and Drug Administration
                  [FDA]-approved) agents

               -  2 weeks from administration of a non-cytotoxic, FDA-approved agent (e.g.,
                  Tarceva, hydroxychloroquine, bevacizumab, etc.)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving any other investigational agents are ineligible

          -  Patients with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to temozolomide or MK-1775 are ineligible; the
             MK-1775 Investigator Brochure and the temozolomide package insert can be referenced
             for more information

          -  Patients on enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drugs (EIAED) are not eligible for
             treatment on this protocol; patients may be on non-enzyme inducing anti-epileptic
             drugs or not be taking any anti-epileptic drugs; patients previously treated with
             EIAED may be enrolled if they have been off the EIAED for 10 days or more prior to
             the first dose of MK-1775

          -  Patients may not be on drugs known to be moderate or potent inhibitors/inducers of
             cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4), sensitive substrates of CYP3A4, or substrates of CYP3A4
             with narrow therapeutic windows

          -  Patients may not be on anti-coagulants (warfarin, etc.) other than low-molecular
             weight heparin (LMWH)

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to,
             ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina
             pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements, are ineligible

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with MK-1775

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are ineligible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Alexander</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adult Brain Tumor Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21231-1000</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Alexander</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-6313</phone>
      <email>brian_alexander@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brian Alexander</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Alexander</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-5200</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brian Alexander</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 6, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gliosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
