<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="7">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01737671</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0823</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01737671</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Methotrexate Infusion Into the Fourth Ventricle in Children With Malignant Fourth Ventricular Brain Tumors: A Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Methotrexate Infusion Into the Fourth Ventricle in Children With Malignant Fourth Ventricular Brain Tumors: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if methotrexate infused into the fourth
      ventricle of the brain can help to control brain tumors.  The safety of this drug will also
      be studied.

      Methotrexate is designed to block cancer cells from dividing, which may slow or stop their
      growth and spread throughout the body.  This may cause the cancer cells to die.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Catheter Placement Surgery:

      If you are eligible to take part in this study, you will have surgery to place a catheter
      into the ommaya reservoir.  The ommaya reservoir is a catheter system that allows drugs to
      be administered directly to parts of the brain.  In this study, the catheter will be used to
      collect about 1 teaspoon of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF - the fluid surrounding the brain and
      spinal cord) to check the status of the disease and for the infusion of methotrexate
      directly into the 4th ventricle of the brain, which is 1 of the 4 connected fluid-filled
      cavities in the brain.

      If the study doctor thinks it is necessary, based on the location of the tumor, the tumor
      may also be removed while you are already under anesthesia just before the catheter is
      placed.

      Study Drug Administration:

      Each cycle is 4 days long and will consist of 4 daily infusions of methotrexate.  You will
      have at least a 2 week rest period between each cycle.

      Methotrexate will be infused through the ommaya reservoir catheter directly into the 4th
      ventricle of the brain starting 2-4 weeks after the catheter placement surgery.  The
      infusion should last about 3 minutes each time.

      You may also be given leucovorin, a drug used to help prevent or treat the side effects of
      methotrexate, by intravenous (IV) infusion through a catheter or port you have already had
      placed in your arm.  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, this infusion will be given
      after each cycle to help with the possible side effects you may experience from
      methotrexate.  The infusion should last about 5 minutes each time.

      Study Visits:

      Within 72 hours after catheter placement surgery:

        -  Your medical history will be reviewed and any updates to your health will be recorded.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vitals.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will have an MRI scan of the brain and spine to check the status of the disease.

      Ten (10) days after catheter placement surgery:

        -  Your medical history will be reviewed and any updates to your health will be recorded.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vitals.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  CSF (about 1 teaspoon) will be collected for routine tests.

        -  You will have a spinal tap (also called a lumbar puncture).  A lumbar puncture is a
           procedure where fluid surrounding the spinal cord is removed by inserting a needle into
           the lower back. The affected area is numbed with local anesthetic during the procedure.

      Within 1 week before the first dose of methotrexate, blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn
      for routine tests.

      Daily during each methotrexate infusion:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vitals.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will have an Ommaya reservoir tap (a catheter is placed into the Ommaya reservoir
           to give the methotrexate infusion).

        -  CSF (about 1 teaspoon) will be collected for routine tests.

      After Cycle 1 is complete:

        -  Your medical history will be reviewed and any updates to your health will be recorded.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vitals.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  CSF (about 1 teaspoon) will be collected for routine tests.

        -  You will have an MRI scan of the brain to check the status of the disease.  If the
           study doctor thinks it is needed, you will also have an MRI of the spine.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a lumbar puncture.

      After Cycle 2 is complete:

        -  Your medical history will be reviewed and any updates to your health will be recorded.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vitals.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  CSF (about 1 teaspoon) will be collected for routine tests.

        -  If the study doctor think it is necessary, you will have a lumbar puncture.

      After Cycle 3 is complete:

        -  Your medical history will be reviewed and any updates to your health will be recorded.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vitals.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  CSF (about 1 teaspoon) will be collected for routine tests.

        -  You will have a lumbar puncture.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have an MRI scan of the brain and
           spine to check the status of the disease.

      If the study doctor thinks it is in your best interest, you will continue with additional
      cycles of methotrexate therapy.

      Also, if the study doctor thinks it is in your best interest, methotrexate may be given
      together with other chemotherapy after completion of Cycle 3.  If you will be receiving
      other chemotherapy, the study doctor will speak with you in more detail about what drugs you
      will receive and how you will receive them.

      Length of Study:

      You will receive up to 3 cycles of the methotrexate, or as long as the doctor thinks it is
      your best interest.  You will no longer be able to receive the study drug if the disease
      gets worse, if intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study
      directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after you complete the follow-up visits.

      Follow-Up Visits:

      At 3, 6, 9, and 12 months after the last dose of study drug:

        -  Your medical history will be reviewed and any updates to your health will be recorded.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vitals.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  You will have an MRI scan of the brain and spine to check the status of the disease.
           The MRI of the spine may not be performed at months 3 and/or 6, if the study doctor
           thinks it is in your best interest.

      This is an investigational study.  Methotrexate is FDA approved and commercially available
      for infusion directly into brain tumors.  The infusion of methotrexate into the 4th
      ventricle of the brain is investigational.

      Up to 10 patients will be enrolled in this study.  All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurological Deficits After Administration of Methotrexate into the Fourth Ventricle of the Brain</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>New neurological deficit defined as new cranial neuropathy, nystagmus, change in mental status, motor deficit, or cerebellar finding (ataxia, dysmetria, dysdiadochokinesis) that is attributed by treating physicians to intraventricular methotrexate infusions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm of Fourth Ventricle of Brain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methotrexate Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 consecutive cycles of intraventricular methotrexate infusions into implanted fourth ventricle catheter/Ommaya reservoir following surgical catheter placement into fourth ventricle, each cycle is 4 consecutive daily doses of intraventricular methotrexate with minimum 2 weeks between cycles. Leucovorin 5 mg/square meter per dose administered after each cycle of intraventricular methotrexate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ommaya Reservoir</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical catheter placement into the fourth ventricle of the brain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methotrexate Infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>2 mg into fourth ventricle of the brain via the Ommaya Reservoir for 4 days. Each patient will undergo three cycles with at least two weeks between each cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methotrexate Infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leucovorin</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg/square meter per dose administered after each cycle of intraventricular methotrexate.  Two intravenous doses administered in total after each cycle.  The first leucovorin dose administered 24 hours after the last intraventricular methotrexate dose of each cycle and the second leucovorin dose administered 36 hours after the last intraventricular methotrexate dose of each cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methotrexate Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Citrovorum</other_name>
    <other_name>Wellcovorin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients under the age of 22 years with recurrent medulloblastoma (PNET) involving
             the brain and/or spine, or recurrent ependymoma involving the brain and/or spine, or
             recurrent atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor (AT/RT) involving the brain and/or spine.

          2. Patients must have a life expectancy of at least 12 weeks as estimated by the
             treating oncologist and/or neurosurgeon to be considered for enrollment.

          3. Patients must have a Lansky score of 20 or greater &lt;/= 16 years of age and a
             Karnofsky score of 20 or greater &gt; 16 years of age to be eligible for enrollment.

          4. Female patients who are post-menarchal must have a negative pregnancy test to be
             eligible.

          5. Patients may be enrolled in the study if they have an altered neurological status,
             such as somnolence, which is attributed to hydrocephalus and/or mass effect from the
             brain tumor by the treating physicians. However, after tumor resection and placement
             of the catheter into the fourth ventricle, the protocol will only be continued if the
             patient has adequate central nervous system function, defined as: Patient is not
             severely somnolent or comatose

          6. Prior to receiving intraventricular methotrexate, patients must have adequate bone
             marrow function, defined as: Peripheral absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;/= 1000/µL,
             Platelet count = 30,000/µL (transfusion independent), Hemoglobin = 9.0 gm/dL (may
             receive RBC transfusions)

          7. All patients and/or their parents or legal guardians must sign a written informed
             consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients will be excluded from this study if currently enrolled in another
             experimental treatment protocol or if receiving any other chemotherapy (either
             systemic or intrathecal).

          2. Pregnant or lactating female patients are ineligible

          3. Patients will be excluded from this study if they have received another
             investigational or chemotherapy agent within 14 days prior to study entry.

          4. Patients will be excluded from this study if they have any evidence of infection in
             any site at the time of considered enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>22 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Soumen Khatua, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Sandberg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary Tomaras, BS,CCRA,CCTM</last_name>
    <phone>713-606-0136</phone>
    <email>mtomaras@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Tomaras, BS,CCRA,CCTM</last_name>
      <phone>713-606-0136</phone>
      <email>mtomaras@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Memorial Hermann Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 23, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 27, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Malignant Fourth Ventricular Brain Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Ependymoma involving brain</keyword>
  <keyword>Ependymoma involving spine</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent ependymoma involving brain and/or spine</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor involving brain</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor involving spine</keyword>
  <keyword>AT/RT</keyword>
  <keyword>Ommaya reservoir catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>Methotrexate</keyword>
  <keyword>Medulloblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>ATRT</keyword>
  <keyword>Atypical teratoid rhabdoid tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Ependymoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Intraventricular chemotherapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
