<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="436">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01915303</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSOM230B2411</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01915303</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Pasireotide s.c. +/- Cabergoline in Patients With Cushing's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>MACS2125</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of Pasireotide s.c. Alone or in Combination With Cabergoline in Patients With Cushing's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Australia: National Health and Medical Research Council</authority>
    <authority>Brazil: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Colombia: National Institutes of Health</authority>
    <authority>Venezuela: Ministry of Health and Social Development</authority>
    <authority>India: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Turkey: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>Bulgaria: Bulgarian Drug Agency</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicinal Products and Health Products</authority>
    <authority>Hungary: National Institute of Pharmacy</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ethics Commission</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Greece: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Greece: Ministry of Health and Welfare</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ethics Committee</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>France: Comité consultatif sur le traitement de l'information en matière de recherche dans le domaine de la santé</authority>
    <authority>Italy: The Italian Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Argentina: Administracion Nacional de Medicamentos, Alimentos y Tecnologia Medica</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to assess whether pasireotide alone and combined with cabergoline will give
      reliefs on patients with recurrent, persistent and newly diagnosed Cushing's disease. The
      study will also assess study drug safety, the changes in Quality of Life and on clinical
      signs and symptoms of Cushing's disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is to assess whether pasireotide alone and combined with cabergoline will give
      reliefs on patients with recurrent, persistent and newly diagnosed Cushing's disease. The
      study will also assess study drug safety, the changes in Quality of Life and on clinical
      signs and symptoms of Cushing's disease. The study will enroll two groups of patients.
      Pasireotide naive patients at the time of screening (Group 1), and patients receiving
      maximal tolerated dose of pasireotide at the time of screening (Group 2).  Group 1 patients
      will begin study treatment of pasireotide at 0.6mg twice a day for 8 weeks. After 8 weeks,
      if cortisol level is not controlled and the dose is tolerated well, pasireotide will be
      increased to 0.9mg for another 8 weeks. If during or at the end of the 8 week period,
      cortisol level is still not controlled cabergoline will be added at 0.5mg once a day.
      Cabergoline can be increased up to 1.0mg once a day in combination with pasireotide. Group 2
      patients will immediately begin combination treatment by adding cabergoline at 0.5mg once a
      day to the current pasireotide treatment. Cabergoline dose can be increased up to 1.0mg once
      a day if cortisol is not controlled at a lower dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mUFC</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 35</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients who attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN at week 35 with pasireotide alone or in combination with cabergoline in Group 1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mUFC</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 17</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients who attain a mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN at week 17 with pasireotide with combination of cabergoline in Group 2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage change in mUFC from baseline to study end at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31, 35 for group 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage change in mUFC from baseline to study end at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured for Group 1 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31, 35 for group 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients that attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured for Group 1 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN or have at least 50% reduction from baseline in mUFC as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31, 35 for group 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients who attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN or have at least 50% reduction from baseline in mUFC as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured for Group 1 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of controlled or partially controlled response</measure>
    <time_frame>from the date patient's first normalization (mUFC ≤ 1.0xULN) or at least 50% reduction from baseline up to the date when the patient's mUFC &gt; 1.0 x ULN</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Duration of controlled or partially controlled response is defined as the period starting from the date of patient's first normalization (mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN) or at least 50% reduction from baseline up to the date when the patient's mUFC &gt; 1.0 x ULN and the reduction from baseline falls to less than 50% from the first time for Group 1 and Group 2 patients, separately</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in plasma ACTH and serum cortisol over time</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline visit and weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31 and 35 for group 1</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in plasma ACTH and serum cortisol over time for Group 1 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ctrough at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Ctrough at baseline for Group 2 patients only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ctrough at week 8</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Ctrough at week 8 for Group 2 patients only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ctrough</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 17</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Ctrough at week 17 for Group 2 patients only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Cmax at baseline for Group 2 patients only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax at week 8</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 8</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Cmax at week 8 for Group 2 patients only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 17</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Cmax at week 17 for Group 2 patients only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity will be assessed using NCI-CTCAE v.4 and for laboratory assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>at screening, baseline visits, and at weeks 4, 8, 13, 17, 22, 26, 31, 35 and study completion visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity will be assessed using NCI-CTCAE v.4 and for laboratory assessments that include biochemistry, hematology, urinalysis; special safety assessments that include the regular monitoring and recording of blood glucose insulin, HbA1c, GH and IGF-1, thyroid and liver function tests, gallbladder examinations and ECGs. Concomitant medications/significant non-drug therapies will be assessed too for group 1 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage change in mUFC from baseline to study end at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17 for group 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage change in mUFC from baseline to study end at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured for Group 1 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17 for group 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured for group 2 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN or have at least 50% reduction from baseline in mUFC as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured</measure>
    <time_frame>at weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17 for group 2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of patients who attain mUFC ≤ 1.0 x ULN or have at least 50% reduction from baseline in mUFC as assessed at each scheduled visit when UFC is measured for group 2 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in plasma ACTH and serum cortisol over time</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline visit and weeks 0, 4, 8, 13, 17</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in plasma ACTH and serum cortisol over time for group 2 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity will be assessed using NCI-CTCAE v.4 and for laboratory assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>at screening, baseline visits, and at weeks 4, 8, 13, 17 and study completion visit</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Toxicity will be assessed using NCI-CTCAE v.4 and for laboratory assessments that include biochemistry, hematology, urinalysis; special safety assessments that include the regular monitoring and recording of blood glucose insulin, HbA1c, GH and IGF-1, thyroid and liver function tests, gallbladder examinations and ECGs. Concomitant medications/significant non-drug therapies will be assessed too for group 2 patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">128</enrollment>
  <condition>Cushing's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1 consists of patients who are not treated with pasireotide at screening.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 2 consists of patients who are currently treated with maximal tolerated doses of pasireotide monotherapy at 0.3mg, 0.6mg or 0.9mg twice a day for at least 8 weeks, but still with elevated UFC.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pasireotide</intervention_name>
    <description>Group 1 consists of Pasireotide-untreated patients will start pasireotide 0.6mg twice a day for 8 weeks. If biochemical control is not achieved by the end of the 8 weeks, and the 0.6mg dose is well-tolerated, the dose will be increased to 0.9mg twice a day for another 8 weeks. If biochemical control is not achieved, cabergoline will be added and patients will begin combination treatment with cabergoline at the starting dose of 0.5mg once a day for 8 weeks. If biochemical control is still not achieved at the end of the third 8 week period, the dose of cabergoline wlil be increased to 1.0mg once a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cabergoline</intervention_name>
    <description>Group 2 patients will immediately start the combination treatment by adding cabergoline 0.5mg once a day at study entry to their current dose of pasireotide. Patients will continue with the combination treatment for 8 weeks. If biochemical control is not achieved by the end of the 8 week period, the dose of cabergoline will be increased to 1mg once a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria for Group 1:

          1. Adult patients with confirmed diagnosis of ACTH-dependent Cushing's disease as
             evidenced by all of the following:

               1. The mean of three 24-hour urine samples collected within 2 weeks &gt; 1xULN with 2
                  out of 3 samples &gt;ULN

               2. Morning plasma ACTH within the normal or above normal range

               3. Either MRI confirmation of pituitary adenoma &gt; 6 mm, or inferior petrosal sinus
                  gradient &gt;3 after CRH stimulation for those patients with a tumor less than or
                  equal to 6 mm*. For patients who have had prior pituitary surgery,
                  histopathology confirming an ACTH staining adenoma *If IPSS had previously been
                  performed without CRH (e.g. with DDAVP), then a central to peripheral
                  pre-stimulation gradient &gt; 2 is required. If IPSS had not previously been
                  performed, IPSS with CRH stimulation is required.

          2. Patients with de novo Cushing's disease can be included only if they are not
             considered candidates for pituitary surgery (e.g. poor surgical candidates,
             surgically unapproachable tumors, patients who refuse to have surgical treatment)

          3. Male or female patients aged 18 years or greater

          4. Karnofsky performance status ≥ 60 (i.e. requires occasional assistance, but is able
             to care for most of their personal needs)

          5. Patients on medical treatment for Cushing's disease the following washout periods
             must be completed before screening assessments are performed

               -  Inhibitors of steroidogenesis (ketoconazole, metyrapone): 1 week

               -  Pituitary directed agents: Dopamine agonists (bromocriptine, cabergoline) and
                  PPARγ agonists (rosiglitazone or pioglitazone): 4 weeks

               -  Octreotide LAR, Lanreotide SR and Lanreotide autogel: 14 weeks

               -  Octreotide (immediate release formulation): 1 week

               -  Progesterone receptor antagonist (mifepristone): 4 weeks

          6. Patients have been on pasireotide in the past but discontinued because of lack of
             efficacy are also allowed to enter Group 1. Patients treated with pasireotide
             subcutaneously must have been discontinued from the treatment for at least 4 weeks
             before screening. Patients treated with pasireotide LAR must have been discontinued
             from the treatment for at least 12 weeks before screening.

          7. Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, if they are using highly effective methods of contraception during
             dosing and for 30 days after stopping study medication.

        Inclusion criteria for Group 2:

          1. Adult patients with confirmed diagnosis of ACTH-dependent Cushing's disease as
             evidenced by all of the following:

               1. The mean of three 24-hour urine samples collected within 2 weeks &gt; 1xULN with 2
                  out of 3 samples &gt;ULN

               2. Morning plasma ACTH within the normal or above normal range

               3. Either MRI confirmation of pituitary adenoma &gt; 6 mm, or inferior petrosal sinus
                  gradient &gt;3 after CRH stimulation for those patients with a tumor less than or
                  equal to 6 mm*. For patients who have had prior pituitary surgery,
                  histopathology confirming an ACTH staining adenoma *If **IPSS had previously
                  been performed without CRH (e.g. with DDAVP), then a central to peripheral
                  pre-stimulation gradient &gt; 2 is required. If IPSS had not previously been
                  performed, IPSS with CRH stimulation is required.

          2. Patients with de novo Cushing's disease can be included only if they are not
             considered candidates for pituitary surgery (e.g. poor surgical candidates,
             surgically unapproachable tumors, patients who refuse to have surgical treatment)

          3. Patients currently treated with maximal tolerated doses of pasireotide for at least 8
             weeks at the time of screening but have not achieved biochemical control. These
             patients will enter the study starting combination therapy.

          4. Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, if they are using highly effective methods of contraception during
             dosing and for 30 days after stopping study medication.

        Exclusion criteria for Group 1 and Group 2:

          1. Patients with compression of the optic chiasm causing any visual field defect that
             requires surgical intervention

          2. Diabetic patients with poor glycemic control as evidenced by HbA1c &gt;8%

          3. Patients with risk factors for torsade de pointes, i.e. patients with a baseline QTcF
             &gt;450 ms in males, and &gt; 460 ms in females. hypokalemia, hypomagnesaemia, uncontrolled
             hypothyroidism, family history of long QT syndrome, or concomitant medications known
             to prolong QT interval.

          4. Patients with clinically significant valvular disease.

          5. Patients with Cushing's syndrome due to ectopic ACTH secretion

          6. Patients with hypercortisolism secondary to adrenal tumors or nodular (primary)
             bilateral adrenal hyperplasia

          7. Patients who have congestive heart failure (NYHA Class III or IV), unstable angina,
             sustained ventricular tachycardia, clinically significant bradycardia, advanced heart
             block, history of acute MI less than one year prior to study entry or clinically
             significant impairment in cardiovascular function

          8. Patients with liver disease such as cirrhosis, chronic active hepatitis, or chronic
             persistent hepatitis, or patients with ALT/AST &gt; 2 X ULN, serum bilirubin &gt;2.0 X ULN

          9. Patients with serum creatinine &gt;2.0 X ULN

         10. Patients with WBC &lt;3 X 10e9/L; Hb 90% &lt; LLN; PLT &lt;100 X 10e9/L
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-669-6682</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <phone_ext>+41613241111</phone_ext>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham The Kirklin Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Ferguson</last_name>
      <phone>+1 205 934 4112</phone>
      <email>susanf@uab.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tom Brooks Vaughan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars Sinai Medical Center SOM230B2411</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Billy Gellepis</last_name>
      <phone>310-423-3395</phone>
      <email>gellepisw@cshs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anat Ben-Shlomo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern Memorial Hospital SOM230B2411</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daphne Adelman</last_name>
      <phone>312-908-9002</phone>
      <email>d-adelman@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Molitch</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago Hospitals SOM230B2411</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>773-702-3853</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roy E. Weiss</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sinai Hospital of Baltimore SOM230B2411</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alanvin Orpia</last_name>
      <phone>410-601-0960</phone>
      <email>aorpia@lifebridgehealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Henry G. Fein</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University SOM230B2411</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shirley McCartney</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-4314</phone>
      <email>mccartns@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Fleseriu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mid South Endocrine Associates Midstate Endocrinology Assoc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Terri Jerkins</last_name>
      <email>twjerkins@aol.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Terri Jerkins</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buenos aires</city>
        <zip>C1120AAF</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buenos Aires</city>
        <zip>C1280AEB</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>RS</state>
        <zip>90560-030</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sofia</city>
        <zip>1431</zip>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bogotá</city>
        <zip>00000</zip>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bogotá</city>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest</city>
        <zip>29200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron Cedex</city>
        <zip>69677</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille cedex 05</city>
        <zip>13385</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac Cedex</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vandoeuvre Cedex</city>
        <zip>54511</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <zip>91054</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <zip>45147</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Würzburg</city>
        <zip>97080</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>GR 54635</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mumbai</city>
        <state>Maharashtra</state>
        <zip>400012</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <zip>110 029</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ancona</city>
        <state>AN</state>
        <zip>60126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>MI</state>
        <zip>20149</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Padova</city>
        <state>PD</state>
        <zip>35128</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <zip>80131</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wilayah Persekutuan</city>
        <zip>62502</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Málaga</city>
        <state>Andalucia</state>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alzira</city>
        <state>Comunidad Valenciana</state>
        <zip>46600</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <zip>34303</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izmir</city>
        <zip>35340</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pendik / Istanbul</city>
        <zip>1330</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sihhiye/Ankara</city>
        <zip>06100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caracas</city>
        <state>Distrito Capital</state>
        <zip>1010</zip>
        <country>Venezuela</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Argentina</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Bulgaria</country>
    <country>Colombia</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
    <country>Venezuela</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 8, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cushing's disease, pituitary tumors, pasireotide, cabergoline, combination treatment, UFC, hormone disorder, cortisol, adrenocorticotropic hormone</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cushing Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary ACTH Hypersecretion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenocorticotropic Hormone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cabergoline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
