<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="107">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on October 24, 2013</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01904123</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0358</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01904123</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Trial of WP1066</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of WP1066 in Patients With Central Nervous System (CNS) Melanoma and Recurrent Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find the highest tolerable dose of WP1066
      that can be given to patients with recurrent cancerous brain tumors or melanoma that has
      spread to the brain.  The safety of this drug will also be studied.

      WP1066 is designed to target the STAT3 pathway in cancer cells, which makes these cells
      divide, increases new blood vessels to the tumor, causes the cancer cells to move throughout
      the body and brain, and avoids them being detected by the immune system.  Targeting this
      pathway may cause the immune system to kill the cancer cells.

      This is the first study using WP1066 in humans.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be assigned to a study
      group based on when you join this study.  Up to 6 groups of 1-6 participants will be
      enrolled in Part 1 of the study, and up to 6 participants will be enrolled in Part 2.

      If you are enrolled in Part 1, the dose of WP1066 you receive will depend on when you joined
      this study.  The first group of participants will receive the lowest dose level of WP1066.
      Each new group will receive a higher dose of WP1066 than the group before it, if no
      intolerable side effects were seen.  This will continue until the highest tolerable dose of
      WP1066 is found.

      If you are enrolled in Part 2, you will receive WP1066 at the highest dose that was
      tolerated in Part 1.

      Study Drug Administration:

      You will take WP1066 by mouth 1 time per day on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday of Weeks 1 and
      2 of each 28-day cycle.  For 2 hours before and 2 hours after each dose, you must fast (have
      nothing to eat or drink except water).

      If you miss a dose, you may take it within 24 hours.  However, if it has been more than 24
      hours since when you were supposed to take WP1066, you will need to contact the study
      doctor.

      For the first and last dose of Cycle 1, you will take WP1066 in the clinic so that timed
      blood tests can be done.  If you are the first enrolled participant in a study group, you
      will be watched for 1 hour after your first dose in Cycle 1, and your vital signs will be
      checked every 15 minutes.

      The study doctor may decide to lower your dose of the study drug if you have side effects.

      You will write down the times of your doses of WP1066 in a study drug diary that will be
      given to you.  You should bring the diary to the clinic at the end of each cycle.

      Study Visits:

      At every visit, you will be asked about any new drugs you may be taking, including vitamins,
      herbs, and supplements.  You will also be asked about any changes in your health, how you
      feel, and any side effects you may be having.

      On Day 1 of Cycle 1:

        -  You will have a physical and neurological exam, including measurement of your vital
           signs and weight.

        -  Your performance status will be recorded.

        -  Blood (up to 6 tablespoons) and urine will be collected for routine tests.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons each time) will be drawn for pharmacokinetic (PK) testing
           before receiving WP1066 and 8 times during the 10 hours after the dose.  PK testing
           measures the amount of study drug in the body at different time points.

        -  You will have an EKG to check your heart function.

      On Day 2 of Cycle 1, blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for PK testing.

      On Day 8 of Cycle 1, blood (up to 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      On Day 14 of Cycle 1, blood (about 2 teaspoons each time) will be drawn for PK testing
      before receiving WP1066 and 8 times during the 10 hours after the dose.

      On Day 15 of Cycle 1, blood (about 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for PK testing and routine
      tests.

      On Day 22 of Cycle 1 and Days 8, 15, and 22 of Cycle 2, blood (up to 6 tablespoons) will be
      drawn for routine tests.

      On Day 1 of Cycle 2:

        -  You will have a physical and neurological exam, including measurement of your vital
           signs and weight.

        -  Your performance status will be recorded.

        -  Blood (up to 6 tablespoons) and urine will be collected for routine tests.

        -  You will have an EKG to check your heart function.

      On Day 1 of Cycles 3 and beyond:

        -  You will have a physical and neurological exam, including measurement of your vital
           signs and weight.

        -  Your performance status will be recorded.

        -  Blood (up to 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      Every 8 weeks, you will have an MRI to check the status of the disease.

      Every 12 weeks, if you have melanoma, you will have a CT scan of the chest, abdomen, and
      pelvis to check the status of the disease.

      If the study doctor thinks it is needed, certain tests may be repeated at other times.

      If it is more convenient, you can have your blood and urine collections for routine tests
      done at your local clinic or lab instead of at MD Anderson.

      If you need to have surgery to remove the tumor or have a tumor biopsy performed for routine
      care, any leftover tumor tissue will be tested to learn if the immune system has responded
      to the study drug and to find out if STAT3 is in the tumor.

      Length of Study Drug Dosing:

      You may continue taking the study drug for as long as the doctor thinks it is in your best
      interest.  You will no longer be able to take the study drug if the disease gets worse, if
      intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the follow-up visits.

      Follow-Up Visits:

      At 1 and 2 months after your last study drug dose:

        -  You will be asked about any changes in your health, how you feel, and any side effects
           you may be having.

        -  You will have a physical and neurological exam, including measurement of your vital
           signs and weight.

        -  Your performance status will be recorded.

        -  Blood (up to 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      This is an investigational study.  WP1066 is not FDA approved or commercially available.  It
      is currently being used for research purposes only.

      Up to 21 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of WP1066</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is dose level at which 0/6 or 1/6 patients experience a dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) with at least 2 patients experiencing DLT at next higher dose level. Dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) defined as an adverse event or an abnormal laboratory value assessed as being at least possibly related to the investigation agent that occurs during the first 28 days after administration of the first dose of WP1066 and will be assigned a grade based on NIH CTC-defined toxicity criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>WP1066</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each 28 day cycle consists of two weeks of treatment with WP1066 administered on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday followed by a two-week cycle of no administration. Dose escalation in the Phase I portion of the trial will proceed according to an Accelerated Titration Design followed by a 3 + 3 design algorithm.  Phase I starting dose of WP1066 0.08 mg by mouth 1 time per day on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday of Weeks 1 and 2 of each 28-day cycle.  Phase II starting dose maximum tolerated dose from Phase I.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WP1066</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I starting dose: 0.08 mg by mouth 1 time per day on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday of Weeks 1 and 2 of each 28-day cycle.
Phase II starting dose: Maximum tolerated dose from Phase I.</description>
    <arm_group_label>WP1066</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have histologically confirmed melanoma that is metastatic to the brain
             or recurrent glioblastoma multiforme for which standard curative or palliative
             measures do not exist or are no longer effective.

          2. Patients must have measurable disease in the CNS, defined as at least one lesion that
             can be accurately measured in at least one dimension as &gt;5 mm by brain magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI). MRI is to have been performed (with and without gadolinium
             enhancement) of the brain using both 3-mm contiguous slices and standard 5-mm slices
             with 2.5-mm spacing for comparison to subsequent MRI scans.

          3. In the case of GBM patients, they must have previously undergone standard-of-care
             treatment including surgery, radiation, and treatment with temozolomide prior to the
             experimental treatment (WP1066). In the case of melanoma patients with CNS
             metastasis, they may have previously undergone a resection (with radiographic
             evidence of progression), have undergone Gamma Knife radiosurgery (with radiographic
             evidence of progression), or have been treated with other systemic therapies that
             failed.

          4. Age &gt;18 years. Because no dosing or adverse event data are currently available on the
             use of WP1066 in patients &lt;18 years of age, children are excluded from this study.

          5. ECOG performance status &lt;2, Karnofsky Performance Scale score &gt;60%, and a Curran
             Group status of I-IV for malignant glioma patients.

          6. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:  leukocytes
             &gt;3,000/mcL, absolute neutrophil count &gt;1,000/mcL, platelets &gt;50,000/mcL, total
             bilirubin within normal institutional limits, AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) &lt;2.5 X
             institutional upper limit of normal, creatinine within normal institutional limits,
             OR creatinine clearance &gt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above
             institutional normal, PT/PTT &lt;1.5 x normal institutional standard.

          7. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
             document.

          8. Melanoma patients must be intolerant of, or have disease that has proven refractory
             to approved therapies that have been shown to improve overall survival such as
             vemurafenib for BRAF mutation-positive metastatic melanoma and Ipilimumab for
             metastatic melanoma.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas) prior to entering the study or those who have not recovered from
             adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier. Biological
             agents, immune modulators, and targeted therapeutic approaches require a 2-week
             washout window.

          2. Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents require a 4 week washout
             period. Patients who have received cellular or gene therapy at any time are not
             eligible.

          3. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to WP1066.

          4. The enzymatic metabolism profile of WP1066 is unknown. Patients who are receiving
             drugs that significantly interact with the CYP450 enzyme(s) are ineligible. However,
             if they are switched to other medications with a 2-week washout window, they will be
             eligible. Patients are also excluded if they have been exposed within 7 days of
             planned first study treatment day to mediations that are predominantly CYP2D6, 2C9 or
             2C19 substrates, strong inhibitors or inducers, and sensitive substrates of CYP3A4
             with narrow therapeutic range.

          5. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          6. No single lesion can be larger than 3 cm in maximal diameter, be causing focal
             neurological symptoms or resulting in a GCS of less than 15. At MDACC, the
             neurosurgeons do not routinely administer steroids to patients with small,
             asymptomatic CNS metastases.

          7. The effects of WP1066 on the developing human fetus are unknown. Pregnant women are
             excluded from this study because WP1066 could potentially be teratogenic or have
             abortifacient effects. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse
             events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with WP1066,
             breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is treated with WP0166. Women of
             child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or
             barrier method of birth control: abstinence) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she should inform
             her treating physician immediately. Men treated or enrolled on this protocol must
             also agree to use adequate contraception prior to the study, for the duration of
             study participation, and 4 months after completion of WP1066 administration.

          8. HIV-positive patients receiving combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible
             because of the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with WP1066.

          9. Patients who have received bevacizumab at any point in their treatment course are not
             eligible.

         10. The potential for further hemorrhaging with the use of WP1066 is unknown.
             Furthermore, because melanoma CNS metastases commonly hemorrhage, toxicity may be
             inappropriately attributed to WP1066 in this setting. It will be at the PIs
             discretion to enroll a patient who has a small, asymptomatic CNS hemorrhage, but
             patients who have had symptomatic hemorrhages will be excluded.

         11. Patients requiring escalation of the corticosteroid dose will be excluded, but
             patients receiving a stable dose for at least one week will be eligible.

         12. Because one of the study parameters is PFS based on radiographic volumetric analysis
             of the tumor, the presence of diffuse leptomeningeal disease will be an exclusion
             criterion for this study. This is secondary to the inadequacy of measuring the extent
             of the tumor burden within this setting and the very poor prognosis of these
             patients.

         13. The cardiac toxicities of WP1066 are unknown. Thus, patients who have a mean QTc
             interval &gt;450 ms at base line will be excluded. Concomitant use of agents that
             prolong the QT interval will be avoided.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Heimberger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amy Heimberger, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-8717</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Central nervous system neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>CNS</keyword>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma Multiforme</keyword>
  <keyword>GBM</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic to the brain</keyword>
  <keyword>WP1066</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
